<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The glory of free grace display'd: or, The transcendant excellency of the love of God in Christ, unto believing, repenting sinners, in some measure describ'd Wherein, 1. The doctrine about election, and the covenant of reconciliation is explained. 2. The error of the antinomians, who assert, that the filth of sin was laid on Christ, and that the holiness as well as the righteousness of Christ is made the elects while in the womb, &amp;c. With their abuse of free-grace particularly detected and confuted. 3. In what sense our sins were laid on Christ, and Christ's righteousness made the believers, according to the sacred scriptures, evinced. 4. The glory of irresistible-grace, as exerted in the conversion of a sinner in opposition to the Arminian, cleared. 5. A modest defence of the sober dominican, about physical predetermination.</title>
            <author>Lobb, Stephen, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 243 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2724B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218819</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830376</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830376</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34827</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34827)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2073:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The glory of free grace display'd: or, The transcendant excellency of the love of God in Christ, unto believing, repenting sinners, in some measure describ'd Wherein, 1. The doctrine about election, and the covenant of reconciliation is explained. 2. The error of the antinomians, who assert, that the filth of sin was laid on Christ, and that the holiness as well as the righteousness of Christ is made the elects while in the womb, &amp;c. With their abuse of free-grace particularly detected and confuted. 3. In what sense our sins were laid on Christ, and Christ's righteousness made the believers, according to the sacred scriptures, evinced. 4. The glory of irresistible-grace, as exerted in the conversion of a sinner in opposition to the Arminian, cleared. 5. A modest defence of the sober dominican, about physical predetermination.</title>
                  <author>Lobb, Stephen, d. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 118, [2], xxii, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T. S. for B. Alsop, at the Angel and Bible against the stocks-market,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Stephen Lobb.</note>
                  <note>Includes errata page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Dr. Williams' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34827:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The GLORY of Free-Grace DISPLAY'D: Or, The Tranſcendent
Excellency of the Love of God in Chriſt, unto Believing, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting Sinners,
in ſome meaſure deſcrib'd. WHEREIN,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Doctrine about <hi>Election,</hi> and the
<hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Reconciliation</hi> is Explained.</item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Error</hi> of the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> who
aſſert, That the <hi>Filth</hi> of Sin was laid on Chriſt, and that the
<hi>Holineſs</hi> as well as the <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> of Chriſt is
made the Elects while in the Womb, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With their Abuſe of
FREE-GRACE particularly detected and confuted.</item>
                  <item>3. In what ſenſe our <hi>Sins</hi> were laid on
Chriſt, and Chriſt's Righteouſneſs made the Believers, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to
the Sacred Scriptures, evinced.</item>
                  <item>4. The Glory of <hi>Irreſiſtible-Grace,</hi> as exerted
in the Converſion of a Sinner in oppoſition to the <hi>Arminian,</hi>
cleared.</item>
                  <item>5. A modeſt Defence of the ſober <hi>Dominican,</hi>
about <hi>Phyſical Predetermination.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.S.</hi> for <hi>B. Alſop,</hi>
at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> againſt the <hi>Stocks-market.</hi>
1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:34827:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34827:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to the well-meaning but weak READER, who is moſt
liable to the being tainted with the Errors which are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the
following Diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>THE deſign of the enſuing Diſcourſe, is to enlighten
<hi>Thee</hi> concerning the true Notion of <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> which contains
in it diſcoveries of <hi>Divine Love</hi> to the <hi>greateſt</hi> of
<hi>Sinners;</hi> and, which is <hi>then</hi> illuſtrated in its fulleſt
glory, <hi>when</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended towards <hi>ſuch,</hi> as are affected with
the dreadfulneſs of their loſt eſtate, as out of Chriſt: For, whatever
ſome may ſuggeſt, none but <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced Sinners,</hi> are capable of
entertaining right conceptions of <hi>Goſpel-Grace.</hi> An <hi>Unconvinced
Sinner,</hi> cannot in any ſaving meaſure underſtand, much leſs
comprehend the glory of this myſtery; for whoever would be ſavingly
acquainted with <hi>it,</hi> muſt know, and believe, that <hi>ſo many,</hi>
and <hi>ſo great</hi> are his tranſgreſſions, that, unleſs he be made
the <hi>object</hi> thereof, he is eternally undone. Whence 'tis
impoſſible, that any ſhould diſcover unto Thee the <hi>true Notion</hi>
of this <hi>Grace,</hi> and not at the ſame time ſhew, who are the
<hi>proper objects</hi> of it: Nor can any ſhew who are the <hi>proper
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> of it, unleſs they acquaint Thee with the <hi>ſtate</hi> of
thoſe perſons, that ſhall be made the actual par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers thereof, which
cannot be without an inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<pb facs="tcp:34827:3"/>on the greatneſs of both the
ſin and miſery of all ſuch: for <hi>Grace</hi> is to the
<hi>miſerable,</hi> to thoſe, who in the ſenſe of ſin, labour, and
are heavy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; and therefore the <hi>firſt</hi> work of a Goſpel
Miniſter, is to preach up <hi>Repentance</hi> towards God, and <hi>then
Faith</hi> in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Yea, we muſt <hi>firſt,</hi> (if
we will be faithful) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with your ſin, and your danger,
aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you, that although you were from eternity <hi>elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> your
ſins were not <hi>actually</hi> in God's ſight par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned from
<hi>eternity,</hi> nor from the <hi>day</hi> of Chriſt's death, nor from the
<hi>time</hi> you were firſt conceived in the womb; for every <hi>Elect
Soul,</hi> while under the reigning power of <hi>Unbelief,</hi> and other
Luſts, is <hi>unpardoned,</hi> and in a ſtate of condemnation; whence
notwithſtanding your election, if you would receive an <hi>actual
pardon,</hi> you muſt go to God <hi>through Chriſt</hi> for it; yea, you
muſt receive Chriſt in your hearts by Faith; and that you may, we muſt
beſeech you, as in Chriſt's ſtead, that you <hi>come</hi> unto Chriſt;
but <hi>come</hi> unto Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Faith</hi> and
<hi>Repentance,</hi> you cannot; for our <hi>coming</hi> unto Chriſt, is our
<hi>believing</hi> in the Lord Chriſt, which believing includes Goſpel
Repentance, which cannot be without conviction of Sin.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of <hi>Free-Grace</hi> thus rightly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is a
Point of the higheſt Concern to all the Children of Fallen Man, leading us
unto a due cloſing with ſuch other <hi>Truths,</hi> as are alſo of very
<pb facs="tcp:34827:3"/>great importance, viz. <hi>The neceſſity of conviction of
ſin, in order to a right believing;</hi> and of that <hi>Faith,</hi> which
<hi>includes in it the entire Principle of Goſpel Repentance,</hi> as
antecedent <hi>unto our actual juſtification</hi> in <hi>God's ſight.</hi>
All which <hi>Goſpel Truths,</hi> how neceſſary ſoever to ſalvation,
are ſadly neglected by <hi>ſuch,</hi> as underſtand not the Scripture
Notion of <hi>Free-Grace;</hi> which being ſo, I have thought my ſelf the
more oblig'd to do my utmost for thy relief, who art in danger of being drawn
aſide, not only to the contemning the but now mentioned Truths, but moreover
to an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining many a <hi>Dangerous Error,</hi> concerning our Lord
Jeſus Christ, as if <hi>he</hi> bore not only the <hi>Guilt</hi> and
<hi>Puniſhment,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Filth</hi> of our Sin; and as if what
the Lord Jeſus hath <hi>done</hi> for the Church, would exempt the
<hi>Elect</hi> from the <hi>neceſſity</hi> there is of their <hi>Repenting,
Believing</hi> and <hi>Rendring a ſincere Obedience to the end of their
Lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe,</hi> and many other Errors, that are but too firmly
linkt unto 'em, are of different miſchievous influences; ſome tending to
the diſcountenancing Holineſs, as others do to the advancing
Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a gratifying the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> all which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
what I have already done, I will, for thy greater Caution, particularly
evince.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Errors</hi> I oppoſe greatly
<hi>diſcountenance Holineſs;</hi> for Juſtification, and a right to
Glory, depending meerly upon an eternal, but ſecret De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree,<pb facs="tcp:34827:4"/>according unto them, the Elect are juſtified actually in God's
ſight, at least, as ſoon as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their <hi>Beings</hi> in the
womb; whence the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of Sin,</hi> or that <hi>Faith,</hi> which
includes in it the Principle of Goſpel Repentance, <hi>is no way a
neceſſary antecedent unto this Juſtification;</hi> and conſequently, if
the Elect be unconcern'd about the knowledge of their Election, they are ſafe
enough, although they mind not Religion in its pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Profane</hi> are as much <hi>encouraged,</hi>
who, confidently perſuading themſelves that their ſins are pardoned, or,
who concluding that their <hi>Sentence</hi> in the Court of Heaven is
<hi>already paſt,</hi> their <hi>Piety</hi> cannot better their ſtate, nor
their <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> any way conduce to the making it the
<hi>worſe,</hi> and theref<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re
contemn God and true Religion. I knew as great a <hi>Debauchee,</hi> as theſe
times afford, who, reading Mr. <hi>Saltmarſhe</hi>'s Book, had arrived to a
ſtrange aſſurance that his ſins were pardoned; and that although he
lived under the prevalency of his luſts, and was <hi>confeſſedly a vile
wretch,</hi> yet, he being ſo <hi>fully</hi> perſuaded both of his
<hi>Election,</hi> and <hi>Juſtification,</hi> knew, as he ſaid, that he
ſhould be eternally happy, although he ſhould dye in that ſtate. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Theſe <hi>Errors</hi> gratifie the <hi>Papiſts</hi>
as much, and that on a twofold account.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that <hi>ſome,</hi> (to wit, two or three)
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> aſſert, That the <hi>Filth</hi> of Sin was laid on
<pb facs="tcp:34827:4"/>Chriſt, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> judge themſelves ſufficiently
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to reproach all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as a People, whoſe
<hi>Heretical Opinions,</hi> are moſt odious, caſting the Lord of Life
under the vileſt of Calumnies. Thus <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> de <hi>Juſtif.
l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>lit. H. &amp;c.</hi> would prove, That we make
Chriſt a <hi>real Sinner.</hi>—Ergo poterit <hi>Chriſtus</hi> dici
<hi>verè peccator,</hi> &amp;, quod horret animus cogitare, <hi>Filius
Diaboli.—Illy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus</hi> in confeſ. Antuerpien. c. 6. &amp; in Apol.
ejuſd. admits (ſaith <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>) that Chriſt may be ſaid to
be <hi>moſt truly a Sinner,</hi> by the imputation of the Father, and his own
voluntary reception of their ſins on himſelf, to which he adds, But this
their <hi>Blaſphemous</hi> and <hi>Sacrilegious Impudence</hi> contradicts
the whole Scripture. Whether this <hi>Illyricus</hi> were of the
<hi>Antinomian</hi> Opinion, or not, I'll not now enquire; for nothing more
ſure, than that <hi>he</hi> embraced <hi>Errors</hi> of a <hi>dangerous
tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</hi> But by this we may ſee, How the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are
gratified by ſuch Doctrines as theſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Antinomians,</hi> not clearly diſtinguiſhing
between the <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Filth</hi> of Sin, (as I have ſhewn both
in the Body of the <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> and in the <hi>Appendix</hi>) give
great advantages unto ſome <hi>Popiſh</hi> Errors.</p>
            <p>For theſe Reaſons I have been the more careful in my
endeavors, that thou, by coming to the <hi>knowledge</hi> of the Truth,
may'ſt be freed from the miſchiefs thou art liable unto, by a too fixed
adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring unto Error. Yea, the ſaving thy ſoul from<pb facs="tcp:34827:5"/>Errer, and
the ruinous conſequences thereof, is my aim in this <hi>Eſſay;</hi> It
being <hi>Grievous</hi> to conſider, that any <hi>Well-meaning
Profeſſors,</hi> in this <hi>day,</hi> and <hi>land</hi> of <hi>light,</hi>
ſhould be tempted to abandon <hi>ſo neceſſary</hi> an <hi>Article</hi>
of the <hi>Proteſtant Doctrine,</hi> and inſtead thereof, embrace an
Opinion that ſo much diſcountenanceth Holineſs, that ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Profaneſs, yea, and ſo much
gratifies the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſts, who are the
great Enemies to our bleſſed J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>; and who are, at this time, attempting our <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ine,</hi> by their bringing us into a
ſtrange confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, reviving old
Errors, ſetting Proteſtant againſt
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roteſtant, and by their
ſcurrilous Pamphlets pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the People to believe, that the greateſt
Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Popery, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> are vile
enough to perpetrate ſuch Villanies as are abhorred by none as much as by
them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> That thou may'ſt not, contrary to the honeſt
inclinations of thy Soul, be drawn unto theſe deſtructive Errors, I have
written the enſuing Treatiſe, deſiring, that thou wouldeſt
ſeriouſly peruſe it; and that thou may'ſt do ſo, to thine own profit,
ſhall be my Prayer unto the Lord, who is able, and I truſt, who will bring
thee to the knowledge of the Truth, as it is in Jeſus.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
               <dateline>From my Study.
<date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 24. 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34827:5"/>The Glory of FREE-GRACE Diſplayed: OR The
Tranſcendent Excellency of the Love of God in Chriſt unto Believing,
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting Sinners, in ſome meaſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Introduction. The Method propoſed. What the Grace of God is,
in ſhort explicated.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THis is a Subject that abounds with its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, affording matter
of the greateſt comforts, unto ſuch, as are of <hi>truly broken,</hi> and
<hi>contrite ſpirits.</hi> A Soul, who has been ſavingly convinced of
ſin, and conſequently, of its loſt<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34827:6"/>condition, while in a
State of Nature, cannot but be greatly refreſhed at the believing medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
of the <hi>Fulneſs</hi> and <hi>Freeneſs</hi> of <hi>the Grace of God in
Chriſt.</hi> What is it, that can raiſe the diſtreſſed conſcience
of him, who doth firmly believe, that he ſinned in <hi>Adam,</hi> and by
that, and many another hainous actual iniquity, hath incurr'd Divine
diſpleaſure, what, I ſay, can ſo much relieve the diſtreſſed
conſcience of ſuch an one, as the knowledge of, and Faith in the
<hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Grace in Chriſt unto all ſuch?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis <hi>glorious Grace,</hi> that alone can prove tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
advantagious, and reviving to the <hi>humble ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> About which,
ſome lying under great <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance,</hi> as others do <hi>under dangerous
miſtakes,</hi> I will attempt to ſpeak ſomwhat, (as the Lord ſhall help
me,) for the inlightening the minds of men concerning it; that ſo, ſuch, to
whom comforts belong, may rejoyce, and glory in God their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, even, when
unhumbled, bold and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſinners, may ſee the greateſt
reaſons, why, they ought to mourn, and be in bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for that,
<hi>while ſo,</hi> they are not actually partakers of this Grace.</p>
            <p>But, before I engage in a diſcourſe of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, 'twill be
abſolutely neceſſary, that I cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the the Reader, againſt any
expectations of a <hi>full diſplay</hi> of this grace, it being far beyond
the heart of man to conceive, or the tongue of Angels to expreſs, the full
glory thereof. The<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34827:6"/>contrivance is ſo profound, that though
the Angels of God may prie into it, they cannot Fathom its depths, how much
leſs then can Man, to whom it may be ſaid, Canſt thou by ſearching find
out this <hi>Grace,</hi> canſt thou find out what is infinite unto
perfection? It is as high as Heaven, what canſt thou do? the meaſure
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is longer than the Earth, and broader than the Sea, what canſt thou
know? thou mayeſt cry out; Oh what is the <hi>length,</hi> and
<hi>breadth</hi> and <hi>depth</hi> and <hi>height</hi> of the love of God,
which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth knowledg! <hi>O how unſearchable are the riches of this
Grace!</hi> but to comprehend, or compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſively to deſcribe it is
impoſſible. For who ever would obtain <hi>adequate conceptions</hi> of it,
muſt ravel into the eternal counſels of God, and ſearch into that
<hi>wiſe</hi> invention, which was the product of an eternal conſultation,
between the Father and the Son, or otherwiſe he can but ſtand <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing,
admiring</hi> and <hi>wondering</hi> at ſuch diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, it hath
pleaſed the Lord in infinite mercy to vouchſafe us. Expect not then a
<hi>full diſplay</hi> of this glory, but in this <hi>treatiſe</hi> be
ſatisfied with ſuch hints, as the leaſt of the Lords Servants can give
thee, looking into the writings of the more learned, and judicious on this
Subject, but eſpecially into the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> where an inlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
underſtanding may ſee more, than he is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of revealing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:34827:7"/>Reader, having given thee this caution, I'le not
detain thee any longer, from what I princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally deſign, but will immediately
attempt the giving thee in ſhort, the plaineſt, cleareſt and moſt full
account I can of this <hi>grace,</hi> in this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing method. I'le
ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What the Grace of God is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>How</hi> or <hi>in what reſpect</hi> 'tis
<hi>magnified</hi> and <hi>exalted,</hi> and in doing ſo, diſcover
<hi>how</hi> and <hi>in what regards,</hi> the <hi>Grace</hi> of God is turned
into <hi>wantonneſs</hi> by many, to the great reproach of God and his glory
with the due improvement we ought to make of every Inſtance of
Free-Grace.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is the <hi>Grace of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, The <hi>Grace of God</hi> may be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after a
twofold manner.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As 'tis <hi>in God,</hi> and ſo tis <hi>God
himſelf</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to favour, and do good unto the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<hi>FREELY,</hi> without a reſpect to any <hi>merit</hi> or <hi>deſert</hi>
in him. Or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. It may be taken for <hi>the good thing it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> freely given unto the creature,
which is but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>effect</hi> of
the former, to wit, of that grace tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is in God. Here it muſt be duly minded,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Grace,</hi> which is now to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>played,
is <hi>the Grace which is in God:</hi> The <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vine Will</hi> it ſelf
inclining to favour man mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> freely,
which grace, as 'tis in God, is a <hi>prope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion,<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34827:7"/>inclination</hi> or
<hi>diſpoſition</hi> of <hi>his Will</hi> to <hi>do good,</hi> or <hi>God
himſelf thus diſpoſed,</hi> and inclined to ſhew mercy, or 'tis <hi>God
himſelf willing, purpoſing</hi> or <hi>determining to make known</hi> the
<hi>greatneſs of his goodneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Object</hi> of this Grace is <hi>man.</hi> (For I
deſign not to mention the <hi>Grace</hi> ſhewn the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> but to
<hi>Man,</hi>) as he is uncapable of <hi>meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the leaſt inſtance</hi>
of Divine Love, yea <hi>Man,</hi> as he hath by his ſin incurr'd the juſt
diſpleaſure of Almighty God. <hi>Grace</hi> then is God himſelf
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining, or rather <hi>purpoſing</hi> and <hi>determining</hi> to ſhew
favour <hi>freely; freely, (i e)</hi> becauſe he <hi>will, God will have
mercy on whom he will have mercy,</hi> yea, and becauſe he <hi>will</hi> have
mercy. For an act of grace is moſt <hi>Sovereign and free,</hi> and God, who
is the abſolute Lord of all things, <hi>doth diſpoſe</hi> of all things
<hi>freely,</hi> that is, as he <hi>will.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. This <hi>Grace,</hi> that is in God, is diſcovered unto
us in its <hi>effects,</hi> even in that the <hi>gracious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns,
purpoſes</hi> and <hi>determinations</hi> of God, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, and
the <hi>good</hi> intended, is actually given out unto the undeſerving
creature, whence the <hi>greate things graciouſly</hi> done, the <hi>good
things mercifully vouchſafed unto the children of men, at ſundry
times,</hi> in <hi>divers ways</hi> and <hi>manners,</hi> do moſt excellently
repreſent unto us that <hi>Grace,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:34827:8"/>that is in God. Which
being ſo, who ever will, in any meaſure, <hi>diſplay</hi> the Grace of
God, muſt not only acquaint you, with the <hi>eternal deſigns of
grace,</hi> but, alſo with the <hi>effects of ſuch deſigns,</hi> the
<hi>great things done</hi> and <hi>actually given out unto thoſe,</hi> for
whom they are prepared<note n="*" place="bottom">[The Schoolmen do
diſtinguiſh between the grace, <hi>Quae in Deo reſidet, et quae à
Deo data eſt. Gratia quae in Deo reſidet eſt ipſa voluntas Divina ſeu
Dei beneplacitum.</hi> The <hi>Gratia à Deo data</hi> is the
<hi>beneficium datum ſeu donum habituale.</hi> About which the Proteſtants
and Papiſts greatly differ, although the <hi>Popiſh Schoolmen</hi> have
ſaid enough to juſtify the Proteſtant Doctors: The difference lieth in
this Our Divines do call the Grace, <hi>quae in Deo reſidet, Gratia gratum
faciens,</hi> but the <hi>Papiſts</hi> call the Grace, <hi>quae data eſt
à Deo</hi> by that name, So <hi>Durand</hi> l. 3. diſ. 13. q.
1.—<hi>alio modo accipitur gratia pro aliquo dono creato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et</hi> 6.
<hi>te hoc dividitur in Gratiam gratum facientem et Gratiam gratis datam.
Gratia gratum faciens perficit hominem in ſe, et ad meritum perſonale.
Gratia verò gratis data Ordinatur ad utilitatem eccleſiae, ut donum
linguarum,</hi> &amp;c.—In like manner <hi>Bellarmine de grat. et lib.
arb. l.</hi> 1. C. 2. <hi>Partitio gratiae tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae eſt in gratiam gratis
datam et gratiam gratum facientem.</hi> But that which is ſtill
conſiderable is, that they muſt acknowledge the truth, for which we plead.
For ſaies <hi>Durand. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſupra. Gratia du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter ſumitur, uno modo
pro acceptatione divina, et ſio gratia non dicit aliquid ſubjectivè
in homine grato; ſed eſt denominatio extrinſeca ab actu divino. Alio modo
accipitur Gratia pro aliquo dono.</hi> And <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> like in manner.
<hi>Prima partitio eſt in Gratiam eternam, et temporariam; Gratia eterna ille
eſt amor, quo nos dilexit Deus ante mundi conſtitutionem, Ab ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa
aeternitate dilexit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gratia temporaria dicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur beneficia
vocationis et justificationis quae ex aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na gratia ut effectus ex cauſa
derivantur. So plain they are in their
conceſſions.</hi>]</note>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:34827:8"/>
            <head>CHAP. II.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>In what reſpects the Grace of God is diſplayed. Grace to Man
in innocency only hinted. Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grace the firſt inſtance, this Grace
explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, confirmed and IMPROVED.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN ſhewing <hi>how,</hi> it hath pleaſed the Lord to make a
Glorious diſplay of his Grace, I ſhall not ſpeak all, that may be ſaid,
nor inſiſt on every particular, which thoſe would, that deſign large
treatiſes, but reſolving to be ſhort, I will confine my ſelf to ſuch
things as do in a more eſpecial manner, ſet forth, and illuſtrate the
<hi>Glory</hi> of this Grace.</p>
            <p>I might inſiſt on that great inſtance of Grace, which,
according to the <hi>eternal counſel of God,</hi> was given us all in
<hi>Adam,</hi> in that we were <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated</hi> after Gods own <hi>Image,</hi>
in <hi>Knowledge, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> and true <hi>Holineſs,</hi> at
which time Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs was not only <hi>concreated with us,</hi> but
created as that which was <hi>connatural unto us,</hi> whereby, Man was capable
without the <hi>help</hi> of<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34827:9"/>any <hi>ſuperadded grace,</hi>
ſupernatural to that ſtate of integrity and perfection, to render the
requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red obedience, that was neceſſary to the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a further
happineſs, when man was alſo made the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Sovereign</hi>
of this lower crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, having received a <hi>right</hi> to all the Glory of
this world, in that there was <hi>but</hi> the <hi>propriety unto</hi> and
<hi>uſe of one only tree denyed him. This</hi> is an <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
inſtance of Free-Grace,</hi> in that man was in his <hi>firſt-make,</hi>
ſo noble a creature, much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the brutes and all other inferior animals,
and but little lower than the <hi>Holy Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi> But I muſt
paſs this by and begin with <hi>Gods Electing-Grace.</hi> (viz.) That the
<hi>Great God</hi> our <hi>Abſolute Sovereign,</hi> who might have exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
the Glory of his <hi>Dominion</hi> in deſtroying us, aſſoon as he had
<hi>made us,</hi> or, who as a moſt <hi>Juſt and Righteous Judge,</hi>
might have ſatified him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in determining to inflict everlaſting wrath,
on all the Children of Men for their ſin in <hi>Adam.</hi> That <hi>this
Lord,</hi> ſhould <hi>from all Eternity purpoſe,</hi> and <hi>unalterably
determine to glorifie</hi> the <hi>riches of his Grace, Mercy</hi> and
<hi>Bounty</hi> in the <hi>actual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, compleat Juſtification,
Sanctification,</hi> and <hi>Glory of ſome,</hi> is of Grace<note n="*" place="margin">My deſign being to explicate the Glory of Free-Grace. I
have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of God's Electing Love ſomewhat concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
his <hi>Overflowing Goodneſs</hi> even <hi>unto all.</hi>
               </note>. But that he
ſhould alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to exalt his <hi>patience, forbearance,</hi> and
<hi>long-ſuffering</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:34827:9"/>in <hi>all,</hi> is moreover
marvelouſly aſtoniſhing.</p>
            <p>About which conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God from all eternity determined to ſend the Lord
Jeſus Chriſt into the World, purpoſing within himſelf, that whoſoever
did believe ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting life.</hi> This is
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved eaſily in that nothing is done in time, but what was from eternity
determined to be done, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> then, in time coming into the
world, in a way agreable to the Will of the Father, being the <hi>Gift of
the</hi> Father, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered</hi> by <hi>the determinate
counſel,</hi> and <hi>fore-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, Acts</hi> 2.28. yea, and this
<hi>Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> ſending the <hi>Miniſters</hi> into the World to
preach to every creature, that whoſoever belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſhould be ſaved,
<hi>Mark</hi> 16.15,16. 'Tis moſt certain that <hi>God from everlaſting did
deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine to ſend the Lord Jeſus Chriſt into the World, that whoever
believed might not periſh but obtain eternal life.</hi> Yea,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>God did determine,</hi> and <hi>fore-ordain, that much
patience and long-ſuffering ſhould be exerciſed towards all,</hi> yea,
<hi>even towards ſuch,</hi> who, <hi>by going on obſtinately in their
ſins, diſcover themſelves to be the veſſels of wrath,</hi> and a
People prepared <hi>for deſtruction,</hi> for this, we ſee confirmed in the
<hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> of the decree, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23. Oh the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
inſtances of Free-Grace vouchſafed the<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34827:10"/>worſt of men,
and how do the thoughts of abuſed grace add to the horrour of the damned!
that they rejected ſo many a gracious invitation, and that their
deſtruction is <hi>only</hi> of themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As <hi>God from everlaſting determined the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
of all the Children of faln man, on their ſincere faith and ſound
repentance, yea, and to bear long with the worſt of ſinners,</hi> even
ſo, <hi>ſuch was the ſuperabundance of his infinitely free love, as to
purpoſe the actual giving unto</hi> ſome <hi>ſincere faith and ſound
repentance,</hi> that ſo, they <hi>might be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God would not, that <hi>All</hi> ſhould periſh, and therefore
although the wickedneſs of all was great, yet, the Lord determined to extend
his infinite grace to <hi>ſome,</hi> that they might, by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving faith
from God, and all thoſe other graces, which are the <hi>merits</hi> and
<hi>purchaſe</hi> of Chriſts blood, &amp;c. and <hi>the work of Chriſt's
Spirit,</hi> be eternally ſaved.</p>
            <p>The eternal purpoſe of giving this <hi>ſuperabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant grace</hi>
is called <hi>Election; about which obſerve theſe</hi> following
particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God <hi>hath Elected ſome to life everlaſting.</hi>
This is acknowledged by the <hi>Remonſtrants,</hi> who have corrupted this
doctrine in part, and ſhall be proved in the <hi>confirmation</hi> of the
following par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:34827:10"/>2. The <hi>Election,</hi> or
<hi>foreknowledge of God is of a certain ſelect number of particular
perſons, known unto the Lord from all eternity:</hi> whom he foreknew,
thoſe he predeſtinated, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. The Lord <hi>knoweth,</hi> who
are his, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. and calleth them by <hi>name, John</hi> 10.3.
<hi>Jacob</hi> have I loved: <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.13. Before I <hi>formed thee in
the belly,</hi> I knew thee, and ordained thee a prophet to the nations,
<hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in particular was from eternity
<hi>known</hi> unto the Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> The great God from everlaſting
<hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knew,</hi> and <hi>predeſtinated this,</hi> (and conſequently
every other) <hi>particular elect perſon</hi> to their work here, and
<hi>glory hereafter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Election being an act of the Divine will, an immanent,
and an eternal act</hi> 'tis moſt <hi>free,</hi> we cannot ſuppoſe any
thing to precede what is eternal, <hi>God's election</hi> therefore is
according to the <hi>good pleaſure of his will, Epheſ.</hi> 1.5. The
<hi>elect being predeſtinated, or fore-ordained, according to the purpoſe
of him, who worketh all things, after the counſel of his will, Epheſ.</hi>
1.11. For, the myſtery of Gods will, which is made known unto us, is
<hi>according to his, good pleaſure,</hi> which he hath purpoſed in
himſelf <hi>ver.</hi> 9. 'Twas not the <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight</hi> of Faith, and
good works, that moved God to elect any, the <hi>principal cauſe</hi> of
election being the will of God, the eternal purpoſe <hi>of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34827:11"/>4. <hi>The ſelect Number of particular
perſons, who were from eternity moſt freely fore-ordained to be ſaved,
are ordained to Salvation, in</hi> and <hi>through the Lord Jeſus
Chriſt.</hi> According as he hath choſen us in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> before
the Foundation of the world, having predeſtinated us unto the Adoption of
Children by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, Eph.</hi> 1.4,5. Yea, God hath appointed us
to Obtain Salvation <hi>by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi>
5.9.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The <hi>unalterable determination,</hi> and <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
of God,</hi> is, <hi>that ſuch as are ordained to be ſaved through
Chriſt, be regenerated and renewed in their minds</hi> by <hi>the powerful
working of the holy Spirit.</hi> According as he hath choſen us in him, that
we ſhould be <hi>Holy</hi> and without <hi>blame</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in love.
<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. For, whom he did foreknow he did predeſtinate to be
<hi>conformed to the Image of his Son, Rom.</hi> 8.29. whence tis ſaid, that
we are created in Jeſus Chriſt unto <hi>good works,</hi> in which, God hath
fore-ordained, that we ſhould walk, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. For God hath
choſen you unto Salvation <hi>through the Sanctification of the Spirit,</hi>
2 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 2.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>The Improvement followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Lord left not the whole lump<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34827:11"/>of
mankind to periſh in eternal miſery but reſolved the Salvation of
<hi>ſome,</hi> is <hi>fully of grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Moſt High condeſcendeth ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely, as
to regard the Low eſtate of faln man, affording ſuitable helps for the
effectual engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſome</hi> to lay hold on eternal life is of grace;
The Lord gives Grace and Glory, and every good thing to a Select Number, which
is the ture reaſon why <hi>any</hi> are ſaved. But that <hi>which is
ſurprizing is this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Worſt of men,</hi> who appear to be
veſſels of wrath, have been endured with much <hi>long-ſuffering:</hi>
Surely 'tis not the <hi>Decree,</hi> that hath any ſuch cauſality in it, as
doth effect mans ſin,<note n="a" place="margin">Deteſtanda &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominanda
opinio eſt, quae Deum cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſquam malae vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis, aut malae actionis
credit Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorem; cujus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinatio nunquam extra bonitatem, nunquam
extra ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiam. Adulteria—non inſtruere novit ſancta Divinitas;
ſed damnare: nec <hi>diſponere;</hi> ſed punire. <hi>Aug.</hi> reſp. ad
art. ſibi impoſ. art. l. 10. Poſſet enim peccatum aliquod ex
praede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatione Dei eſſe: Si poſſet aliquis hominum juſtè
peccare: Nullus autem hominum juſtè peccat, quamvis eum Deus
juſtè peccare permittat. <hi>Fulgent.</hi> ad Mon. de praed. lib.
1.</note>
               <hi>Decreta nil ponunt in eſſe;</hi> Man's <hi>ſin</hi> is from
<hi>himſelf,</hi> and his <hi>deſtruction</hi> is but the product of his
own ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy, and rebellion. Oh the many <hi>exhortations, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
calls, preſſing</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34827:12"/>invitations,</hi> that are given <hi>all</hi> to return unto God, that
they may live; and how doth the Lord <hi>wait</hi> to be gracious, exerciſing
the greateſt patience in bearing the affronts of <hi>vile ſinners ſo
long!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It muſt be duly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred,<note n="b" place="margin">Ego
hoc dico quod dixi quia quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid Deusagit, <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerecorditer, juſte,
ſanctèque</hi> facit.—non poteſt tantum <hi>juſtus</hi> dici
Deus aut <hi>ſolùm miſericors:</hi> ſed <hi>Juſtus</hi> et
<hi>miſericors.</hi> Sic le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimus, ſic credimus. Auguſt. Reſp. ad
ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn. Pelagianor.</note> That the Lord in exalting Free-Grace, regards the
glory of his other moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent attributes, <hi>viz.</hi> his
<hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and in both, his
<hi>Infinite Wiſdom.</hi> I'le only hint, in this place, ſomewhat
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the glorification of <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> in a way conſiſtent
with his <hi>Holineſs.</hi> Although the Lord hath wonderfully diſcovered
himſelf to be the Lord God, <hi>Gracious,</hi> and <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful,
Long-ſuffering, ſlow to anger</hi> and <hi>abundant in goodneſs,</hi>
yet, ſtill the Lord is <hi>holy,</hi> yea, he is the <hi>Holy, Holy,
Holy,</hi> Lord God of Hoſts, ſhewing himſelf to be <hi>ſo,</hi> by his
love to holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the creature; and by his abhorrence unto <hi>ſin,</hi>
that is moſt contrary thereunto; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly as the
<hi>determination</hi> is to ſave <hi>ſome,</hi> it is further (as hath
been prov'd,) through <hi>the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Spirit:</hi> Oh then,
let none preſume to ſay, If they are <hi>elected,</hi> they ſhall be
<hi>ſaved,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:34827:12"/>though they remain wallowing in their
ſin! No, No, Reader, this is not ſo, for <hi>without holineſs</hi> no
ſeeing the face of God, 1 <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Out of Chriſt no
Salvation,</hi> and to remain Unſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, Unholy, and in ſin, is to be
out of Chriſt: give therefore all dilligence to make thy election
<hi>ſure,</hi> by being ſavingly <hi>Called,</hi> to the Leading a new
(which is an <hi>holy</hi>) <hi>life. But of</hi> this more Hereafter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A ſecond Inſtance of grace, Adding light unto the former,
ſhewing how the gracious decree is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed notwithſtanding the
difficulty. The Covenant between God the Father and the Son which is the
Covenant of reconciliation, or the Mediatorial Covenant diſcovered in ſome
of its particulars. The uſe ſhewing how grace is hereby glorified.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THat God might effectually accompliſh the Salvation of any, in a
way conſiſtent with the glory of his <hi>Holineſs, Righteouſneſs,
Truth</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſs,</hi> and accordingly ſee the Execution of
the decree of Grace, 'twas abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that <hi>Infinite
Wiſdom</hi> be <hi>in exerciſe;</hi> for, the work was ſtupendious, too
great for finite capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34827:13"/>to engage in, a work no way
beneath God himſelf. A <hi>Holy Good</hi> and <hi>juſt Law,</hi> unto which
was annexed a <hi>ſevere threatning,</hi> is tranſgreſſed, mankind is
become <hi>unholy</hi> and <hi>unclean,</hi> altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>filthy</hi> and
polluted, liable to to the greateſt miſeries: the Lord ſtill Juſt and
Righteous, True, and faithful, a God of purer eyes than to behold iniquity, or
delight in ſin, or in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconciled ſinner; <hi>Sin</hi> muſt be
puniſhed, <hi>juſtice</hi> muſt be ſatisfied, <hi>Holineſs</hi> and
<hi>Truth Glorified,</hi> but, <hi>Man</hi> in the circumſtances he then was,
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to do either; <hi>He</hi> cannot <hi>appeaſe Gods Wrath,</hi> nor
<hi>ſatisfy Juſtice,</hi> nor <hi>purifie,</hi> or <hi>cleanſe</hi> his
own heart to perfection, how then can he become the object of everlaſting
love: or how is it poſſible that the <hi>Gracious decree</hi> be executed?
I anſwer,</p>
            <p>Whoever conſiders theſe things ſeriouſly, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but cry
out, and ſay, if this work be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, it muſt be the Lords own
doing; and <hi>marvelous in our eyes.</hi> The <hi>contrivance muſt be the
effort of infinite wiſdome;</hi> and the <hi>Glory of that Grace,</hi> for
which ſuch a work muſt be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on, is <hi>Unſpeakable:</hi> and
verily the Lord hath ſhewn himſelf to be God, even in that he hath found
out a way for the doing this. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> dwelt with <hi>Prudence,</hi>
and found out the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this witty invention. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.12,30.
3. <hi>God the Father, conſulted with God the Son, and it rejoyced their
ſoul,</hi> that <hi>Grace might be<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34827:13"/>magnified,</hi> that
<hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> might greet each other. That the
<hi>Love</hi> of God might be made known unto man, without the impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of
the honour of his other Attributes.</p>
            <p>But what was the contrivance? 'twas this; <hi>God the Father entred
into a Covenant with God the Son,</hi> in which Covenant there is
obſervable,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>What the Father required from the Son.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>What the Father Promiſed the Son.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. What the Father required the Son to do, which more
generally, was the <hi>exalting Free-Grace in the actual Salvation of ſome,
even in a way agreable with the other glorious perfections of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But more particularly ſeveral things in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the obtaining
this end muſt be done.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A body muſt be prepared for the Son,</hi> he muſt
aſſume humane nature: it being neceſſary, that he that
<hi>ſanctifieth,</hi> and <hi>they who</hi> are <hi>ſanctified,</hi>
ſhould be of <hi>one,</hi> of <hi>one common Parent, Adam;</hi> and therefore
God the Son took on him the fleſh and blood, <hi>viz.</hi> The nature of the
Brethren, the <hi>humane</hi> (but not <hi>corrupt</hi>) <hi>nature, Heb.</hi>
2.11,14,16. And <hi>therefore a body was prepared for the Son, Heb.</hi> 10.5.
&amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:34827:14"/>2. In <hi>this nature,</hi> God the Son
muſt come <hi>into the World, Prov.</hi> 8.30,31. And <hi>ſuffer f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> mans</hi> ſin, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5. He was
<hi>wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniquities,
Gal.</hi> 3.13. <hi>John</hi> 10.18.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He muſt render a ſinleſs, a full, compleat and
perfect obedience to Gods Law, being made under the Law, Gal.</hi> 4.4. It
became <hi>him to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil all Righteouſneſs, Math.</hi> 3.15. He came
<hi>not to deſtroy the Law</hi> but to <hi>fulfil it, Math.</hi> 5.17. In
doing which, <hi>the end of the Law was anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the honour of Gods
Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>governing wiſdom conſerved,</hi> and the <hi>door
of grace opened to believing, repenting, returning ſinners, who were givens
to the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Lord Chriſt was obliged to keep and preſerve
theſe given him, <hi>This is the Fathers Will, that of all that he hath given
me, I ſhould loſe nothing, but ſhall raiſe it up at the laſt day,
John</hi> 6.39.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God <hi>the Father</hi> moreover doth <hi>make rich
promiſes unto the Son,</hi> on the Sons performing the required conditions;
The Son <hi>ſhall be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rewarded,</hi> he ſhall be <hi>exalted,</hi>
and made very high, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.13. Yea, God <hi>highly exalted</hi>
him, giving him a <hi>name</hi> above every name, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2.9. &amp;c.
Again God <hi>gives him</hi> a <hi>ſelect number,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:34827:14"/>who
ſhall in proceſs of time be actually with him in the eternal glory: <hi>He
ſhall ſee his ſeed,</hi> and the <hi>travel of his ſoul,</hi> and be
ſatisfied, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10.11. yea, a <hi>ſelect number among the
Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, Pſal.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Nations ſhall run unto him, Iſa.</hi> 5.5.
Who are called Children, <hi>given</hi> unto Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.13. So
<hi>John</hi> 10.29. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſpeaking of his
<hi>ſheep,</hi> that is, of thoſe that were <hi>ordained to eternal
life,</hi> doth ſay <hi>my Father which gave them me.</hi> Thus you ſee,
the <hi>terms</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> all ordered for the <hi>exaltation
of infinitely free Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The USES</p>
            <p>'Tis wonderful that the thoughts of God ſhould from all eternity
be concerned for faln man's ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Lord Chriſt, God-man,</hi> muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in
this <hi>great work,</hi> that he, who was eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in the boſom of the
Father, ſhould empty himſelf of the Glory of God and take upon him the form
of a ſervant, is mightily ſurprizing. That God ſhould humble himſelf
ſo infinitely, as to undergo the <hi>wrath of the Father!</hi> Oh what manner
of love, what manner of Grace is this! Read <hi>believingly,</hi> and
<hi>conſiderately</hi> the account given in the Scriptures of our Lord
Jeſus his <hi>fulfilling his part</hi> of the Covenant in the particulars
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34827:15"/>and you cannot but ſee <hi>free-grace, highly
exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God aſſumes humane nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What a wonder is this, and how many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, were wrought for the
effecting it, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing humane nature was by ſin <hi>Corrupted,</hi> and
yet, it muſt be aſſumed, and united unto the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, without
<hi>Corruption!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>God</hi> in this nature ſuffers; not, that the
<hi>divine nature,</hi> as <hi>ſuch,</hi> is capable of the leaſt
ſufferings; and therefore, 'tis the <hi>humane nature,</hi> that is the
<hi>immediate ſubject</hi> of ſufferings; but <hi>paſſions,</hi> as
well as <hi>actions</hi> being of <hi>perſons,</hi> we may ſafely ſay,
That <hi>he,</hi> who is God, ſuffered: for, our <hi>iniquities</hi> were
laid on Chriſt, <hi>Iſay,</hi> 53. <hi>Chriſt was made ſin,</hi> as
'tis 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. yea, and a <hi>curſe,</hi> that ſuch as do
believe might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from an eternal curſe. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>how</hi> was <hi>Chriſt made ſin,</hi> or <hi>in what
ſenſe, were the iniquities of any laid on him? was the filth of ſin laid
on Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:34827:15"/>
            <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> difficulty propoſed in the laſt Chapter ſpoken
unto. Sin with reference unto its FILTH, GUILT <hi>and</hi> PUNISHMENT
diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, <hi>and</hi> Explained. <hi>The puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and
Guilt of Sin</hi> laid on Chriſt aſſerted. Concerning the <hi>Filth of
Sin. The</hi> ſenſe of ſome <hi>Antonomians,</hi> reduced to three
particulars, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.</hi> Their <hi>firſt Error in</hi> ſaying the
<hi>Filth of Sin was laid on Chriſt,</hi> detected, <hi>and</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed.
<hi>That</hi> the Filth of Sin be laid on Chriſt <hi>impoſſible.</hi> The
conſequences of this Error dreadful <hi>and</hi> unſcriptural. The
<hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> of Chriſt aſſerted and
vindicated. The <hi>Antinomians</hi> abuſe <hi>of the</hi> Grace of God
hinted.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN giving a truely Scriptural, a full, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying anſwer
unto this difficulty, we ſhall have a fair occaſion of ſhewing, How, and
after what manner, <hi>Free-Grace</hi> is, in its Excellencies, diſplayed.
But, that we may entertain right con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions concerning this thing, we muſt
care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Filth,</hi> the <hi>Guilt</hi> and
<hi>Puniſhment</hi> of ſin.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is the <hi>Sin</hi> it ſelf <hi>formally</hi>
conſidered<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34827:16"/>which is a <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> of a
holy, good, and juſt Law; and accordingly, regarding <hi>ſin</hi> as it is
either <hi>contrary</hi> to, or <hi>different</hi> from this Law, tis
ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>impure, unclean,</hi> and <hi>polluting.</hi> In <hi>Sin</hi>
there is a <hi>diſſonancy,</hi> or <hi>diſconformity</hi> to the
<hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptive</hi> part of the Law, an irregularity, or a want of conformity
unto it, an <hi>obliquity,</hi> which is, <hi>filth, pollution,</hi> a
<hi>blot</hi> or <hi>ſtain,</hi> the <hi>fault it ſelf.</hi> In
whomſoever there is this <hi>fault,</hi> or this <hi>irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity,</hi> or
<hi>obliquity,</hi> there is a <hi>deformity,</hi> there is <hi>filth</hi> and
<hi>defilement,</hi> and that perſon is <hi>truly faulty</hi> for he hath
tranſgreſſed the Law; there is ſo much in him, either <hi>contrary
unto,</hi> or <hi>diſſonant</hi> from the Law, which is ſin, whence he
may be ſaid to be formally, or in a <hi>proper,</hi> and <hi>ſtrict
ſenſe</hi> a <hi>ſinner</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">[More expreſly to
declare what is this Filth, is ſomewhat difficult; although
<hi>Maeratius</hi> the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite (<hi>diſp. in ſum. Th. tract. de pec.
diſ.</hi> 13. <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. &amp;c.) aſſerts that the <hi>Macula
peccati formaliter eſt ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa malitia peccati actualis;</hi> to which he
adds, <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus moraliter durat, &amp; perſeverat, etium tranſacto
Phyſice actu peccati,</hi> &amp;c. This he gives, as the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſentiment
of the <hi>Modern Schoolmen,</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that the actual <hi>ſin,</hi>
though as <hi>Phyſically</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, immediately paſſeth away;
yet as <hi>morally,</hi> it remains; called <hi>actual,</hi> as you reſpect
the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in which 'tis committed; called the <hi>Macu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> as it
remains until by Repentance or the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of grace it be blotted out: But
I cannot comprehend <hi>How</hi> the <hi>Filth</hi> of ſin, which remains,
ſhould be the ſame <hi>Numerically</hi> with the Act, which ſo ſuddenly
ceaſeth to be, it ſeeming to be little leſs than an Implication to
aſſert, that the <hi>ſame Numerical act, is, and is not, in one and the
ſame instant.</hi> I ſhould therefore rather humbly conclude it to be thus.
<hi>Actual ſins</hi> being contrary to the <hi>Pure Law</hi> of God are
<hi>Filthy</hi> and <hi>Impure,</hi> which <hi>Filthy</hi> and <hi>Impure
Acts,</hi> leave behind them much <hi>Filth,</hi> which conſiſts in vitious
habits, which habits are ſtrengthned, by a frequency of ſinful, filthy
Acts, and conſequently the ſoul thereby the more <hi>filthy</hi> and
polluted; whence the remaining Filth is the continued blindneſs and
<hi>habitual aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of the heart from God.]</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34827:16"/>2. There is <hi>Guilt,</hi> which doth
immediately attend this <hi>ſin</hi> where ever it is, ſo that whoever
ſinneth, contracts <hi>Guilt,</hi> which <hi>Guilt</hi> is a liable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to
puniſhment, an <hi>Obnoxiouſneſs</hi> thereunto for ſome
<hi>fault.</hi> Guilt, as tis diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>fault it
ſelf,</hi> is the immediate effect of the Fault, or of the ſin, and is not
<hi>properly</hi> or in a ſtrict ſenſe ſin; but only
<hi>Metonymically,</hi> and <hi>Improperly</hi> ſo. In which ſenſe, as I
ſhall hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhew, 'tis frequently in Scripture called <hi>ſin.</hi>
It being ſins reſpect unto the threatning part of the Law. For as the
inclinations, thoughts, words, and actions, as diſſonant from, or
diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form unto the Precept of the Law, are formally ſins; even ſo, as
<hi>ſin</hi> regards the threatning part of the ſame Law, 'tis <hi>guilt;
Guilt then is ſin</hi>'s <hi>extrinſecal reſpect unto the threatning, the
ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Law.</hi> To be liable to the threatning<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34827:17"/>is to be <hi>Guilty.</hi> To be judged liable unto it, is to be judged
<hi>Guilty,</hi> or to be judged a <hi>ſinner:</hi> I think not my ſelf
obliged to inſiſt on the diſtinction, <hi>inter Reatum culpae &amp;
poenae.</hi> For where-ever there is the <hi>dignitas poenae,</hi> there is the
<hi>obligatio ad poenam;</hi> (Whatever <hi>Maeratius</hi> and others ſay to
the contrary) and there can be no <hi>obligatio ad poenam,</hi> where there is
not <hi>Dignitas poenae propter culpam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>puniſhment</hi> is the <hi>evil threatned for
ſin;</hi> 'tis an <hi>evil</hi> or ſomewhat <hi>painful,</hi> and grievous,
inflicted for <hi>ſin.</hi> 'Tis <hi>malum paſſionis propter ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum
actionis,</hi> or <hi>malum naturale propter malum morale,</hi> which is alſo
an <hi>effect</hi> of ſin, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently beareth the <hi>name</hi> of
ſin, it's cauſe. And ſo the word that ſignifies <hi>Sin</hi> is uſed
in the ſacred writing to denote <hi>puniſhment,</hi> as in <hi>Gen.</hi>
4.13<note n="*" place="margin">Note Gen. 47.</note> Where <hi>Cain</hi> ſaid,
my <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is greater than I can bear,</hi> that is, in the Hebrew,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> mine <hi>Iniquity</hi> or my
<hi>ſin,</hi> the like alſo in <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.15. Leſt thou be
conſumed in the <hi>Iniquity</hi> of the City (is) ſaith <hi>Ainſworth in
loc.</hi>
               <q rend="inline">"The <hi>Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment for Iniquity,</hi> Hereupon
is that uſual Phraſe of <hi>bearing Iniquity, for ſuffering
Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>" Lev. 28.17,19,20. <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.34.</q> To
<hi>Puniſh</hi> is to inflict evil on the <hi>Guilty,</hi> as
<hi>ſuch;</hi> for evils inflicted on the <hi>Innocent</hi> as
<hi>Innocent,</hi> are not <hi>puniſhments.</hi> Whence obſerve, that when
'tis<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34827:17"/>ſaid, our <hi>Iniquities</hi> were laid on the Lord
Chriſt, we may ſafely underſtand it of the <hi>puniſhment</hi> and
<hi>guilt</hi> of ſin.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>puniſhment of our ſin was laid on
Chriſt,</hi> is moſt evident, in that the Lord Chriſt, was made a
<hi>Sacrifice for ſin.</hi> All his fufferings being <hi>Penal,</hi> he being
<hi>wounded,</hi> and <hi>bruiſed for our ſins,</hi> our <hi>griefs</hi>
laid on him, and he <hi>made a curſe for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Guilt of Sin, was</hi> alſo <hi>laid on
Chriſt,</hi> is a truth moſt agreable unto the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>In order to the confirming which I ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to ſhew (1)
<hi>That this is Poſſible;</hi> the <hi>Guilt</hi> may be laid on Chriſt
without the laying any <hi>ſtain</hi> on his moſt <hi>pure nature</hi> (2)
that <hi>this was really ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>this may be,</hi> viz. That the <hi>Guilt of ſin
may</hi> be laid <hi>on Chriſt,</hi> and the Lord Chriſt remain
<hi>pure</hi> and <hi>free</hi> from the leaſt <hi>blemiſh,</hi> appears
from this, that the <hi>Guilt</hi> of ſin doth not contain in it, the
<hi>formal nature of ſin</hi> that is ſo Polluting, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat
extrinſecal thereunto, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>ſeparable from ſin,</hi>
yea, and from the <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſinner:</hi> I know that <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
who, denies the <hi>Guilt of ſin to have been laid on Chriſt,</hi> doth
aſſert, Guilt to be <hi>inſeparable</hi> from the ſin it ſelf,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34827:18"/>for, ſaith he, ſpeaking of the <hi>Reatus culpae.</hi>
               <q rend="inline">"<hi>Reatus, ut rectè docet</hi> Philippus,
<hi>eſt Relatio, cujus proximum fundamentum eſt actus malus, ſive
iniquitas. Non poteſt autem Relatio</hi> à fundamento proximo
ſeparari, <hi>quia ex ipſo fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damento naturaliter &amp; neceſſario
ſequitur.</hi>" <hi>Bell. de amiſſ. Grat. &amp; Stat. peccat. l.</hi> 5.
<hi>c.</hi> 7.</q> But what more evident, than that, although, <hi>ſin</hi>
ever contracts <hi>Guilt,</hi> and <hi>Guilt</hi> ever attends <hi>ſin;</hi>
Which is the whole <hi>Bellarmine</hi> proves in ſaying that <hi>Relatio ex
ipſo fundamento,</hi> &amp;c. yet <hi>Guilt</hi> is not an <hi>Inſeparable
Conſequent</hi> of ſin, even according to the ſenſe of the
<hi>Schoolmen,</hi> yea, and of <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> himſelf. Do not the
<hi>Schoolmen</hi> generally diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Guilt</hi> and
<hi>Filth</hi> of ſin? <hi>Malderus</hi> in 12 <hi>ae. Thomae, q.</hi> 85.
<hi>art.</hi> 1.2. men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions eight different ſentiments that the Learned
entertain concerning the <hi>Macula,</hi> the <hi>Filth of ſin,</hi> and 'tis
the opinion of <hi>but</hi> a few, that the <hi>Macula</hi> and the
<hi>Reatus</hi> is the <hi>ſame;</hi> Theſe Schoolmen commonly
diſcourſing of the <hi>Fault</hi> it ſelf, the <hi>Macula,</hi> and the
<hi>Reatus culpae,</hi> and <hi>Reatus poenae</hi> as diſtinct; ſo
<hi>Maeratius</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite diſp. in ſum. tract. de pec.
diſp.</hi> 13. <hi>ſect.</hi> 5. and <hi>Bellarmine:</hi> They moſtly
<hi>agreeing in this,</hi> That the <hi>Reatus culpae,</hi> or the <hi>Dignitas
poenae</hi> is not the ſame with the <hi>filth</hi> of ſin, neither doth
this <hi>Guilt</hi> contain within it the <hi>formal nature</hi> of ſin. For
ſaith <hi>Maeratius, ubi ſupra.</hi>
               <q rend="inline">"<hi>Quare cum ex omni peccato ſequatur poenae
Dignitas, &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem <pb n="27" facs="tcp:34827:18"/>obligatio; ſi Dignitas haec,
&amp; obligatio, ſit formaliter peccatum, ex iis altera dignitas, &amp;
obligatio ſequetur, quae vel erit peccatum, vel non; ſi ſecundum, habemus
intentum; ſi pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, dabitur proceſſus in infinitum;</hi>"</q> yea, and
they farther conclude, That the <hi>guilt</hi> is <hi>ſeparable</hi> from the
<hi>fault it ſelf.</hi> Dignitas &amp; obligatio luendae poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae poſſunt
in eo eſſe, qui caret peccato; yea, and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ubi ſupra c.
19. aſſerts that
<q rend="inline">"Reatus culpae <hi>non est</hi> propriè
peccatum, <hi>ſed effectus neceſſario conſequens, &amp; aliquid manens
post ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum peccati, non enim homo est</hi> dignus odio <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſè,
quia peccavit, alioqui nunquam talis digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas auferri poſſet, &amp;</hi>
peccatum eſſet Irremiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile; <hi>ſicut fieri non poteſt, ut qui
peccavit, non peccaverit; praeterea talis dignitas</hi>
&amp;c.—<hi>non</hi> eſt aliquid recedens à
lege—<hi>non</hi> deformat, <hi>vel</hi> occidit ſpiritualiter animam,
<hi>non est</hi> privatio boni, neque habet aliquid aliud eorum, quae
propriè peccato conveniunt."</q> So plain 'tis, that <hi>Guilt,</hi> the
<hi>Guilt of the Fault,</hi> is not <hi>properly,</hi> or <hi>formally
ſin,</hi> 'tis ſomewhat <hi>diſtinct</hi> from the <hi>Fault, for it</hi>
doth not pollute, or deform the ſoul; yea, Guilt is <hi>ſeparable</hi> from
the <hi>fault it ſelf,</hi> otherwiſe, the <hi>Guilt</hi> of
<hi>Adam</hi>'s actual ſin, could not be made <hi>ours,</hi> for if his
actual ſin, and the guilt thereof, had been <hi>inſeparable,</hi> there
could have been no paſſing of the guilt of his ſin to us, unleſs his
actual ſin had been removed alſo from him unto us. Again the <hi>pardon of
ſin,</hi> which conſiſts in <pb n="28" facs="tcp:34827:19"/>the removing the guilt of
ſin, would alſo become an Impoſſibility to the unſpeakable horrour of
all the Children of fallen Adam. But that the Guilt is ſeparable from the
filth of ſin, is eaſily illuſtrated, by the <hi>Metaphor</hi> of a
<hi>Debtor, Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and <hi>Surety,</hi> according to the Rules of Law.
A <hi>Debtor</hi> is liable to pay one thouſand pounds unto his
<hi>Creditor.</hi> This <hi>liableneſs is Guilt. Inde Reus conſtitutus
dicitur, qui ſe obligavit.</hi> Which <hi>Guilt</hi> may be the product of
his own extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy or Fault: But this <hi>debtor becoming Inſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent,</hi>
another who voluntarily undertaking the payment, thereby becomes <hi>liable to
pay</hi> the debt, <hi>i.e.</hi> He becomes <hi>Guilty:</hi> [For, Interdum
Reus Expromiſſorem ſignificat, <hi>i.e. eum, qui</hi> alienam <hi>in
ſe</hi> obligationem, <hi>vel</hi> novatione, <hi>vel</hi> delegatione
ſuſcepit. <hi>Schard.</hi> in verb.] but <hi>Guilty</hi> of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<hi>Fault,</hi> [<hi>Venia</hi> namque digni <hi>ſunt, qui</hi> alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ
tenentur Culpâ, <hi>cujusmodi ſunt</hi> Fide-juſſores pro alieno
debito obligati. <hi>Schard.</hi> in verb. <hi>Fidejuſſ.</hi>] So plain it
is, That the <hi>Fault,</hi> and <hi>Guilt</hi> are ſo <hi>ſeparable,</hi>
that the <hi>Fault</hi> may remain on the one, when the <hi>Guilt</hi>
paſſeth to the other.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, That the <hi>Guilt of our ſins</hi>
paſſed from us unto Chriſt, is now to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. But before I
proceed to do ſo, it muſt be duly remembred, That, what hath been already
ſaid, doth with the greateſt clearneſs ſhew, <hi>That the laying the
Guilt of ſin on Chriſt, may be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34827:19"/>the caſting
any Filth on the face of this our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to the Proof.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This may be evinced from the conſideration, that Jeſus
Chriſt ſuffered for our ſins as a <hi>ſurety.</hi> The Lord Jeſus
voluntarily offered up himſelf, and moſt freely undertook to pay what
ſinful man, the <hi>Debtor,</hi> could not: On which account <hi>He</hi> was
immediately liable to pay the <hi>Debt,</hi> or undergo the puniſhment
<hi>(i.e.)</hi> He was <hi>Guilty,</hi> as has been already intimated:
<hi>Man</hi> was <hi>faulty</hi> in contracting ſo great a debt, but
<hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>innocently merciful</hi> in taking it on himſelf to
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy the Father whereby Chriſt became <hi>Guilty</hi> of anothers
<hi>Fault.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>God the Father's inflicting evil</hi> on Chriſt as
<hi>Penal</hi> moſt righteouſly, doth neceſſarily infer this truth; It
being <hi>unjuſt</hi> to puniſh any, but the <hi>Guilty:</hi> to which add
<hi>thoſe Scriptures,</hi> that make mention of the <hi>Lords bearing our
iniquities, his being wounded for our tranſgreſſions, his being made
ſin,</hi> and a <hi>curſe, Iſa.</hi> 53.4,5,6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.
<hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</p>
            <p>That which will give light unto theſe texts, and ſtrength unto
my arguments is a <hi>truth</hi> of great importance concerning the
<hi>guilt,</hi> and<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34827:20"/>
               <hi>puniſhment</hi> of ſin,
<hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>although the Faul, and the Guilt are ſeparable</hi>
yet the <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are not;</hi> Whence whoſoever
is found <hi>Guilty</hi> at the <hi>Bar, muſt be ſentenced,</hi> yea, and
<hi>puniſhed</hi> as <hi>ſuch.</hi> If Guilt and Puniſhment had not been
by the unalterable determination of <hi>God,</hi> as he is a <hi>Righteous
Lawgiver,</hi> ſo fixedly united unto each other, as never to admit of the
leaſt ſeparation, the Juſtice and Righteouſneſs of God might have
been ſufficiently glorified in the pardoning ſin without any regard unto a
ſacrifice, yea, it might have been <hi>poſſible,</hi> for that bitter
cup, to have paſſed, according unto the Lord Jeſus his deſire; and man,
notwithſtanding might have been moſt happy. But ſince Laws would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
to be but <hi>ludicrous</hi> and <hi>feeble things,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a due
<hi>execution</hi> of the threatned evil, caſting the worſt of reflections
upon the Lawgiver, <hi>God,</hi> who is <hi>Infinitely Wiſe, Holy,
Juſt,</hi> and <hi>Righteous</hi> giveth moſt illuſtrious inſtances of
the <hi>Excellency of his Laws,</hi> in that there is a day, in which ſearch
ſhall be made after the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour, and when all ſuch, as are
found guilty ſhall be condemned to the threatned puniſhment; for God will
by no means <hi>clear the guilty, Exod.</hi> 34.7. They that ſhall preſume
to <hi>Juſtifie</hi> the <hi>wicked,</hi> or, <hi>condemn the Righteous,</hi>
even they both are an <hi>abomination unto the Lord, Prov.</hi> 17.15. Whence
'tis a thing moſt <hi>unjuſt to puniſh</hi> the <hi>Innocent,</hi> and
permit the <hi>Guilty</hi> to go free:<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34827:20"/>which being ſo, it
follows, that whoever is juſtly puniſhed, muſt be really guilty of his
own or of anothers fault; to puniſh any as not guilty, or as innocent, is as
great an act of injuſtice, as 'tis, <hi>not</hi> to <hi>puniſh</hi> thoſe
who at the Judgment-Seat are found <hi>Guilty.</hi> Theſe truths carry their
own evidence with them, proclaiming this other, namely, <hi>That if the Lord
Jeſus Chriſt did bear the Puniſhment of our iniquities;</hi> it was,
<hi>becauſe antecedently thereunto,</hi> the <hi>Guilt of our iniquities was
laid on him;</hi> And that the Lord did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of
our ſins can never be denied by any, that believe the fore-mentioned texts,
it being ſo expreſs, <hi>That he hath born our griefs, and carryed our
ſorrows; he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for
our iniquities,</hi> yea, the Lord <hi>hath laid on him the iniquity of us
all,</hi> he was <hi>made ſin,</hi> and a <hi>Curſe.</hi> But in what
ſenſe, if not in this, That at leaſt the <hi>puniſhment</hi> of our
iniquity was laid on Chriſt? Is not this ſo plain that neither
<hi>Arminian,</hi> nor <hi>Papiſt</hi> do preſume to deny it?
<hi>Bellarmine,</hi> I am ſure, aſſerts it, and if the
<hi>Puniſhment</hi> of ſin be laid on Chriſt, ſince 'tis done by the
Lord who is <hi>Juſt,</hi> it muſt be becauſe <hi>antecedently</hi> to
the infliction of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>Guilt</hi> was laid on him, for
otherwiſe not only the <hi>Innocent</hi> would be puniſhed, but more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
as <hi>Innocent,</hi> which is <hi>injuſtice;</hi> for, although an
<hi>Innocent Perſon</hi> may <hi>juſtly</hi> undergo ſevere
puniſhments; yet not <hi>as Innocent,</hi> but as <hi>guilty of another's
Faults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:34827:21"/>For the fuller clearing this Truth I'le only
attempt to prove, that the <hi>bearing ſin,</hi> or <hi>Iniquity,</hi> or the
being <hi>made ſin,</hi> and a <hi>Curſe</hi> doth ſignify <hi>both</hi>
the being <hi>Guilty</hi> and <hi>as ſuch</hi> the being pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Puniſhment</hi> by a <hi>Metonymy,</hi> bears the name of
<hi>ſin,</hi> I have proved out of <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.13. <hi>ch.</hi> 19.15.
and which may be further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, from that in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.10. Where
<hi>Saul</hi> ſware to the Witch, that there ſhall no <hi>Puniſhment</hi>
happen unto her: In the Hebrew 'tis
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there ſhall no <hi>Sin,</hi> or
<hi>Iniquity</hi> happen. So alſo in <hi>Zechar.</hi> 14.19. This ſhall be
the <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>Aegypt</hi> and the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of
all nations. In the Hebrew 'tis <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
the <hi>ſin</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> &amp;c. In like manner to <hi>bear
ſin,</hi> is to bear the <hi>Guilt</hi> or <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of
<hi>ſin, Ezek.</hi> 18.20. The Son ſhall not <hi>bear the iniquity</hi> of
the Father, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> the Son ſhall not bear the <hi>Guilt,</hi> nor
the <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the Fathers ſin; but the <hi>wickedneſs</hi>
of the wicked ſhall be upon him <hi>(i.e.)</hi> the <hi>Guilt</hi> and
<hi>Puniſhment</hi> of the wicked ſhall be upon him; whence that word which
in the Hebrew doth ſignify <hi>Guilt</hi> doth alſo ſignify <hi>Sin;</hi>
tis <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.21. we are
<hi>Guilty</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſame word
is elſewhere tranſlated <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>treſpaſſes;</hi> as
in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.21. God will wound the hairy ſcalp of ſuch an one,
as goeth on ſtill in his <hi>treſpaſſes</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Again to have <hi>iniquity laid
on us,</hi> is the ſame with the bearing <hi>iniquity,</hi> that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34827:21"/>is, the bearing the guilt of ſin. In fine, The <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
made ſin,</hi> and the <hi>being made a curſe,</hi> are <hi>terms</hi> much
of the ſame import, denoting the <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment,</hi>
and (as I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,) <hi>more properly,</hi> the <hi>guilt</hi> of
<hi>ſin,</hi> becauſe the <hi>wicked,</hi> even on their ſinning are
<hi>immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accurſed;</hi> are <hi>abnoxious,</hi> though not
<hi>immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately Puniſhed, q. d.</hi> Since to be <hi>obnoxious</hi> is to be
<hi>guilty,</hi> to be <hi>curſed</hi> is to be <hi>guilty;</hi> but, that
the <hi>being made a curſe</hi> doth not, as formerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered,
ſignify the <hi>being made formally ſin,</hi> is evident, in that, 'tis an
<hi>evil threatned</hi> for what is <hi>ſtrictly ſin;</hi> and therefore,
<hi>as ſuch,</hi> denotes ſomewhat diſtinct from <hi>ſin,</hi> taking
<hi>ſin,</hi> in a ſtrict ſenſe, for the <hi>very fault,</hi> or
<hi>tranſgreſſion it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have in ſome weak meaſure performed, what I engag'd to
doe, and have prov'd, <hi>That Guilt is ſeparable from Sin,</hi> the formal
Nature and Filth thereof; and conſequently, <hi>may paſs from us to
Chriſt,</hi> even when it muſt not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded as if <hi>Chriſt</hi>
had been for ſuch a reaſon <hi>formally</hi> a <hi>ſinner.</hi> I have
further ſhewn, <hi>That the Guilt,</hi> as well as <hi>Puniſhment of
ſin,</hi> is <hi>laid on Chriſt, Theſe</hi> being ſo
<hi>inſeparable,</hi> that a <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judge</hi> in doing Right,
<hi>cannot omit the Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhing the Guilty;</hi> nor preſume to inflict any
evil <hi>penally on ſuch,</hi> as are <hi>not in any wiſe Guilty:</hi>
But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. To conſider the <hi>Filth of Sin.</hi> The <hi>Filth of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34827:22"/>Sin,</hi> being of a <hi>Polluting</hi> and <hi>Defiling
Nature,</hi> was not <hi>laid on Chriſt,</hi> as ſome very boldly have
aſſerted, who not diſtinctly minding <hi>what the Filth of Sin</hi> is;
<hi>how diſtinguiſhed from Guilt,</hi> &amp;c. have under the notion of
exalting <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> faln into <hi>Dangerous Errors;</hi> which I will
eſſay to demonſtrate by ſhewing the <hi>falſeneſs,
Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity</hi> and <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> thereof. But before I do ſo,
'twill be neceſſary, that I acquaint you with the ſenſe of thoſe men
that aſſert it, which is this.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">"God doth not only lay the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> and
Guilt of Sin on Chriſt, but <hi>ſimply</hi> the <hi>very Fault it
ſelf,</hi> that men commit, that is, The <hi>Tranſgreſſion it
ſelf</hi> is become the <hi>tranſgreſſion of Chriſt,</hi> ſo that,
in reſpect of the <hi>Reality</hi> of being a <hi>Tranſgreſſor,</hi>
Chriſt is as <hi>really a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor,</hi> as the perſon that did
commit the ſin.—Yea Chriſt Jeſus by vertue of Gods laying ſin on
him, is as <hi>really a Tranſgreſſor,</hi> as if he <hi>himſelf, had
actually committed Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.</hi> The very <hi>Erring,
Straying,</hi> and <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing</hi> of the Elect is paſſed
from them and laid on Chriſt.—Haſt thou been an Idolater,
Blaſphemer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If thou haſt part in the Lord Chriſt,
<hi>all theſe Tranſgreſſions of thine</hi> become <hi>actually</hi> the
Tranſgreſſions of Chriſt, and ſo <hi>ceaſe to be thine,</hi> and
thou ceaſeſt to be a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor from that time they were laid on
Chriſt to the laſt hour of thy life.—Thy Sins being laid on Chriſt
are taken from thee.—If God<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34827:22"/>himſelf ſay, thy
ſins lye upon thee, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſay, he did before lay them on Chriſt,
how much is this better than a Contradiction?—The Sin it ſelf or the
<hi>Filth</hi> is removed from the Elect by being laid on Chriſt, and the
ſoul made <hi>Perfect.</hi>—God doth not waſh them by halves, nor
doth he leave ſome <hi>ſpots</hi> and <hi>blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes</hi> and
<hi>ſtains</hi> behind.—<hi>Chriſt's holineſs</hi> is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto
the Elect, as well as his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, otherwiſe they could not be
perfect in this life, ſince the <hi>Spirit's work in their Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication is
but imperfect</hi> in this life; 'tis Chriſt therefore who by bearing our
ſins carries away all the <hi>Abhorrency</hi> and <hi>loathſomneſs</hi>
of ſin, otherwiſe God could take no pleaſure in us.—God is a God of
ſo much Purity, that he <hi>cannot endure that Perſon where the leaſt
SPOT of Sin is found.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>This, and much more, is aſſerted by Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> in his
Sermons on <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 53.6. as alſo by <hi>ſome others,</hi> which
for the greater clearneſs, I'le <hi>ſum</hi> up in theſe following
particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That theſe men conclude that the <hi>Filth of ſin is
laid on Chriſt,</hi> and made <hi>really his Filth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 2. That Chriſt is our Juſtification by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of
his Righteouſneſs, <hi>even ſo, he is our Sanctification by the
Imputation of his Holineſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:34827:23"/>3. That the <hi>Filth</hi> of ſin being
laid on Chriſt, <hi>the Elect</hi> are <hi>thereby totally,</hi> and
<hi>perfectly</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from every <hi>loathſome</hi> Spot and
<hi>blemiſh of ſin.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To all which I reply diſtinctly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the <hi>firſt.</hi> That the <hi>Filth</hi> of ſin
is laid on Chriſt, and made <hi>really his Filth</hi> (as they ſay) this is
<hi>Impoſſible, Abſurd</hi> and <hi>Falſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Impoſſible,</hi> for by the <hi>Filth</hi> of ſin
we muſt underſtand, either <hi>Irregular, Oblique,</hi> and
<hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly defections,</hi> or <hi>inclinations,</hi> or <hi>words,</hi>
or <hi>actions.</hi> For ſin is a <hi>moral relation,</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be,
but in a ſubject; and as the <hi>Perſon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> is the <hi>Remote
Subject,</hi> even ſo, the <hi>Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, Thought, Word</hi> or
<hi>Action,</hi> or ſome <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> muſt be the <hi>neareſt
Subject;</hi> whence then, ſince ſin cannot be, and not be in ſome
<hi>Subject,</hi> the ſin in its filth cannot paſs from us to Chriſt, but
in <hi>tranſity, i.e.</hi> in its paſſage from one Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to another,
it muſt be conſidered, as in no <hi>Subject (i.e.)</hi> as what is
<hi>deſtroyed.</hi> For the Relation muſt paſs without its Subject, which
is <hi>impoſſible;</hi> or with the <hi>neareſt Subject</hi> it ſelf,
that is, All our <hi>ſinful Defections, Propenſions, Words</hi> and
<hi>Actions</hi> muſt paſs from us into Chriſt, but if this be not alſo
<hi>impoſſible,</hi> what is? But 2ly. Tis <hi>Abſurd</hi> and falſe.
For,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:34827:23"/>2. If the <hi>Filth</hi> of our ſin be
laid on Chriſt, then ſurely, the Lord Chriſt is thereby made <hi>really
filthy;</hi> for as <hi>Guilt</hi> is laid on Chriſt, and thereby Chriſt is
made <hi>really guilty</hi> that is, really <hi>guilty of another mans
ſin,</hi> even ſo, if the <hi>Filth</hi> of ſin be laid on Chriſt, then
Chriſt muſt be <hi>really filthy,</hi> for <hi>in quocunque ineſt
abſtractum, de eo dicitur con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretum,</hi> the <hi>denomination</hi> is
<hi>à forma denominante: Filth,</hi> on whomſoever 'tis, doth give the
denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>filthy;</hi> but was our Lord Chriſt really fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy? Was
there any ſin in any reſpect in him, who knew no ſin, and in whom there
was no guile? <hi>Guilt</hi> is an <hi>extrinſecal reſpect</hi> of ſin to
<hi>the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Law,</hi> and a man may be <hi>guilty</hi> of ſin,
that is of <hi>anothers ſin,</hi> who hath no ſin in him of <hi>his
own;</hi> but <hi>Filth</hi> the <hi>fault it ſelf,</hi> is ſo
<hi>intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal to ſin,</hi> that in whomſoever the <hi>Filth of
ſin</hi> is, in him <hi>ſin</hi> muſt be; and were it a thing
poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that the ſin of the elect ſhould paſs from the elect to
Chriſt, it would make the Lord Chriſt a <hi>real ſinner, really Unclean,
Impure, Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy,</hi> and <hi>Corrupt,</hi> but who can entertain ſuch a
thought without abhorrence? For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Scriptures</hi> never aſſert that the <hi>Filth
of ſin</hi> was laid on Chriſt. Tis true our <hi>ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities</hi> were laid
on Chriſt, that is, the <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Guilt</hi> of our
iniquities, as hath been proved, but not the <hi>Filth of our iniquities;</hi>
nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was it neceſſary, that any more ſhould be <pb n="38" facs="tcp:34827:24"/>laid on Chriſt, than the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> and <hi>Guilt.</hi>
For the Lord Chriſt came only to exempt us from wrath, to bring us into a
ſtate of Grace, and to purchaſe a right to glory for us, by his
<hi>ſufferings,</hi> and <hi>perfect righteouſneſs.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Scriptures</hi> do moſt vehemently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
that there was no <hi>ſpot in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>God,</hi> we cannot ſay, that
any <hi>Filth</hi> was on him without <hi>blaſphemy</hi> ſurely, that
<hi>God,</hi> who is of purer eyes than to behold iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, could never be
ſo in love with the <hi>filth,</hi> the <hi>worſt of iniquity,</hi> as to
take it on himſelf. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (2) Durſt we aver that the Lord Chriſt, with
reſpect to his <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> had the leaſt <hi>Filth</hi> of
ſin, either in, or upon him. For he was born an <hi>Holy thing, Luke</hi>
1.35. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo that <hi>Holy</hi> thing, which ſhall be born of
thee, ſhall be called the Son of God. He was <hi>born with holy
inclinations,</hi> and propenſions, yea and all his <hi>Thoughts, Words</hi>
and <hi>Actions</hi> were <hi>holy all his lifetime, for he fulfilled all
Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Matth.</hi> 3.15. <hi>ch.</hi> 5.17. and at his <hi>death,
his blood was the pretious blood of him,</hi> who was <hi>without blemiſh and
without ſpot,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. He <hi>did not ſin,</hi> neither
was <hi>guile found in his mouth, Ch.</hi> 2.22. For ſuch an High Prieſt
became us, who is <hi>Holy, Harmleſs, Undefiled, Separate</hi> from
<hi>Sinners, Heb.</hi> 7.26. Which could not be,<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34827:24"/>had he the
leaſt <hi>ſpot</hi> or <hi>blemiſh on him.</hi> Note well <hi>Iſa.</hi>
53.9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In what <hi>part of Chriſt</hi> was the <hi>filth of
ſin laid,</hi> or what was there in Chriſt, that was either
<hi>faulty,</hi> or <hi>filthy?</hi> was there any <hi>flaw</hi> in his
<hi>underſtanding,</hi> or, were the <hi>inclinations</hi> of his ſoul
after evil? were his thoughts irregular, or his words, or actions diſſonant
from Gods Law? The <hi>Filth</hi> of ſin is a <hi>ſpiritual filth,</hi>
pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Soul, but which part of his righteous ſoul was polluted? was
our <hi>Ignorance</hi> laid on Chriſt, making Chriſt <hi>Ignorant?</hi> or
our <hi>Pride, Stubbornneſs, Uncleanneſs, Sinful anger,</hi> and <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
Paſſions</hi> in Chriſt? was the Lord Chriſt, <hi>Ignorant, Proud,
Paſſionate,</hi> or <hi>Unclean?</hi> what ſound believer doth not
tremble at ſuch thoughts as theſe. But, for the <hi>Filth</hi> of ſin to
be laid on Chriſt, and yet the Filth of no one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſin to be found
on him, is ſtrange. Oh that men, who preſume to contradict the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
of the Juſt, would ſhew, what they mean by the <hi>filth of ſin,</hi> as
'tis diſtinguiſhed, both from <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> and
<hi>what</hi> they underſtand by the <hi>Fathers laying the Filth of ſin on
Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>what</hi> by the words, <hi>tranſacting the filth of
ſin on Chriſt!</hi> For me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, 'tis impoſſible, that any truly
gracious ſoul ſhould conclude <hi>that the filth of ſin, the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34827:25"/>fault it ſelf, as diſtinguiſhed from Guilt and
Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment, can in any reſpect be laid on Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore then conſider, 'tis a great diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to
<hi>Free-Grace,</hi> to ſay, <hi>that the Father laid</hi> the <hi>filth of
ſin</hi> on Chriſt, for this is inconſiſtent with the
<hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of God, and to ſet up
<hi>Free-Grace</hi> to the reproach of <hi>Divine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> or
<hi>Wiſdom</hi> is to <hi>abuſe it.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:34827:25"/>
            <head>CHAP. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>A</hi> ſecond Error of the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> viz.
<hi>The</hi> Elect made holy by Chriſt's Holineſs.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Somewhat</hi> concerning Juſtification
premiſed.</item>
                  <item>Several reaſons againſt the <hi>Error.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Wherein its tendency to the ſubverſion of a great part of
the Chriſtian Religion is evinced. The third error conſidered, <hi>its</hi>
deſtructiveneſs to all Religion proved particularly.</item>
               </list>
            </argument>
            <p>To the Second.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">"THat, as Chriſt is our Juſtification by the
imputation of his Righteouſneſs, even ſo, <hi>he</hi> is our
<hi>Sanctification through</hi> the <hi>imputation</hi> of <hi>his
holineſs.</hi>"</q> For 'tis ſuggeſted, that they muſt be
<hi>perfectly</hi> Holy before their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Heaven, and that they are
not made <hi>ſo</hi> in this life by the <hi>ſanctification</hi> of the
Spirit, therefore it muſt be by the <hi>imputed Holineſs</hi> of
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>That I may be the more clear in conſidering this, I humbly
apprehend it very neceſſary, that I do acquaint the <hi>vulgar,</hi> with
the true no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and <hi>Sanctification;</hi> In
order unto which, tis requiſite, that we remember<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34827:26"/>the
<hi>diſtinction,</hi> that is between the <hi>guilt,</hi> and the
<hi>filth</hi> of ſin, <hi>Juſtification</hi> reſpecting the <hi>guilt,
Sanctification</hi> the <hi>Filth</hi> of ſin; <hi>Guilt of ſin,</hi> is an
<hi>external reſpect</hi> of it with regard unto the <hi>ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of
<hi>the Law only,</hi> and is <hi>ſeparable</hi> from ſin, as the Reverend
Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> alſo hath ſhewn of Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification <hi>pag.</hi> 285.
But the <hi>Fault</hi> it <hi>ſelf,</hi> or the <hi>filth,</hi> the
<hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> of the <hi>preceptive part of the Law</hi> is the
<hi>formal nature of ſin,</hi> and is ſo <hi>intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal</hi> thereunto,
as to be <hi>inſeparable from</hi> it. <hi>Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification</hi> then makes
only an <hi>external relative-change,</hi> by removing <hi>guilt,</hi> and
giving us a <hi>right</hi> to life, and as it regards <hi>guilt,</hi> it
reſpects the <hi>paſt State; Sanctification</hi> imports an <hi>internal,
and a phyſical change</hi> by introducing <hi>new light</hi> into the the
heart, and new <hi>principles, inclinations,</hi> and <hi>propenſions towards
God,</hi> and regards the <hi>future ſtate,</hi> weakning the <hi>habits</hi>
of <hi>ſin, ſtrengthening</hi> the <hi>habits</hi> of infuſed Grace, and
thereby preventing much ſin, that otherwiſe would pollute the ſoul,
whereby the man is in <hi>part ſanctified; Juſtification</hi> is through
the <hi>blood,</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt;
Sanctification</hi> is through the <hi>working of the Spirit of</hi> the ſame
Lord Jeſus: <hi>Chriſt</hi> is our <hi>Juſtification</hi> by his
<hi>blood,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> and the ſame
<hi>Chriſt</hi> is our <hi>ſanctification</hi> by his <hi>Spirit.</hi> For
God hath choſen you to ſalvation, <hi>through the ſanctification of the
Spirit,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2.</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>filth</hi> and <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin are
diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and accordingly <hi>Juſtification</hi> and
<hi>Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation:</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:34827:26"/>But ſuch as confound the
<hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>filth</hi> of ſin with ſome<note n="*" place="margin">'Tis ſaid by one, I do not think, as ſome do, <hi>that Guilt
diſſers from ſin,</hi> as that which is an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, or a bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
over, to the Puniſhment of ſin, rather than <hi>ſin it ſelf</hi> being
paſt and gone, to be guilty, and to commit a ſin is all one, they are but
two words expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſame thing. Dr. <hi>Criſp.</hi> on
<hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
               </note> cannot but confound <hi>Juſtification</hi> and
<hi>Sanctification,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, fall into the <hi>Popiſh
error</hi> about this point; for the great error of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> in
this, lyeth much in their conſidering <hi>Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> and
<hi>Sanctification pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly,</hi> as though, the being
<hi>Juſtified</hi> did import the ſame with the being
<hi>ſanctified.</hi> Whence 'tis, that it muſt be ſeriouſly
conſidered, that <hi>Juſtification doth no way regard the filth of ſin,
as its object.</hi> Neither is the ſoul cleanſed from <hi>filth,</hi> even
in that, 'tis <hi>Juſtified;</hi> for <hi>Juſtification,</hi> as
<hi>ſuch,</hi> doth not conſiſt in the renewing of our minds, or the
making any <hi>internal-phyſical</hi>-change on our hearts, for that is the
<hi>Spirits work in our Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> and therefore it muſt be
acknowledged, That we are not made <hi>holy</hi> by Chriſt's
<hi>Holineſs,</hi> by the <hi>imputation of it, (i.e.)</hi> God doth not
judge the elect to be really and perfectly holy, becauſe Chriſt is
<hi>really and perfectly ſo;</hi> for <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> in whomſoever
'tis, imports an <hi>inward work on the ſoul.</hi> No one can be really, and
perfectly holy, but he, in whom are the <hi>habits of holineſs.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:34827:27"/>He whoſe Propenſions, Diſpoſitions, and Habits are
not holy, cannot be <hi>reputed perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy;</hi> Chriſt's Holineſs
therefore cannot be made ours, but by a <hi>transfuſion of Chriſts
Habits</hi> into our ſouls; 'tis true, <hi>Chriſts Righteouſneſs</hi>
may be <hi>given us,</hi> and after the <hi>Donation</hi> or <hi>gift
thereof,</hi> be truly <hi>reputed,</hi> and <hi>reckoned,</hi> as ours, and we
may be <hi>dealt with accordingly;</hi> but there can be no giving the
<hi>Holineſs</hi> of Chriſt unto us, in a way diſtinct from the
imputation of Righteouſneſs, but by <hi>transfuſing</hi> it into us,
which is as impoſſible, as the <hi>transfuſing of ſin</hi> from one
into another<note n="a" place="bottom">So that, underſtanding the courſe of
Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the common uſe of the phraſe of <hi>Reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and
<hi>Accounting,</hi> you ſhall find that <hi>Imputing</hi> is nothing but
Gods <hi>determination,</hi> and <hi>conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> that he doth paſs
upon things, as <hi>really</hi> and <hi>truly things are,</hi> without any
<hi>Imagining</hi> and <hi>fancying</hi> things to be ſo and ſo, when
indeed and <hi>Truth</hi> they are not ſo. Dr. <hi>Criſp.</hi> on
<hi>Iſaiah,</hi> whence if the <hi>Elect</hi> are <hi>Reputed perfectly holy
by Chriſts holineſs,</hi> the holineſs of Chriſt muſt be indeed, and
in Truth in <hi>them;</hi> for <hi>De quocunque dicitur concretum, ei in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
abſtractum. Dici de, ſequitur eſſe in.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>For the clearing this, remember that as <hi>ſin, guilt,</hi> and
<hi>Puniſhment</hi> are to be diſtinctly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, even ſo
<hi>Holineſs, Righteouſneſs</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi> But, before I
proceed to ſhew, how <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and the
<hi>Reward</hi> are to be diſtinctly conſidered, it will be meet I prove,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34827:27"/>That (although <hi>Holineſs</hi> and inherent
<hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> are the ſame, yet) there is a
<hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> ſomewhat <hi>diſtinct</hi> from
<hi>Holineſs,</hi> which is done by a due obſervation of the import of the
words <hi>Righteous</hi> and <hi>Holy;</hi> for if to be <hi>Righteous</hi> is
ſomewhat diſtinct from the being <hi>Holy,</hi> then ſurely
<hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> is ſomewhat diſtinct from <hi>Holineſs,</hi>
in that the <hi>Denominatives Righteous</hi> and <hi>Holy,</hi> are from
<hi>Righteouſneſs and Holineſs,</hi> their <hi>Denominating Forms;</hi>
for which reaſon, if <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> be
the <hi>ſame,</hi> ſince <hi>Denominativum</hi> &amp; <hi>Denominans
conveniunt in re ſignificatâ,</hi> quia <hi>ſignificant eandem formam
eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialiter,</hi> to be Righteous and to be Holy muſt be the ſame;
The ſame <hi>denominating Form, ever giving the ſame denomination:</hi> And
if to be <hi>Righteous,</hi> be not the ſame with the being <hi>Holy,</hi>
Righteouſneſs and Holineſs cannot be the <hi>ſame;</hi> But to be
<hi>Righteous,</hi> is ſomewhat diſtinct from the being <hi>Holy.</hi> To
be <hi>made Righteous,</hi> is to be <hi>declared, pronounced, judged,
eſteemed and reputed</hi> in the eye of the Law to be <hi>juſt, i.e.</hi>
to be <hi>not guilty,</hi> not <hi>liable unto the curſe due to ſin,</hi>
but to have a right unto the Reward. He is Righteous (that is,) <hi>not
guilty;</hi> He is Righteous <hi>(i.e.)</hi> He hath a <hi>right</hi> unto the
<hi>Reward.</hi> But to be made <hi>Holy</hi> is another thing, it is to be
<hi>Sanctified,</hi> which is by the <hi>infuſion</hi> of Habits into the
Soul. To be <hi>ſanctified,</hi> is to be <hi>Phyſically</hi> and
<hi>internally changed,</hi> to be inherently Holy. So that 'tis moſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34827:28"/>apparent, that there is a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the
being <hi>Righteous,</hi> and the <hi>being</hi> Holy; or between the being
<hi>made Righteous,</hi> and the being <hi>made Holy;</hi> the <hi>one</hi>
being our <hi>Juſtification,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> our
<hi>Sanctification,</hi> which do greatly differ: And therefore
<hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> as <hi>Formally</hi> and <hi>ſtrictly</hi>
conſidered, differs from <hi>Holineſs,</hi> for, otherwiſe the
<hi>imputation</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> would be the ſame with the
<hi>imputation of Holineſs,</hi> or our being made Righteous would be our
being Holy, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> by a <hi>Righteouſneſs imputed,</hi> we
ſhould be <hi>ſanctified,</hi> which is moſt untrue; it being a
confounding, <hi>Juſtification</hi> and Sanctification. A thing not to be
admitted by ſound Proteſtants; which confuſion cannot well be declined
but by our diſtinguiſhing between <hi>Holineſs</hi> and
<hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> as well as between <hi>ſin</hi> and
<hi>guilt.</hi> That there is a difference between <hi>theſe</hi> and the
<hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> is no way doubted by any.</p>
            <p>This premiſed, I proceed to the ſhewing how <hi>Holineſs,
Righteouſneſs</hi> and the <hi>Reward</hi> are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Holineſs,</hi> which is oppoſed unto the
<hi>formal</hi> nature of ſin, conſiſts in the ſouls <hi>conformity to
the preceptive part of the Law.</hi> When the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, propenſions,
thoughts, words and actions are exactly agreeable to Gods moſt <hi>holy</hi>
Law, then 'tis, that the man is <hi>Holy: Formally Holy. Chriſt's
Holineſs</hi> then conſiſts in the <hi>conſonancy,<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34827:28"/>agreeableneſs</hi> and <hi>conformity</hi> of <hi>Chriſt's
propenſions, diſpoſitions</hi> and <hi>habits unto that Law given him by
the Father,</hi> and is <hi>ſubjectively</hi> in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> The Lord
Jeſus Chriſt, exactly anſwering the whole Law, in his life was
<hi>perfectly holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> as 'tis condiſtinguiſhed
from <hi>Holineſs,</hi> regards rather the <hi>promiſſory part of the
Law,</hi> than the <hi>preceptive,</hi> it being in an eſpecial manner
oppoſed unto <hi>Guilt,</hi> as <hi>Holineſs</hi> is unto ſin; whence as
to be Guilty and Unrighteous imports one and the ſame thing, even ſo to be
<hi>Guiltleſs</hi> or <hi>Innocent,</hi> and to be <hi>Righteous.</hi> For
ſaith the Apoſtle, as by one mans diſobedience, <hi>many</hi> are made
<hi>Sinners (i.e.) guilty,</hi> even ſo by the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of <hi>one</hi>
ſhall <hi>many</hi> be made <hi>Righteous, i.e. Guiltleſs</hi> or
<hi>Innocent,</hi> free from wrath, having a Right unto the Reward:
<hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> being <hi>holineſs's reſpect unto the
promiſſory part of the Law,</hi> and is ſomewhat <hi>extrinſecal</hi>
unto holineſs and therefore can as eaſily paſs from one, unto another, as
Guilt can; and as the ſin of one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <hi>imputed</hi> unto another,
but in its <hi>Guilt,</hi> even ſo the <hi>holineſs</hi> of one, cannot be
imputed unto another, but in its <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Reward</hi> is the <hi>good thing promiſed</hi>
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Holineſs,</hi> as the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> is the evil threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
againſt ſin: And the <hi>Reward</hi> neceſſarily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth a
<hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> as the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> doth
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34827:29"/>
               <hi>Guilt.</hi> And as no puniſhment but for guilt, ſo
no <hi>Reward</hi> but for <hi>Righteouſneſs;</hi> for as <hi>Reatus</hi>
is <hi>dignitas poenae propter culpam,</hi> ſo <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> is
<hi>dignitas praemii propter obedientiam perfectam,</hi> and the Reward is for
righteouſneſs. From the whole it muſt be noted, That as <hi>Guilt,</hi>
which is ſins <hi>extrinſecal reſpect</hi> unto the <hi>threatning</hi>
of the Law, may paſs from the actual ſinner, and be made the guilt of him
who knew no ſin, without a paſſing of the actual ſin; even ſo
<hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> which is the <hi>extrinſecal reſpect of
Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> unto the <hi>promiſſory part of the Law,</hi> may paſs
from Chriſt, who is perfectly Holy, to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that is not ſo.</p>
            <p>This being ſo 'tis eaſy to conclude,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Reward</hi> of Chriſts obedience may be
actually given out unto all ſuch, as are united unto Chriſt. As the
<hi>puniſhment</hi> of mans ſin, was laid on Chriſt, even ſo the
<hi>Reward</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Holineſs</hi> ſhall be given unto the
believer. The <hi>Reward,</hi> conſidered <hi>ſtrictly,</hi> and in an
<hi>eminent manner,</hi> is the product of Chriſts
<hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> and Holineſs, it being given out, as the great
<hi>effect</hi> of Chriſts fulfilling the Law of Innocency, and not as the
<hi>merit</hi> of our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the Lord Chriſt, is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34827:29"/>given unto all ſuch, as are born of God, as do ſavingly
believe; Even <hi>as</hi> their <hi>guilt</hi> is made <hi>Chriſts, ſo
Chriſts</hi> Righteouſneſs is made <hi>their</hi> Righteouſneſs. In
which there is a <hi>non-imputation</hi> of ſin, and an <hi>actual imputation
of Righteouſneſs,</hi> God doth not proceed in Judgment with them, as with
<hi>guilty ſinners;</hi> but treats them as <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> giving them
a <hi>Right to Impunity</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> ſo that the <hi>freedom from
Puniſhment,</hi> and the <hi>eternal</hi> life is the <hi>effect</hi> of this
Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which Righteouſneſs is <hi>given</hi> unto,
and <hi>reckoned, judged</hi> and <hi>eſteemed</hi> to be the
<hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> of the believer, which can eaſily be made theirs,
as hath been already ſhewn. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Holineſs</hi> of Chriſt, was never deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by God the Father, or the Son, for the <hi>formal Sanctification</hi> of any,
For as the being <hi>juſtified</hi> or made Righteous by Chriſt's
Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, denotes an <hi>extrinſecal,</hi> an <hi>outward</hi> and
a <hi>relative change</hi> only, even ſo the being <hi>ſanctified</hi> by
Chriſts Holineſs muſt import an <hi>internal</hi> and <hi>phyſical
change,</hi> which cannot be, but by the <hi>transfuſion</hi> of the
<hi>acts</hi> or habits of Holineſs from one unto another; For
<hi>Sanctification,</hi> which moſt certainly is ſomewhat diſtinct from
<hi>juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> conſiſts in a <hi>real internal phyſical
change,</hi> done by the <hi>infuſion</hi> of new <hi>habits,</hi>
diſpoſitions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whence then it will follow, that if we are
<hi>Sanctified</hi> by Chriſts <hi>Holineſs,</hi> the <hi>Holineſs</hi>
of<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34827:30"/>Chriſt muſt be <hi>transfuſed</hi> into us, for
<hi>Holineſs</hi> is ſeated in the ſoul, as in its moſt <hi>proper
Subject.</hi> Yea, the <hi>Holineſs of Chriſt,</hi> is ſeated in the
ſoul of Chriſt, and if any are truly and perfectly holy by Chriſts
holineſs, this <hi>holineſs</hi> muſt be removed from Chriſts ſoul,
into the ſouls of ſuch as are eſteemed by the Lord to be <hi>Holy</hi> by
ſuch an Holineſs, which is. 1. <hi>Impoſſible,</hi> in that the
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> that are in Chriſt
cannot <hi>migrate,</hi> or paſs from Chriſt to us, without their
<hi>deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> 2. <hi>Abſurd</hi> and <hi>falſe,</hi> for. 1. If
the habits of Chriſts Holineſs, be removed from Chriſt, Chriſt
ceaſeth to be <hi>holy,</hi> and conſequently can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not remain a <hi>Meet
Interceſſor</hi> or <hi>Advocate</hi> on the behalf of the ſincerely
humbled ſoul. 2. The <hi>Elect</hi> are hereby ſet up above the Lord
Jeſus, in that <hi>they</hi> are <hi>perfectly holy,</hi> even when the Lord
Jeſus is void of holineſs.<note n="*" place="margin">That a thing ſhould
be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and yet be leſt behind is a flat Contradiction ſaith Dr.
<hi>Criſp.</hi>
               </note>. But if it be ſaid, that the habits of Chriſts
Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs paſs from Chriſt unto the Elect, and yet remain in Chriſt,
then an <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> may in one and the ſame inſtant, contrary to the
fulleſt evidence deſirable paſs from one Subject to another with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
deſtruction, and remain in two diſtinct Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects at one and the ſame
time, yea, in a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and can continue in being without any Subject,
that is, without what is eſſential to its<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34827:30"/>Being; but if
this be once granted 'twill follow that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,
Conſubſtantiation,</hi> and the groſſeſt of Errors and plaineſt of
<hi>Popiſh</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions may be eaſily admitted, as he
<hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt truths.</hi> Moreover what is more <hi>dangerous?</hi> If the
Elect be made perfectly Holy by Chriſt's Holineſs then 'twill follow, that
the <hi>Sanctification</hi> of the Spirit, is an <hi>uſeleſs things;</hi>
that converſion, Faith in Chriſt and repentance towards God are no way
neceſſary to our actual Salvation, for a man may be both <hi>holy</hi> and
<hi>happy</hi> without them. For conſider,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third thing. <hi>The Elect are totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from
the filth of ſin, no one ſpot remaining on them.</hi> If they were made
holy by Chriſts holineſs, and every ſpot removed by Chriſt, without the
Spirit, what remaineth to be further done by the <hi>Spirit?</hi> Your
<hi>Sanctification</hi> being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready perfected without the Spirit, the Spirit
muſt run over the ſame work, and <hi>actum agere,</hi> or ſet
<hi>idle,</hi> which is groſs: what greater deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pight can be done againſt
the Spirit of God? wherein can you offend him more? Oh conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it and
tremble! 2. If this be true, <hi>Our Preaching</hi> is in <hi>vain,
Praying</hi> of no uſe, <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances unprofitable</hi> things, though
deſigned by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt for converſion, and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, yea
for the helping on, and promoting the work of Holineſs on the Heart. But what
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34827:31"/>uſe can preaching be of, if this be true? muſt it be
for the inlightening you in the knowledg of Chriſt and for the turning you
from the power of Satan unto the moſt High? how can this be, ſince, when
you were in the Womb, Chriſts holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was made yours, and can you be
perfectly holy or can you be without the <hi>ſpot</hi> and <hi>filth</hi> of
ſin, even when the <hi>ſpot</hi> of Ignorance is on your underſtandings,
and the <hi>Filth</hi> of obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, rebellion and pride on your
<hi>wills?</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">It muſt be here remembred, That the
<hi>Filth</hi> of ſin remains on us until the habitual blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and
ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our hearts be removed; for ſince this <hi>Ignorance</hi>
on the Underſtanding and the <hi>Depraved habits of the Will,</hi> &amp;c. is
the <hi>Filth</hi> of the ſoul; the <hi>Filth,</hi> the <hi>Spot</hi>
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains, as long as theſe abide. About this conſult <hi>Bellar. de
juſtif. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>Who</hi> ſaith <hi>Quemad nodum ex
averſione à lege Dei orta eſt Macula, ita ex converſione
tollitur.</hi>
               </note> Again, why will you <hi>pray,</hi> and draw near to the
<hi>Lords Supper,</hi> for ſtrengthening grace, and fuller meaſures of
holineſs, even when you are perfect and want no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? Remember that it hath
been ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that we are Sanctified by the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:34827:31"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <argument>
               <list>
                  <item>A digreſſion concerning the <hi>actual imputation</hi> of
Chriſts Merits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to all the Elect in the
<hi>Womb.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The unſoundneſs of this notion.</item>
                  <item>The abſurd conſequences that naturally ſlow from
it.</item>
                  <item>The plain Scripture notion about our actual Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
declared.</item>
                  <item>Faith in Chriſt antecedent thereunto.</item>
                  <item>The convinced ſinner, <hi>the only Subject capable of
Juſtification.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>A return from the digreſſion, ſhewing wherein Grace is
highly glorified by ſome, and wherein abuſed by others.</item>
               </list>
            </argument>
            <p>THus, you ſee where theſe errors lead men, and <hi>how,</hi>
ſuch as do entertain <hi>one error,</hi> do but prepare they way unto
<hi>many.</hi> For that which is remarkable is this, Thoſe perſons, who
embrace the error, I have now confuted, do aſſert, that the <hi>Elect are
actually juſtified, even in the womb,</hi> though they know it not; for
ſaith one
<q rend="inline">"God laies the <hi>ſins</hi> of the Elect on the
Lord Jeſus Chriſt by <hi>Obligation, Execution</hi> and
<hi>Application;</hi> which <hi>Application,</hi> as done by the Father, is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34827:32"/>
                  <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>manifeſt: Secretly</hi> unto
particular Elect Perſons, before they come into the world, even <hi>while in
the womb,</hi> aſſoon as conceived, for which Reaſon the Lord hath no
more to lay to the charge of an Elect perſon, yet in the <hi>height of
iniquity,</hi> and in the <hi>Exceſs of Riot,</hi> and committing all the
<hi>Abominations that can be committed,</hi> even then, the Lord hath no more
to lay to that Perſons charge, than he hath to lay to the charge of a
<hi>Perſon Triumphant</hi> in Glory, though the Elect perſon knows it not,"
So Dr. <hi>Criſp.</hi> on <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Reading which, is enough to engage a tender conſcience to
abhor it. But to go on, and ſhew the <hi>unſoundneſs</hi> hereof.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Elect,</hi> aſſoon as they receive Being, are in the
ſight of God <hi>actually juſtified</hi> by this <hi>ſecret</hi>
Application of their ſins unto Chriſt, 'tis <hi>impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> that
any one Elect ſoul, can be truly conſidered as <hi>born,</hi> or as
<hi>conceiv'd,</hi> in <hi>ſin;</hi> for their <hi>concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and this
ſecret <hi>application</hi> is in one and the ſame inſtant. Neither do
they need any <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> by the Spirit, as I ſhall ſhew
immediately, neither can they be capable of a <hi>Pardon;</hi> for they are not
actually <hi>guilty,</hi> nor by nature the Children of Wrath: This is plain.
For Chriſts <hi>Holineſs</hi> being made their Holineſs, aſſoon as
they received their Being in the Womb, there<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34827:32"/>was no one
<hi>inſtant</hi> in which they were <hi>ſinners,</hi> without <hi>perfect
Holineſs;</hi> whence 'twill follow, that there is no <hi>Original
ſin,</hi> no being by nature the Children of wrath, no <hi>need of
pardon;</hi> for a <hi>pardon</hi> preſuppoſeth <hi>Guilt,</hi> as
<hi>Guilt</hi> inferreth <hi>Sin;</hi> where no <hi>Sin,</hi> their no
<hi>Guilt,</hi> no <hi>Pardon,</hi> yea, and hereby <hi>Repentance,</hi> and
<hi>Faith</hi> in the blood of Chriſt for pardon, is made of none effect. But
if it be ſaid that although the <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> and
<hi>Holineſs</hi> of Chriſt is imputed unto the <hi>Elect,</hi> aſſoon
as they receive their Being; yet the <hi>Elect</hi> may remain under the
<hi>power</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> filthy, unclean and polluted, full of
ſinful ſpots and blemiſhes. If ſo, it muſt be acknowledged. <hi>That
one and the ſame perſon, may be at one and the ſame time, a Child of
God</hi> and a <hi>Child of the Devil.</hi> 1. <hi>As Chriſts
Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> is <hi>imputed</hi> unto him,
<hi>ſo He</hi> is the Child of God, in a ſtate of grace, actually in Gods
account juſtified, having a right unto the Kingdom, the Object of Gods
ſpecial love and favour; but yet, 2. As he is under the <hi>power of
ſin,</hi> and <hi>Unclean,</hi> ſo he is the <hi>Child of the Devil,</hi>
and in a ſtate of wrath, actually unjuſtified in Gods account, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to
eternal burnings, the Object of Gods hatred, being a worker of iniquity. But
how <hi>impoſſible</hi> is this? Oh how dangerous to aſſert! what! can
a man be at one and the ſame time the <hi>Child of God,</hi> and alſo of
the <hi>Devil?</hi> He may as well, be in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> at
the <hi>ſame<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34827:33"/>time,</hi> bathing himſelf in the Rivers of
pleaſure, that run at the right hand of God for ever, even when tormented in
that lake that burneth with Fire and brimſtone. What ſtrange confuſion is
this? but they ſay that the ſin paſſing from the Elect, ceaſeth to be
the ſin of the Elect. <hi>q. d.</hi> The Elect are never in a ſtate of
ſin, or wrath though under the Power of ſin.</p>
            <p>The truth then is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is not actually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto
any under the reigning power of unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,</hi> for, he <hi>that believeth not,
is condemned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, Joh.</hi> 3.18. <hi>The wrath of God abideth on on him,
ver.</hi> 36. There is no <hi>Communication</hi> of any juſtifying, pardoning
grace to any, that are not <hi>united</hi> unto Chriſt, and whatever ſoul
is united unto Chriſt, he is <hi>ſo</hi> by <hi>Faith,</hi>
               <q rend="inline">"for, as the Reverend Dr. <hi>O.</hi> it muſt be
remembred that, we require <hi>Evangelical Faith</hi> in order of nature
<hi>antecedently</hi> unto our juſtification by the imputation of the
Righteouſneſs of Chriſt unto us, which <hi>juſtifying Faith,</hi>
includeth in its nature the <hi>entire principle of Evangelical
repentance,</hi> ſo as that it is utterly impoſſible, that a man ſhould
be a true believer, and not at the ſame inſtant of time, be <hi>truly
penitent.</hi>"</q> A man that continueth under the power of ſin, no way
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of his loſt eſtate out of Chriſt, (as is the caſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34827:33"/>of many <hi>Elect perſons,</hi> a long time, after they
are out of the Womb,) is ſo far from being <hi>actually juſtified</hi> in
the <hi>ſight of God,</hi> that he is not, while ſo, a <hi>meet Subject of
juſtification; Conviction</hi> of ſin, being a neceſſary
<hi>antecedent</hi> unto that <hi>Faith,</hi> that in order of nature goes
before juſtification, and therefore it muſt be conſidered, that a
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced ſinner,</hi> (as the ſame Reverend Dr. hath largely proved,)
is the only <hi>Subjectum capax juſtificationis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, we may clearly ſee, wherein the
<hi>Grace</hi> of God is <hi>highly glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> and <hi>wherein by</hi>
ſome 'tis <hi>greatly abuſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Tis <hi>highly glorified,</hi> in that the <hi>Son of</hi>
God, according to the <hi>eternal compact</hi> between the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son,
<hi>aſſum'd Humane Nature,</hi> made under the Law, voluntarily taking on
him the <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of our ſins, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by poor
faln man, may be freed from both, in being pardoned, and in being delivered
from the weight of that wrath, which omnipotency was to inflict: <hi>Now</hi>
the <hi>Guilty</hi> may eſcape that guilt, which tormenteth the conſciences
of many here, and which is amongſt the damned, as a <hi>Gnawing Worm,</hi>
that continually adds to their inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble horrors hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:34827:34"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:34827:34"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:34827:35"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:34827:35"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:34827:36"/>2. <hi>Free-Grace</hi> is greatly
<hi>abuſed</hi> by ſuch, as do aſſert,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>ſpots,</hi> and <hi>blemiſhes</hi> of our
ſins, are laid on Chriſt; as if he, who is infinitely <hi>pure,</hi> had
been <hi>defiled</hi> and <hi>ſtained</hi> with the <hi>Filth</hi> of our
abominations; as if <hi>infinite Wiſdom,</hi> could not find out a way to
make a diſplay of <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> in the accompliſhing faln mans
ſalvation, but by the making Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>God-Man,</hi> ſubject
unto the <hi>Pollution of ſin.</hi> Oh! How is God diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the bold
confidence of Finite mortals! who can preſume to deny the Lord to be
<hi>graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> unleſs his grace be made known in a way agreeable to
their corrupt imaginations!</p>
            <p n="2">2. To aſſert, that the <hi>Grace of God</hi> is ſuch, as
makes the <hi>Elect holy</hi> by <hi>Chriſts Holineſs,</hi> even when they
are not only ſubject to much ſin, but are under <hi>the reigning power of
the worſt of ſins,</hi> is to abuſe the <hi>Grace</hi> of God, for
theſe talk as if ſuch as are in themſelves <hi>impure, unclean,</hi> and
<hi>unholy</hi> could, <hi>while ſo,</hi> be <hi>eſteemed by the
Father</hi> of our bleſſed Jeſus, as <hi>clean, pure</hi> and
<hi>holy;</hi> or, as if God could not ſet forth the <hi>Excellency</hi> of
his Grace any other way, than by lying under many a miſtake. <hi>Theſe</hi>
notwithſtanding their pretence of exulting <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> denying the
<hi>Omniſcience,</hi> or <hi>Infinite knowledge</hi> of him, who is
<hi>All-wiſe;</hi> and<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34827:36"/>repreſenting the <hi>Infallible
God,</hi> as liable to <hi>error</hi> do ſadly abuſe
<hi>Free-Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To ſuggeſt, that <hi>Free-Grace</hi> is <hi>glorified
in the actual imputing Chriſts righteouſneſs unto any, while in
unbelief,</hi> as if the ſwearer or Sabbath breaker, the drunkard, or unclean
perſon, that delights in fornication and adultery, might, while ſo, be an
actual partaker of the ſpecial bleſſings of God; or as if the
<hi>Sanctification of the Spirit,</hi> had been no way neceſſary to our
Salvation; is a ſad abuſe of <hi>Grace,</hi> tending to the great
diſhonour of the infinite <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>purity of God.</hi>
But ſince <hi>God</hi> is not only <hi>Gracious,</hi> but alſo is
<hi>moſt holy, Grace is</hi> not, it <hi>cannot</hi> be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, but in a
way conſiſtent with the glory of Divine <hi>Purity</hi> and
<hi>Holineſs.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Some there are, who <hi>magnifie the Free-Grace of God, by
concealing that glorious diſcovery God hath made thereof in our Lord
Jeſus;</hi> theſe are they, who contend for the <hi>actual juſtification
of all the Elect from Eternity,</hi> as if Jeſus Chriſt died to procure
<hi>that</hi> for the Elect, which they had before the Worlds were made; or as
if the <hi>decree of God, his electing Will,</hi> an <hi>Immanent act,</hi> had
been <hi>tranſient</hi> in the actual creating, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and ſaving
all the Elect from eternity, (that is) as if they had been created millions of
years before there was any <hi>creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:34827:37"/>Thus men on pretence of lifting up the
<hi>Free-Grace</hi> of God, do not only trouble the Churches with their
confuſion and variety of contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but morcover do lightly eſteem
the greateſt <hi>Inſtance</hi> of Free-Grace, the <hi>Elect</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>re capable of receiving,
<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Love of God in Chriſt. For hereby God commendeth his
Love to us, that while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt died for us,</hi> Rom.
5.8. Again <hi>God SO loved the World that he gave his only begotten Son,
Joh.</hi> 3.16. and without blood no Remiſſion.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There are others, who in their abuſe of Free-Grace, do
<hi>greatly reproach the Spirit of Chriſt, and of God the Father of our Lord
Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> by aſſerting that <hi>the Elect are actually
Juſtified in the womb, even before they do believe,</hi> yea, while they are
in a ſtate of darkneſs, and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to the powerful working of Gods holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Theſe
are they who inſiſt on <hi>Faith,</hi> as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>only</hi> for
the procuring the knowledge of that juſtification, which they actually had
before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. But how do theſe men
<hi>ſin againſt the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of God, by reproaching its works, as if
the <hi>gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> of the
<hi>Spirit,</hi> had been of no <hi>eſteem;</hi> as if our <hi>Faith</hi> and
<hi>Repentance,</hi> our <hi>Love to God</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lking</hi> according to the Goſpel of our
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Redeemer, had <hi>been our
ſin!</hi> Tis true, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> doth
conſider the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and the Apoſtle concluded,<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34827:37"/>that his righteouſneſs, which was not done in Faith, to be as
<hi>dung,</hi> in compariſon of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Chriſt: And
ſurely <hi>becauſe of the many imperfections</hi> that <hi>attend our
beſt performances,</hi> we have cauſe to be humbled daily before the Lord
and to apply our ſelves to the blood, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Chriſt, for
pardoning mercy. But yet it muſt be ſtill aſſerted, that <hi>there is a
difference between thoſe graces, that are the work of God's ſpirit in
us,</hi> and the <hi>imperfections which proceed from the remains of our old
corruption,</hi> for that which is the <hi>work of God's Spirit,</hi> as
ſuch, is not <hi>dung,</hi> nor <hi>droſs,</hi> nor <hi>filth,</hi> nor
<hi>ſtinking rags,</hi> much leſs <hi>filthy ſins.</hi> The Spirit of God
is the <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and other graces;
but the <hi>Spirit of God is not the Author of ſin and filth.</hi> The
<hi>giving grace to the ſoul,</hi> is the <hi>renewing the Image of God on
the ſoul;</hi> but the <hi>image of God doth</hi> not <hi>conſiſt</hi> in
<hi>ſin,</hi> and <hi>filth,</hi> and <hi>ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rags.</hi> The
<hi>believer,</hi> in being a partaker of the graces of God's ſpirit, is a
<hi>partaker</hi> of <hi>the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature,</hi> but <hi>the divine nature is
not compoſed of ſin,</hi> or <hi>any filthy thing:</hi> 'Tis <hi>our
duty</hi> to <hi>believe in Chriſt, to love God,</hi> &amp;c. but, <hi>'tis
not our duty to ſin,</hi> or <hi>wallow in any ſpiritual
uncleanneſs.</hi> Whence then, ſuch as do deny the <hi>neceſſity of
ſaith in or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der to our being actually juſtified;</hi> or ſuch as do
<hi>reproach the working of Gods holy ſpirit,</hi> calling what is <hi>holy,
unholy,</hi> what is <hi>pure, impure; revil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> the <hi>divine nature,
reproaching Gods image,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:34827:38"/>on pretence of exalting free
grace, do greatly ſin, in abuſing a great inſtance of free grace
<hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>holy Spirit's work,</hi> unto <hi>which we are
infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely obliged.</hi> For 'tis the Spirit that doth <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, carry
on,</hi> and <hi>finiſh</hi> the work of Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on the ſoul;
whence, although, while we are in this life, our <hi>Sanctification</hi> is but
<hi>imperfect,</hi> yet there is not one ſoul in Heaven one inſtant without
<hi>perfect holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, it may be, you'l quaery how it can be, that the ſoul, which,
while on earth, is but <hi>imperfectly ſanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>fied,</hi> ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>perfectly purged</hi> from the <hi>filth</hi> of ſin when in Heaven? I
Anſwer. There are ſeveral ſorts of men, who talk, as if they had been
fully acquainted with the whole counſel of God, and as if they could give a
particular account of the <hi>methods</hi> of <hi>divine operations;</hi> hence
ſome are confident enough to aſſert <hi>that the perfect purgati-on of
the filth of ſin, muſt be either by the Spirit in this life,</hi> or <hi>by
a purgatory fire in the other.</hi> The one aſſerts <hi>perfection,</hi>
not only of <hi>parts,</hi> but of <hi>degrees</hi> attainable <hi>here,</hi>
and conſequently denies the <hi>neceſſity of Ordinances,</hi> &amp;c. The
<hi>other</hi> viz. the <hi>Papiſts</hi> conclude, that as ſome arrive to
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection here, others do not, e're they arrive un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>purgatery</hi>
ſire, but the <hi>Antinomian</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes to ſay, that our <hi>perfect
Sanctification</hi> muſt. be by <hi>Chriſt's Holineſs,</hi> even as our
<hi>compleat Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification</hi> is by <hi>Chriſts Righteouſneſs.</hi>
But I have<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34827:38"/>already ſhewn, That our <hi>perfect
Sanctification,</hi> which conſiſts in the removal of the filth of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
ſin is not done by the <hi>Holineſs of Chriſt:</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it
poſſible, that any <hi>material flames</hi> ſhould be
<hi>adjuſted,</hi> for the cleanſing the ſoul, which is a <hi>Being
ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>Immaterial: Materiale non agit in immateriale.</hi> It
is done then by the <hi>Spirit;</hi> when? not <hi>in this life,</hi> for until
the <hi>body of Sin</hi> be put off, there will be the <hi>remainders of old
luſts,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Note, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.46.
<hi>Prov.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.20. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8. No meer man
ſince the Fall ever arriv'd unto a ſtate of ſinleſs perfection in this
life.</note>. which are inconſiſtent with a Sanctification, that is
<hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> with a <hi>perfection of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees.</hi> Doth it, (you, it may
be, will ſay) enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Heaven with its imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections <hi>(i.e.)
Spots</hi> and <hi>Filth? Anſ.</hi> No ſurely, for no <hi>Spot</hi> can
have an admittance into that <hi>holy place.</hi> Doth the departed ſoul make
its ſtay af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it paſſeth from the body, e're it enter Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?
<hi>Anſ.</hi> The ſtay cannot be long, for ſaid Jeſus Chriſt to the
<hi>Thief</hi> on the Croſs, <hi>This day thou ſhalt be with me in
Paradiſe,</hi> Who ſtood in need of as long a ſtay for a <hi>further
Sanctification,</hi> as any, his converſion being juſt then; How then is
it? I anſwer, That ſince 'tis certain, <hi>That 'tis the Spirits work to
ſanctify,</hi> which <hi>work is not perfected while</hi> the ſoul is in
the body, and yet <hi>enters into Heaven perfect,</hi> we ſhould ſatisfy
our ſelves with theſe plain truths, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſearch into the
<hi>ſecrets</hi> of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34827:39"/>ſince the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, on the ſouls par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the
body of ſin, can in a <hi>moment per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Sanctify it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for your fuller Satisfaction</p>
            <p>Conſider, That the <hi>Tyrant Sin,</hi> hath its <hi>uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
Throne,</hi> in our <hi>members,</hi> in our <hi>body,</hi> the
<hi>fleſh</hi> (which is the true reaſon, why the <hi>Elect</hi> in the
<hi>body,</hi> are not <hi>perfectly ſanctified</hi>) and you will ſuddenly
be engaged to conclude, <hi>That our ſanctification may be immediately
perfected, on the ſouls freedom from the body.</hi> If the <hi>body</hi> of
<hi>ſin,</hi> be the hinderer of our perfect Sanctification, how eaſily may
our perfect Sanctification be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, when once we are freed from the
<hi>body of this death?</hi> Remember the <hi>guilt</hi> of ſin being removed
by the <hi>Blood of Chriſt, a Right to Glory</hi> purchaſed by his
Righteouſneſs, and <hi>through the Sanctification of the Spirit</hi> all
the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and powers of the ſoul</hi> being <hi>exactly confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable
to the Rule given 'em,</hi> by the Lord, which is done on the ſouls leaving
the body, caſting off its <hi>Chains</hi> and Fetters, nothing remains but
<hi>that the ſoul immediately at death may go to God.</hi> Read ſeriouſly
the 7th. of the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:34827:39"/>
            <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Glory of Gods Free-Grace further diſcovered;
<hi>in</hi> ſeveral propoſitions. Grace how ſhewn unto mankind in
General. The greatneſs and exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſs thereof. Common Grace offered
unto more than the Elect. Special Grace to ſome on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>This</hi>
Irreſiſtible, without the laying any violence on our faculties: Man,
<hi>though paſſive in</hi> converſion, <hi>yet</hi> not ſo
<hi>paſſive, as pure mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Several other Goſpel truths evinced.
The Uſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>FRom what hath been ſaid, it evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that although our
bleſſed <hi>Redeemer,</hi> was never <hi>polluted,</hi> or any <hi>way
defiled</hi> by the ſins of the Elect, yet in order to the glorifying
<hi>Free-Grace,</hi> conſiſtently with the magnifying the <hi>Juſtice,
Truth, Faithfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>infinite Wiſdom</hi> of God, it was
neceſſary, that the Lord Jeſus ſhould take on him the <hi>guilt</hi> of
our iniquities, which being done 'twas but <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> in God
the Father, to lay on him <hi>all</hi> thoſe <hi>ſorrows</hi> he underwent:
A particular conſideration whereof, cannot but deeply affect the ſouls of
truly, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and ſound believers. But I muſt haſten to what I
deſign further on this ſubject, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34827:40"/>on
ſome of thoſe <hi>ſpecial Bleſſings</hi> that are the purchaſe of
Chriſts blood. All which, for the greater clearneſs, I ſhall lay down in
ſeveral <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions,</hi> paſſing by thoſe which are moſt
evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and making my ſtay only in explicating and <hi>confirming</hi>
ſuch as may ſeem to ſome obſcure.</p>
            <p>Propoſ. 1.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>on the account of Chriſt's ſufferings in
humane nature all mankind is, in ſome ſenſe,</hi> ſo <hi>far redeemed
from that miſery,</hi> in <hi>which, antecedently unto the Promiſe of
Chriſt's death,</hi> they <hi>did lie, that they are now in a much more happy
condition than the faln Angels,</hi> not <hi>only upon the account of their
receiving at leaſt a temporarie reprieve</hi> from everlaſting flames, but
alſo becauſe their <hi>Salvation</hi> is become <hi>poſſible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EXPLICATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faln man,</hi> antecedently unto the promiſe of the
Meſſiah, being in as helpleſs, and as deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately miſerable
condition, as the <hi>Devils</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and as unable to ſatisfie
divine juſtice, any other way, than by remaining in chains of darkneſs for
ever, <hi>Chriſt's ſufferings</hi> afford that<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34827:40"/>relief
unto <hi>all</hi> mankind, as to deliver them from this miſery that is ſo
deſperate; for their <hi>ſalvation</hi> is not now as
<hi>impoſſible,</hi> as it was before the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Lord Jeſus:
For the Lord Chriſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying infinite juſtice, no one man can truly
ſay, that the reaſon why he periſhed is becauſe there was <hi>not
enough</hi> in the <hi>blood of Chriſt to ranſom him:</hi> for whoſoever
doth ſincerely believe, ſhall be actually <hi>redeemed</hi> from the wrath
to come. Our remaining in our ſin is the great reaſon, why the wrath of God
abideth on us; ſo St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> that great enemie to
<hi>Pelagianiſm,</hi> ſo much envied by the <hi>Arminians.</hi>
               <q rend="inline">"Quod ergo ad <hi>magnitudinem</hi> et <hi>potentiam
pretii;</hi> &amp; quod ad unam pertinet cauſam generis humani: <hi>Sanguis
Chriſti Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptio eſt totius mundi,</hi> ſed qui hoc ſeculum, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
ſide Chriſti, &amp; ſine regenerationis ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, pertranſeunt,
<hi>redemptionis alieni ſunt.</hi>" <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> ad Artic. ſibi
impoſit. ad Artic. 1.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Again,
<q rend="inline">"Sed hoc inter <hi>malos homines,</hi> et
<hi>Daemones</hi> diſtat: quod hominibus etiam valde malis ſupereſt, ſi
Deus miſereatur, <hi>Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio:</hi> Daemonibus nulla ſervata
<hi>eſt converſio.</hi>" Auſt. ubi ſup. ad Art. 6.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That what Perſon ſoever doth ſavingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
ſincerely repent, and is really a ſound con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, ſhall actually be
ſaved in the day of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 55.1. Mark 16.16. Joh. 3.16.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34827:41"/>Joh. 7.37. 1 Tim 2.3,4. Rev. 3.20. Rev. 22.17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the helps vouchſafed unto all for the ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
us ſavingly to believe, and ſincerely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, are ſuch as will leave
all thoſe who, believe not, inexcuſable.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They who receive <hi>leaſt,</hi> receiving one ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,
have given them <hi>ſufficient</hi> for the enabling them to do <hi>more</hi>
towards the ſaving their ſouls, than they <hi>actually do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If thoſe men do <hi>actually improve</hi> the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
helps</hi> vouchſafed them, they <hi>may, for ought any man can prove to the
contrary,</hi> receive ſuch further aſſiſtances, as may have a
<hi>ſpecial influence</hi> in enabling them to turn ſincerely unto God,
through Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For, there is in <hi>Scripture,</hi> as a motive to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
repentance, a <hi>who can tell,</hi> a <hi>may be,</hi> or <hi>who knoweth
but,</hi> or a <hi>perhaps</hi> the Lord may be gracious, <hi>Joel</hi>
2.13.14. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.15. <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi> 3.8,9. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.3.
<hi>Acts</hi> 8.22. Call theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <hi>half-Promiſes,</hi> or not,
the encouragement they afford <hi>all</hi> to improve the received talents, is
as great as is given any, to engage in <hi>worldly affairs.</hi> What greater
motive hath the <hi>Seeds-man</hi> to ſow his ſeed, than a <hi>May be</hi>
he ſhall meet with a good harveſt? what moves the <hi>Merchant</hi> to
ſend a<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34827:41"/>conſiderable part of his eſtate beyond Seas,
but a <hi>perhaps</hi> there may be a good return? what ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated
<hi>Jacob</hi> in his great diſtreſſes to go on, when he feared that his
Brother <hi>Eſau</hi> deſigned the deſtroying him, but a
<hi>peradventure</hi> he will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of me? <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.26. What was the
motive <hi>Jeremiah</hi> gave <hi>Baruch</hi> to read in the roll the words of
the Lord in the ears of the People, but <hi>It may be</hi> they will preſent
their ſupplications before the Lord, and return? or what other encouragement
did the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf give <hi>Jeremiah</hi> to Preach unto <hi>Judah,</hi>
but <hi>It may be</hi> the houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> will hear all the evil
that I purpoſe to do unto them, that they may return every man from the evil
of his way? <hi>Jer.</hi> 36.2,3,6 &amp; 7. And is a <hi>may be,</hi> a
<hi>peradventure,</hi> powerful enough to raiſe the hearts of men to great
undertakings, as to the things of this life, and yet not <hi>ſufficient</hi>
to oblige us to act for <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>glory?</hi> or doth this <hi>may
be</hi> prove a motive ſufficient to engage the Miniſters of Chriſt to
endeavour the ſalvation of precious and immortal ſouls, and yet
<hi>inſufficient</hi> for the moving you to the doing any thing for your
ſelves? ſurely this <hi>may be</hi> doth not argue only a
<hi>Poſſibility,</hi> but moreover a great <hi>Probability:</hi> Thou art
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O man! inexcuſable, if thou neglecteſt thy duty, and wilt not
ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate, ſince by ſtriving, thou
<hi>mayſt</hi> have an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the heavenly glory given thee; 'tis
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34827:42"/>
               <hi>poſſible,</hi> 'tis <hi>probable;</hi> but if thou
wilt not ſtrive for Heaven, nothing more ſure, than that <hi>Hell will be
thy portion.</hi> Oh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe things and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<note n="*" place="margin">Si ergo à Juſtitia &amp; pietate
quis deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, ſuo in praeceps fertur arbitrio; ſuâ
concupiſcentià tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hitur; ſua perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione decipitur. <hi>Aug.
Reſp.</hi> ad Art. ſibi impoſ. ad Art. 13.</note>That if you die in your
ſins, <hi>your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> will be of your ſelves, you will be
<hi>found ſelf-condemned ſinners,</hi> to whom the Lord may ſay, <hi>How
often would I have gathered you together,</hi> but <hi>you would not! Man's
ſin,</hi> and conſequently <hi>his ruine</hi> is <hi>from himſelf,</hi>
and not from the Lord, <hi>ſo.</hi>—<q rend="inline">"Quae mala cum homines admittunt, ſuis
concupiſcentiis &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piditatibus ſerviunt, quas ab illa prima
volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tariae praevaricationis <hi>labe traxerunt.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Such is the corruption of humane nature, ſince the
fall, as engageth all mankind to ſlight, neglect, ſcorn, contemn, and
obſtinately to deſpiſe all the common helps offered us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It muſt be acknowledged, that <hi>man</hi> after the fall remains
a <hi>man,</hi> whence whatever is <hi>eſſential</hi> unto the humane
nature, as <hi>ſuch,</hi> is to be found in <hi>him,</hi> (i.e.) <hi>man</hi>
is ſtill a <hi>living, rational crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> his ſoul is ſtill
ennobled with the powers or faculties of <hi>underſtanding,</hi> and
<hi>will,</hi> he is capable of <hi>knowing</hi> and <hi>willing.</hi> Theſe
faculties<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34827:42"/>are not totally eradicated, or rooted out of the
ſoul, for that would be to deſtroy it. <hi>Man</hi> is ſtill
<hi>man,</hi> but a <hi>corrupt man,</hi> that is, though the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
powers</hi> and faculties remain, yet they are ſadly vitiated, in that they
are become the <hi>ſeat</hi> of <hi>vicious propenſions,
diſpoſitions,</hi> and <hi>habits:</hi> For the <hi>Underſtanding</hi>
hath not only loſt its <hi>primogeneal, directive light,</hi> and become
darkneſs, but the <hi>will</hi> is alſo ſtrangely <hi>corrupted,</hi> not
in the <hi>Arminian</hi> ſenſe alone as the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi>
expreſs it,<note n="*" place="margin">Act. Scrip. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. min. Remonſt. in
Explic. 3. et. 4. art. de Grat. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> who ſay,
<q rend="inline">"Quare li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatem volendi indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renter tam bonum
ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, quam malum in ſtatu lapſûs voluntati adeſſe negamus,
quin potius <hi>liberum Arbitrium</hi> ad bona iſtiuſmodi non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
vulneratum, ſauciatum, infirmatum, incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum &amp; attenuatum eſt, ſed
&amp; <hi>Captivatum, perditum,</hi> &amp; <hi>amiſſum, vireſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
ejus non modo <hi>debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatae</hi> &amp; <hi>caſſae</hi> niſi
reſtaurentur à gratia, ſed &amp; <hi>nul.</hi>"</q>
               <hi>Free-will</hi> to what is ſavingly good (ſay they) is not only
<hi>wounded,</hi> and <hi>weakned,</hi> but without a gracious reſtauration
altogether <hi>loſt,</hi> (i.e.) the <hi>Underſtanding</hi> having loſt
its <hi>directive light,</hi> and the <hi>will</hi> being a <hi>blind
power,</hi> cannot embrace what is ſavingly good, not becauſe of any
<hi>weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> in the faculty of the <hi>will,</hi> but for want of a a
<hi>Guide</hi> to direct it.
<q rend="inline">"In lapſu boni ſalutaris et ſalvifici
cognitione deſtituta mens, nequaquam illud ut volendum voluntati monſtrare
potuit, <pb n="72" facs="tcp:34827:43"/>nec voluntas illud velle."</q> But this is
<hi>unſound,</hi> for the weakneſs of the <hi>will,</hi> is not meerly
becauſe of the <hi>blindneſs</hi> of the <hi>underſtanding,</hi> but,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis ſo <hi>ſubjected</hi> unto <hi>vitious, propenſions,
diſpoſitions,</hi> and <hi>habits.</hi> The heart of man na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally runneth
out after ſin, 'tis bent to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit evil, 'tis obſtinately reſolved
againſt what is ſavingly good, and therefore <hi>morally impotent;</hi> men
ſin becauſe they <hi>will</hi> ſin, as appears both from Scripture and
experience. <hi>You will not come unto me</hi> that ye may have life, you will
have none of my counſel, you <hi>will not</hi> return, you are a
ſtiff-neck'd people, obſtinate and rebellious, whence the <hi>common
aſſiſtances</hi> of Gods Spirit proves <hi>ineffectual</hi> and if God
did not Glorify <hi>Free-Grace</hi> any further, <hi>none,</hi> not the
<hi>Elect</hi> would return unto God, for although <hi>Common Grace</hi> given
unto all, is ſufficient to leave all men without excuſe, their
<hi>non-improvement</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſin; yet none are <hi>thereby</hi>
effectually en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to turn unto God in Faith, no not the <hi>Elect, who,</hi>
while unregenerate, are as ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſtinate, as any; <hi>their
ſouls</hi> being as much polluted with Ignorance, ſinfull defections,
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations and habits, as others, <hi>who</hi> are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Children of
Wrath, as others, and for the ſame reaſon, <hi>who</hi> are by nature, as
<hi>ſinful</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious</hi> as others. Who more vile than
<hi>Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeh</hi> in unregeneracy? and who made more havock of the Church
of Chriſt, than <hi>Paul</hi> did<pb n="73" facs="tcp:34827:43"/>in the days of his
Ignorance? Should the Lord leave all the Sons of men to themſelves, they
would (notwithſtanding the <hi>Common Grace</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded them) run on in
ſin to their eternal ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. Wherefore,</p>
            <p n="5">5. As <hi>God did from Eternity in himſelf deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi>
and by <hi>Covenant engage to give unto our Lord Jeſus, a Select number, even
ſo, in time God glorifieth the freeneſs of his grace, and ſhews himſelf
faithful, in giving ſome unto Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoever duly obſerves what hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid concerning
<hi>Election,</hi> and the <hi>Covenant of Reconciliation made between the
Father and the Son,</hi> cannot believe the Lord to be a God of truth, the
faithful one, and not conſent unto this.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That thoſe who are given to the Lord Jeſus
Chriſt, are by SPECIAL grace moſt powerfully, yet ſweetly drawn unto him
by the Father.</hi> For none cometh unto <hi>Chriſt, but whom</hi> the Father
draweth.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>God the Father, giving this Select Number unto
Chriſt,</hi> they <hi>are by Faith through the Spirit united unto
Chriſt.</hi> For <hi>God</hi> in drawing and giving them unto Chriſt, gives
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> unto them. They by
being gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34827:44"/>unto Chriſt, are taken into Covenant with
Chriſt, <hi>they</hi> are <hi>Chriſts,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is
<hi>theirs;</hi> the <hi>Union</hi> between <hi>them</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> being a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Union,</hi> that is <hi>real</hi> but
<hi>myſtical.</hi> That Lord Chriſt, that is offered unto <hi>all</hi> upon
their believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, is <hi>actually</hi> given unto <hi>theſe;</hi> and as
<hi>all</hi> may have Chriſt if they believe, <hi>theſe believe</hi> that
they may have Chriſt; God, of his infinitely Free-Grace, makes theſe a
<hi>willing People</hi> in the day of his power. Whence all that do turn from
the evil of their ways, they muſt aſcribe the whole glory to God, <hi>even
to the praiſe</hi> of his <hi>Grace</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <p>
                     <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>inde, quoniam,
Demino in te miſericorditer ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>, jam cidiciſti, in abundantia divitiarum tuarum, non Gloriari:
hoc ſupereſt, ut</hi> non confidas in virtute tua: <hi>(i.e.) ne dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>tes v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ripus tuis, quod ſeculi facultates divitiasque contemans;
&amp;—quod viam mandato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Dei currere
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Haec enim omnia
<hi>nullatenus haberes; niſi a Deo, manere Gratuitae Donationis, acciperes.
Non hoc homini dat natura; ſed Gratia: Non hoc ex qual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> te condition is humanae habetur, ſed ex benignitate
divinae illuminationis acquiritur,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again <hi>Quicquid habes bonae voluntatis, vel bonae
operationis, Deo aſſigna, qui dedit Fulgent. de converſ. ad Theod.</hi>
Epiſt. 6. towards the end.</p>
               </note>.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To aſſert, <hi>That any, while in unregeneracy, may be
united unto Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>that any, who ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly believe, may not be
united unto Chriſt, is moſt falſe, unſound, and dangerouſly
abſurd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:34827:44"/>1. To be <hi>unregenerate,</hi> is to
abide in a ſtate of ſin, altogether <hi>Unclean, Filthy</hi> and
<hi>Polluted,</hi> at a diſtance from God and Jeſus Chriſt; how then can
theſe be <hi>One?</hi> what, is Chriſt joyned to an Harlot? or can light
have any <hi>Union or Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> with darkneſs?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>A believer</hi> doth cloſe with Chriſt, which
cannot be without <hi>Union.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Tis both unneceſſary, and unprofitable to
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute about a moment or inſtant of nature; as to the precedency of Faith
unto Union, or of Union unto Faith.</hi> e. g. <hi>whether Faith, or the
Union,</hi> is in <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of nature firſt; it being evident, that there is
no inſtant ſuppoſable, in which, a ſoul, who hath ſaving Faith, is
not united unto Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>in which One united unto Chriſt hath
not ſound</hi> ſaving Faith. But</p>
            <p n="10">10. This <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>this union</hi> is in
<hi>order of nature antecedent</hi> to an <hi>actual imputation of Chriſts
Righteouſneſs,</hi> and conſequently, <hi>before our actual
Juſtification in the ſight of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Communion</hi> preſuppoſeth <hi>Union;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<hi>Union</hi> muſt <hi>precede an actual imputation,</hi> which is but the
<hi>Communication of Chriſts Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto us. Faith</hi> and
<hi>Union</hi> being <hi>Simul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanecus,</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:34827:45"/>and at one and
the ſame inſtant, as <hi>Union,</hi> even ſo <hi>Faith,</hi> muſt
precede the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> of Chriſts Righteouſneſs, and our
actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al juſtification in the ſight of God thereby.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>This Faith, which doth ſo neceſſarily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede,
and go before the actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al juſtification of a ſinner,</hi> is <hi>the
<note n="†" place="margin">Fidem autem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, Donum Dei
eſſe fateamur; ſine enj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s
Gratiâ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> currit ad gratiam.
<hi>Proſper. Aq. Reſp. ad Gal. Object.</hi> ad Obj. 8.</note>gift of God,
infus'd into the ſoul by the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that doth irreſiſtibly carry
on its work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Grace</hi> being the <hi>gift of God,</hi> the firſt
thing which the ſoul is capable of in the work of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, or
converſion is the <hi>receiving</hi> the gift, or infuſed habit; the ſoul
doth <hi>recipere effectum agentis,</hi> which is as much as, <hi>Pati,</hi>
whence the ſoul, the <hi>firſt inſtant</hi> or moment of converſion,
muſt be conſidered as <hi>paſſive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>Converting Grace</hi> is
<hi>irreſiſtible;</hi> which may be evinced to any unprejudiced mind, that
will but conſider, that <hi>antecedently</hi> unto conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the ſoul
is obſtinately bent towards ſin. The <hi>inclinations of the will,</hi> are
continually evil, averſe to what is good, and both <hi>actually</hi> and
<hi>habitually</hi> determined to vanity, for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the
<hi>Spirit,</hi> in carrying on the work of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, meets with great
oppoſition from the<pb n="77" facs="tcp:34827:45"/>
               <hi>ſinner;</hi> yea, with ſuch
oppoſition, as would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together impede and hinder the Spirits work, had not
the <hi>power of</hi> the Spirit been <hi>great enough</hi> to <hi>conquer</hi>
and <hi>overcome this habitual obſtinacy of the will;</hi> but the
<hi>power</hi> of God's Spirit being <hi>greater</hi> than <hi>that</hi> of the
<hi>Sinner,</hi> the <hi>Sinner</hi> is <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome,</hi> and converted. How?
but by that <hi>Grace</hi> that is <hi>Irreſiſtible;</hi> it being moſt
evident, that 'tis <hi>naturally impoſſible for finite power to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail
againſt what is infinite;</hi> So clear 'tis, that <hi>converting grace is
irreſiſtible:</hi> And ſurely, had it not been <hi>ſo,</hi> never one
obſtinate ſinner, no, not one child of <hi>Adam</hi> (ſince all are by
nature obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately rebellious ſinners) would be converted, for ſuch is
the nature of our corrupt wills, that they will never yield, until overcome by
an <hi>overſtrong</hi> and <hi>irreſiſtible power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. This <hi>infuſed Irreſiſtible grace is given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Adult, ordinarily in the uſe of means, as the preaching of the</hi> word,
&amp;c. <hi>Whence man though paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive in the firſt moment of his
converſion, yet, not ſo paſſive as ſome</hi> ſuggeſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be noted, that Man in converſion is not ſo
<hi>paſſive</hi> as a Stone when thrown up into the Air: For the infuſion
of Grace, being into a <hi>Soul,</hi> that is, <hi>active life,</hi> to the end
the Soul may be the better prepared for action, the Soul muſt be alſo
<hi>active</hi> in the great work of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The infuſion of Grace
into the ſoul, that is, <hi>active life,</hi> is not like the infuſion of
the ſoul<pb n="78" facs="tcp:34827:46"/>into the body, that is, <hi>antecedently</hi> to
its receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſoul <hi>wholly unactive, purely paſſive;</hi> No, the
Lord doth conſider the <hi>nature,</hi> he hath giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en <hi>beings,</hi> and
his actions towards ſuch <hi>beings</hi> are <hi>ſuitable to their
natures.</hi> As a meer paſſive thing is purely paſſive in its
receptions, even ſo what is <hi>eſſentially active,</hi> cannot but be
<hi>active</hi> in its <hi>receptions.</hi> To inſiſt on <hi>niceties</hi>
concerning the oppoſition that is between <hi>action</hi> and
<hi>paſſion,</hi> and conſequently on the <hi>ſeeming
inconſiſtency,</hi> ſome may judge to be, in this expreſſion
<hi>active reception,</hi> q. d. <hi>active paſſion,</hi> is but to
<hi>quibble;</hi> ſince 'tis <hi>impoſſible</hi> to ſuppoſe an
<hi>Eſſentially-active-being</hi> to be in every regard, as
<hi>paſſive</hi> as <hi>pure matter</hi> is. <hi>God</hi> carries on the
work of converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on man, in a way agreeable unto that nature God hath
given him; which is by <hi>inlightening the underſtanding,</hi> and by
<hi>ſuſcitating,</hi> and <hi>ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the powers of the ſoul to
their being duly converſant about their proper objects, influencing,</hi> and
<hi>enabling</hi> the <hi>will</hi> to <hi>cloſe with</hi> what is
<hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the word,</hi> as <hi>good,</hi> and accordingly
<hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and believed to be ſo. Although</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not comprehend
how, yet nothing more evident, than that <hi>God doth irreſiſtibly, and yet
moſt ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without laying any violence on our faculties, draw us from
ſin unto Jèſus Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">This notion is
agreeable to the Sentiments of the Schoolmen, as <hi>Marius Scrib.</hi> de lib.
Arb. diſp. 19.<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34827:46"/>qu. 8. doth aſſert. <hi>Dionyſ.
Carthuſianus</hi> in 2. d. 39. q. 2. <hi>Capreolus</hi> d. 45. q. 1. Concl,
5. <hi>Ferrarienſis</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo contr. Gent. c. 88. <hi>Dreido</hi> opuſc.
lib. de concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Lib. arb. et praed eſtinationis 2. p. c. 3. ad pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum.
All theſe reconciling humane Liberty with the <hi>Irreſiſtable Divine
Will</hi> thus. Dicunt enim Dei voluntatem et providentiam Dei tantae eſſe
virtutis &amp; efficaciae, ut licet <hi>et nulla potentia &amp; libertas
refiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere</hi> valeat, omnes tamen cauſas, quibus coopera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,
<hi>ſuaviter</hi> moveat, infinitae ſiquidem eſt <hi>virtutis</hi> &amp;
<hi>ſapientiae,</hi> &amp; cum fit infinitae <hi>Sapientiae, ſcit omnia
ſuaviter diſponere,</hi> licet nobis videantur factu im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilia: cum
verò infinitae ſit virtutis attingit à fine uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad
finem fortiter, ita ut per infinitam ſuam virtutem ſciat etiam, quae
videntur diſſonantia, concordare: et propter Sapientiam ſine praejudicio
humanae libertatis effectum ſuae voluntatis ſemper ſortiri. Et
<hi>Cajetanus</hi> iiſdem pene id videtur profite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. 1. p. q. 4. a 23. &amp;
9.19. ar. 8. docens quod <hi>talis</hi> eſt <hi>cooperatio</hi> primae
cauſae, quod <hi>diſponit omnia ſuavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> juxta ſcil. modum
cujusque, <hi>cooperans unicuique.</hi> So <hi>Auſtin.</hi> Et hoc eſt opus
ejus, quo continet omnia, &amp; quo ejus ſapientia pertendit à fine
uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad finem <hi>fortiter,</hi> et diſponit <hi>omnia
ſuaviter.</hi> lib. 4. de Gen. ad lit. c. 12.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>Irreſiſtible</hi> grace is given ordinarily in
the uſe of means, <hi>viz.</hi> the preaching of the word whence
<hi>Paul</hi> muſt go to be inſtructed by <hi>Anani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Acts</hi> 9.
<hi>Philip</hi> is ſent to preach to the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch, Peter</hi> is ſent to
<hi>Cornelius, Acts</hi> 10. to the end, that by the <hi>fooliſhneſs of
Preaching</hi> many might be converted, 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 1.21.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>It is therefore the great duty of all men
ſeriouſly<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34827:47"/>apply themſelves to the uſe of means, that
ſo they may be converted, and turned unto God.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our ſouls are <hi>Eſſentially-active-beings,</hi> and
therefore ſhould be engag'd for God, and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and not for ſin, and
the pleaſures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are <hi>commanded</hi> to prepare our hearts in order to
our turning unto the Lord, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.3. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.6.
<hi>ch.</hi> 18.31. which Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as they <hi>expreſly</hi> ſhew it to
be our duty to be <hi>active</hi> in turning unto God, even ſo, more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
they <hi>imply,</hi> that, if <hi>we are active in our work, God will be
graciouſly pleaſed by his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> abundantly to <hi>encourage
us therein.</hi> All men, even the <hi>wicked, muſt</hi> pray, they
<hi>muſt</hi> attend on the word, and mind the Salvation of their ſouls,
which if they do, <hi>who can tell,</hi> but that the Lord may be gracious.
Thus <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer, <hi>pray</hi> God,
if <hi>perhaps</hi> he will forgive the thoughts of thy heart; For when the
wicked do <hi>pray,</hi> and <hi>hear</hi> the word, although their
<hi>prayers,</hi> &amp;c.—are an abomination unto the Lord, in that they
do not pray with that Faith and Love, &amp;c. they ought; <hi>yet,</hi> even in
that they do both <hi>pray</hi> and <hi>hear</hi> the word, they are not ſo
<hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>minable,</hi> as they would
be, ſhould they <hi>totally</hi> neglect theſe duties. For, he, who pray's
with an <hi>unſound heart,</hi> fails as to<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34827:47"/>the
<hi>manner</hi> of prayer, but he, who prays <hi>not at all,</hi> fails as to
the <hi>matter</hi> as well as <hi>manner,</hi> and conſequently is the
<hi>greater tranſgreſſor:</hi> Again, <hi>he</hi> who prays and hears the
word, is in a fairer way of receiving a bleſſing from the Lord, than
<hi>he,</hi> who will neither pray, nor hear the word. In the diſcharge of
theſe duties, we may meet with God, 'tis <hi>probable,</hi> becauſe
frequently it hath been ſo; but he who lives in the conſtant neglect of
them, is in danger of loſing his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſoul eternally. But remember,
<hi>that 'tis both duty to pray,</hi> and <hi>hear, yea, and to do ſo in
Faith with hearts ſincerely devoted unto God.</hi> We muſt engage in duty,
and yet conclude that all the good we receive is of <hi>Grace</hi> ſo
<hi>Fulgentius</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">—Cum timore &amp; tremore
tuam ſalutem opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: Nec <hi>Lectio deſit operibus bonis:</hi> Nec bona
opera deſint ſtudio lectionis—In Scripturis S. ſtudium tui cordis
impende. Et, ibi ſi fueris; qui ſis, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que debeas eſſe, cognoſce:
Ad has ſi humilis &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis acceſſeris, ibi profectò invenies
&amp; <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>evenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi>
gratiam, quâ poteſt eliſus ſurgere; &amp; <hi>comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantem,</hi>
quâ viam recti queat itineris currere; &amp; <hi>ſubſequentem,</hi>
quâ valeat ad regni caeleſtis beatitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem pervenire. <hi>Ful.</hi> de
conv. ad <hi>Theodor.</hi> Epiſt. 6. Yea the ſame <hi>Fulgentius</hi> in
the ſame Epiſtle doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us both unto our duty, and to give the
Glory of all to <hi>Free-Grace.</hi> Hujus Gratiae adjutorium, ſemper eſt
nobis a Deo poſcendum, ſed nec ipſum, quod poſcimus, noſtris viribus
aſſignemus: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que enim haberi poteſt ipſe ſaltem <hi>Orationis
affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> niſi divinitus fuerit attributus. Ut ergo deſidere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
adiutorium Gratiae, hoc ipſum quoque opus eſt Gratiae. Ipſa namque
incipit infundi; ut incipiat poſci: Ipſa quoque amplius infunditur, cum
poſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus datu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Quis
vero poteſt Gratiam poſcere niſi velit? ſed niſi in eo Deus ipſum
voluntatem ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur; velle n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tenus
poterit.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:34827:48"/>From the whole that hath been ſaid, 'tis
moſt certain, that the <hi>manifold grace of God,</hi> hath been diverſly
extended to <hi>mankind</hi> in general, and to <hi>ſome</hi> in particular.
1. To <hi>mankind in general,</hi> and that in theſe following
reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To all <hi>mankind,</hi> in that, God the <hi>Son
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed Humane Nature,</hi> in which, he ſuffered, and fulfilled all
righteouſneſs, to the end mans <hi>Salvation</hi> might become
<hi>poſſible.</hi> The Lord might have left us all in that helpleſs, and
deſperately miſerable ſtate, in which <hi>we</hi> with the fallen Angels
were once fixed: But, God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the riches of his grace towards fallen man,
even, when the leaſt favour was not ſhewn the fallen Angels.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To all <hi>mankind,</hi> in that as the <hi>Salvation</hi>
of all is become <hi>poſſible,</hi> the Lord moreover affords unto all,
ſuch a <hi>ſufficiency</hi> of <hi>help,</hi> in order to the doing what is
neceſſary unto an actual en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the glories of God as leaves
<hi>all</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:34827:48"/>ſuch as remain in ſin moſt
<hi>Inexcuſable.</hi> The <hi>worſt</hi> of men, who received leaſt,
receiving more than they improve, muſt acknowledg, that Grace was afforded
them, but they <hi>moſt wretchedly</hi> rejected it. But then</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Grace of God is infinitely exalted, in that it is
extended after an eminent manner to <hi>SOME</hi> in ſpecial; <hi>ſome</hi>
receive <hi>Faith, and all ſuch other graces,</hi> as are neceſſary to
their actual Salvation, who muſt aſcribe the <hi>glory</hi> of their
<hi>Faith, Repentance</hi> and <hi>Converſion, their ſincere
Obedience,</hi> and <hi>final perſeverance</hi> to the <hi>glory of
Free-Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I might enlarge, and ſhew how and in what reſpect the Grace
of God is exalted, in the <hi>Supporting, Refreſhing</hi> and
<hi>comforting</hi> the believer, while in this life diverſely exerciſed;
But I, deſigning to be ſhort, will inſiſt only on what may clear God
from the <hi>Reproaches</hi> are caſt on him by the <hi>wicked,</hi> who
aſſert that, according to the <hi>Opinion</hi> of many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<hi>Divines</hi> both among the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi>
it may be ſoundly argued, <hi>That God</hi> doth lay men under a <hi>Natural
neceſſity,</hi> (i.e.) [a neceſſity of the <hi>conſequent,</hi> or
rather of the <hi>Effect</hi>] of <hi>ſinning;</hi> which Notion, if
<hi>true,</hi> would ſubvert not only the greateſt part of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34827:49"/>the preceding Diſcourſe, but even the <hi>whole</hi> of
<hi>Religion.</hi> The <hi>Falſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Unſoundneſs</hi> of
which wretched reflection, as caſt on God by the
<hi>Irrationally-Atheſtical Debauchees</hi> of our times, I will attempt to
evince in the following Chapter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:34827:49"/>
            <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Grace <hi>of God</hi> further cleared. Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
owned and acknowledged by moſt. <hi>God</hi> no way <hi>the Author</hi> of
mans ſin. The <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> notion about <hi>Phyſical
Predetermination</hi> vindicated from the Abſurdities are ſaid to flow from
it. The <hi>neceſſity</hi> of our being <hi>Modeſt</hi> in enquiries of
this Nature. Several reaſons for this, drawn from the Depths of the
Myſtery, as well as from the ſhallowneſs of Humane Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, and the
General Confuſion the Jews, <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and Schoolmen</hi> run into,
when too nice in their Diſquiſitions. Some <hi>Truths</hi> of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
importance concerning the exalting Free-Grace, the reaſonableneſs of our
diſcharge of Duty notwithſtand <hi>Predetermination;</hi> and of mans
inexcuſableneſs if he neglect it. Theſe <hi>Truths</hi> known to the
<hi>Heathen;</hi> whence Grace appears in its fuller Glory. <hi>A
Recapitulation</hi> of ſome of the moſt material things inſiſted on, as
Inſtances of <hi>Free-Grace.</hi> The Concluſion with a Caution, that none
Preſume to ſin becauſe the Lord is Gracious.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THus, I have ſhewn, in many a reſpect, <hi>how</hi> the
<hi>Grace</hi> of God, is diſplayed in it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:34827:50"/>glory; It therefore, now remains only that I
evince, <hi>That this grace,</hi> is ſo <hi>infinitely extended towards all
men,</hi> that what man ſoever <hi>periſheth eternally,</hi> He doth ſo,
becauſe He will.</p>
            <p>I have already proved, that the <hi>Decree</hi> doth lay no cauſal
influence on mans will, in order to the determining it to a commiſſion of
<hi>this,</hi> or the other <hi>individuated actual ſin,</hi> in that, as
'tis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all, the <hi>Decree,</hi> being an <hi>Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,</hi>
and not <hi>Tranſient act</hi> as ſuch, <hi>nil ponit in eſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I'le now eſſay to demonſtrate, that ſuch is the
Tranſcendency of Free-grace, that, what <hi>influence</hi> ſoever proceeds
from the <hi>firſt cauſe,</hi> in an <hi>execution</hi> of the <hi>eternal
decree,</hi> it is not <hi>ſuch</hi> as doth lay a man <hi>under a Phyſical
neceſſity of Sinning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I make an entrance, on a <hi>Province,</hi> ſo
intricate, it will be neceſſary, that by way of <hi>Prologue,</hi> I
intimate what in this controverſy is <hi>plain,</hi> and what <hi>ſeems
obſcure</hi> and <hi>difficult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What is <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>undoubtedly True.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>firſt Being,</hi> yea, and
the <hi>firſt Efficient,</hi> the <hi>Holy, Juſt</hi> and <hi>Wiſe
diſpoſer</hi> of <hi>all things,</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> and
<hi>Conſerver of all Beings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. That ſuch is the <hi>purity of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
that 'tis <hi>Impoſſible God</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:34827:50"/>of Sin,</hi> and conſequently, <hi>have any cauſal
influence</hi> on the <hi>ſinfulneſs of humane actions.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>firſt</hi> Propoſition, although
denied by <hi>Epicurus,</hi> and by <hi>Ennius,</hi> [as Cicero de Divinat.
lib. 2. <hi>Ego Deûm genus eſſe ſemper dixi,</hi> &amp; <hi>dicam
coelitum:</hi> Sed <hi>eos non curare opinor,</hi> quid agat humanum genus.] by
<hi>Averrois</hi> and ſome other <hi>Peripateticks,</hi> contrary to the
ſenſe of the great <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> [as Franc. Patric. diſcuſ.
perip. tom. 4. l. 9. expreſſeth it,
<q rend="inline">'Quid ergo <hi>Averrois</hi> quid Peripatetici
caeteri aiunt, Deum in ſui con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatione, in motione primi Coeli contentum,
<hi>haec noſtratia non curare? Id praeterquam quod nefarium &amp;
ſceleſtum dogma eſt, contra prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptoris mentem ac dicta eſt.</hi>]'
&amp;c.</q>—I ſay, the <hi>Truth</hi> of this firſt propoſition,
notwithſtanding it hath been denyed by a <hi>few,</hi> is ſo plain, and
obvious, as to command the aſſent of <hi>moſt,</hi> ſo <hi>Franc.
Patric.</hi> ubi ſupra. tom. 12. l. 3. ſanè de <hi>providentia
vetuſtiſſimum eſt omnium, nedum Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entum,</hi> ſed <hi>Gentium</hi>
etiam <hi>dogma,</hi> and the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Mornay</hi> de verit. Chriſt.
Relig. c. 11. <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
ſeu <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>(i.e.) Deum,</hi> ſeu
<hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiam promiſcue vocabant, quia neutrum ſine altero concipi
poteſt.</hi> But <hi>Lactantius</hi> doth ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently evince this, lib.
2. de orig. erroris. where he ſaith
<q rend="inline">'Nam Divinâ <hi>Providentiâ</hi>
effectum eſſe mundum, ut taceam de <hi>Triſmegiſto,</hi> qui hoc
praedicat, taceam de <hi>Carminibus Sibyllarum,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:34827:51"/>quae
idem nunciant, taceam de <hi>Prophetis,</hi> qui opus mundi ac opificium Dei
uno ſpiritu ac pari voce teſtantur; etiam <hi>inter Philoſophos</hi>
penè <hi>Univerſos</hi> convenit. Idem etiam <hi>Phythagorici, Stoici,
Peripatetici,</hi> qui ſunt principes omnis Diſciplinae. Denique à
primis illis ſapientibus, à <hi>Socrate</hi> uſque ad
<hi>Platonem,</hi> pro confeſſo &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitato habitum eſt; donec unus
multis poſt ſeculis extitit <hi>delirus Epicurus.</hi>' &amp;c.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And not only the old Philoſophers, but among the <hi>Jews,</hi>
the <hi>Aſſarian</hi> ſect, as well as that of the <hi>Muatzali,</hi> and
the followers of <hi>Rambam;</hi> and of the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> not only the
<hi>Dominican</hi> and <hi>Janſeniſt,</hi> but the <hi>Moliniſt,</hi>
yea, and <hi>Durandus</hi> himſelf own a <hi>Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Second,</hi> is a Truth no leſs evident, owned even by the
<hi>worſt of Hercticks</hi> (excepting the <hi>Seleuciani,</hi> and the
followers of <hi>Florinus,</hi> who, in oppoſing the <hi>Coluthians,</hi>
fell into this contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry extream. vide Aug. de Haereſibus c. 59.65.66.) This
<hi>Mar. Scribonius in Pantal. in coſ. de pec. act. diſ.</hi> 18.
<hi>qu.</hi> 5. aſſerts,
<q rend="inline">'Nefarii quidem, ac Sceleſti fuerunt <hi>haeretici
antiqui, nullus tamen ita vecors, ut Deum totaliter Authorem peccati
fecerit.</hi> Non tamen Deum aſtruebant eſſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marium peccati authorem,
ut malum <hi>morale</hi> eſt, ſed ſolùm, quia eſt Creator
omnium, vel quia nonnulli illorum duo principia ponebant, unum boni, aliud
mali, &amp; ſic unum Deum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebant<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34827:51"/>bonum, alium malum;
<hi>nullus</hi> autem <hi>auſus eſt Deum aſſerere verè</hi> ac
<hi>propriè peccati Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi>'</q> The ſame is confeſſed by
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> de amiſs. Grat. et ſtat. pecc. l. 2. c. 1. Moreover,
the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do with the greateſt Zeal conclude, that
<hi>God</hi> is of <hi>purer eyes, than to behold iniquity.</hi> And as
<hi>Durandus,</hi> the <hi>Moliniſts,</hi> yea and the
<hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> who have eſpouſed the ſentiments of St.
<hi>Auſtine,</hi> even ſo the Dominicans, if not <hi>Peter de Aliaco</hi>
and <hi>Abailardus</hi> deny God to be the Author of ſin; for ſurely, as
the learned Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> has prov'd in his Orig. Sacr. lib. 3. c.
3. Whoever believes the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, cannot entertain the thoughts of
Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Author of ſin.
<q rend="inline">'<hi>Shall not the Judge of all the World do
right?</hi> will a <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Infinite Juſtice, Purity</hi> and
<hi>Holineſs,</hi> puniſh the <hi>ſinner</hi> for that which himſelf
was the <hi>cauſe</hi> of? Far be ſuch unworthy thoughts from our
<hi>apprehenſions</hi> of a <hi>Deity,</hi> much more of that <hi>God</hi>
whom we believe to have declared his mind ſo much to the contary, that we
cannot believe <hi>that,</hi> and the <hi>Scriptures</hi> to be <hi>true</hi>
together.'</q>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe <hi>two uncontroulable Truths</hi> there proceeds
another, with as much conviction as either of <hi>theſe,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>what man ſoever ſinneth,</hi> he doth ſo
<hi>freely,</hi> man being the <hi>ſole</hi> Author of the
<hi>ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of thoſe <hi>evil actions</hi> he committeth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:34827:52"/>This is agreeable to the ſentiments, both of
the Schoolmen, and Philoſophers, as hereafter ſhall be evinced. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. To what is <hi>Obſcure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although theſe things are ſo, there ariſe great difficulties
in all humane attempts, <hi>how</hi> to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the two latter with the
firſt propoſition; concerning which, divers men, do diverſly deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant,
every particular <hi>Sect</hi> amongſt the learned, inſiſting on
different <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> for the ſolving theſe <hi>Phaenomena;</hi>
In doing which, ſome in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a more <hi>ſecure</hi> eſtabliſhing
the <hi>two laſt</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, expreſs themſelves ſo
<hi>unwarily,</hi> as to tempt many to fear, they are not right in the
<hi>former;</hi> again, ſuch as make it their principal deſign to confirm,
and illuſtrate the <hi>firſt</hi> about <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> &amp;c.
have been cenſur'd, as if their <hi>Dogmata,</hi> had been attended with the
moſt <hi>black</hi> and <hi>diſmal conſequences;</hi> whence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
of a cordial agreement about theſe three <hi>confeſſed</hi> Truths, there
are <hi>variety</hi> of diſputes; contentions, animoſities, and quarrels
concerning the <hi>How can theſe things be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I humbly apprehend, that ſince, theſe three propoſitions
are ſo undoubtedly true, that few, or none preſume openly, or
<hi>directly</hi> to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them; tis the great <hi>intereſt,</hi> as well
as <hi>duty</hi> of <hi>all,</hi> rather to ſatisfy themſelves in the
produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing plain, cogent, Scriptural arguments for<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34827:52"/>their
confirmation, than to make a too <hi>nice</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>way</hi> and <hi>manner
how theſe things are ſo.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is it not concerning the <hi>Modes,</hi> or <hi>Media</hi>
of Divine <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>operations,</hi> that the great conteſt
is? which, as they are of what more immediately concerns the <hi>Divine
Nature,</hi> muſt be acknowledged to be <hi>infinitely</hi> above
<hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> (which are but finite) <hi>capacities.</hi> Who can by
ſearching find out God? who can know him, or his ways, unto perfection?
Methinks, the arguing of <hi>Le blank,</hi> is admirable. de concord. libert.
hum. cum decret. Div. theſ. 43.
<q rend="inline">'Itaque cum r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m tantam ſcrutanti, undique ſe tenebrae offun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant &amp;
occurrant tricae ac pedicae, ex quibus nos non ſatis extricare valemus, nihil
magis tutum &amp; ingenuum puto, quam <hi>ignorantiam noſtram hic
apertè profiteri,</hi> &amp; ſeriò illud Davidis uſurpare,
<hi>Mirabilis facta eſt ſcientia tua prae me, &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limior, quam ut
aſſequi poſſim.</hi> Ac quanquam aliorum ingenia nolim ex mea tenuitate
metiri, &amp; ſuper hac re <hi>modeſtam</hi> diſquiſitionem damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,
facile tamen adducor, ut credam myſterium hoc ad ea pertinere, de quibus
dicit Sapiens, Altiora te ne quaeſieris, &amp; fortiora te ne ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus
fueris. Nec mirum videri debet, ſi mens noſtra tam anguſtis limitibus
definita, percipere non poſſit <hi>quâ ratione</hi> intellectus
Divinus, cui planè nulli ſunt fines, ea cognoſcat, &amp; attin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34827:53"/>quae ſunt à cognitione noſtra
<hi>remotiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi>'</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Is there any thing more certain, than that, all our
diſcourſes about theſe things can be but about what is
<hi>Obſcure?</hi> But becauſe we cannot comprehend what is
<hi>Obſcure,</hi> muſt we reject what is moſt <hi>plain</hi> and
<hi>obvious? Cajetane,</hi> as I find it in <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> de grat. et
lib. arbit. l. 4. c. 14. expreſſeth himſelf as to this, moſt
excellently,
<q rend="inline">'<hi>Cajetanus</hi> in 1. part. q. 22. art. 4 docet
concordiam iſtam liberi Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrii cum Divina providentia videri
<hi>inexplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem,</hi> &amp; <hi>non intelligibilem</hi> in hac vita; Et
qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſi ita ſe res haberet, non tamen neganda eſſet, vel
<hi>Providentia Dei,</hi> vel <hi>Libertas hominum.</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enim facile
contingere, ut aliquid ab una parte <hi>manifeſtè conſtet,</hi> ab
altera ſit <hi>maximè du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium,</hi> &amp; obſcurum: &amp; tunc non
eſt negandum unum propter alterum: <hi>Nunquid</hi> (inquit S. Aug. lib. de
bono perſeverantiae, c. 14.) ideo negandum eſt quod <hi>Apertum</hi> eſt,
quia <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendi</hi> non poteſt quod <hi>occultum</hi> eſt?'</q>
But</p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis humbly apprehended, That, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is extorted, and
with the greateſt violence forced from the <hi>Dominican Hypotheſis,</hi>
when laid on the rack by the <hi>Moliniſt</hi> and ſome others; it may be
eaſily evinced, that theſe Dominicans in giving <hi>God</hi> the glory of
being the only <hi>wiſe orderer,</hi> and <hi>diſpoſer</hi> of all things
do no way caſt<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34827:53"/>him under the blaſphemous reproach, of
being the Author of the <hi>ſinfulneſs</hi> of any of our <hi>evil</hi>
actions; neither, according unto them, is <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Liberty</hi> and
<hi>Phyſical predetermination Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I begin to attempt the clearing this, I muſt crave leave,
to do my ſelf the right of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the <hi>Reader,</hi> that although I
do engage my ſelf ſo far in favour of theſe <hi>Dominicans,</hi> 'tis not
to diſcover any Zeal for that faction, who in the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> are
as <hi>bloody,</hi> as any; nor for the <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> which is as
<hi>Metaphyſically</hi> and <hi>obſcurely,</hi> as <hi>boldly</hi> worded
by ſome of them, but 'tis to ſhew, that <hi>ſuch</hi> is the
<hi>Grandure</hi> of <hi>Free-Grace,</hi> that notwithſtanding the ſeeming
ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Doctrine, none ſhall be able to ſay, that they
following the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> verily belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that they were ſo
<hi>Phyſically predetermined</hi> to the <hi>ſinfulneſs</hi> of thoſe
actions, they committed, that the <hi>true reaſon</hi> of their damnation, is
their doing what they were by an <hi>Omnipotent, Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong,</hi> and
<hi>Invincible</hi> Force violently compelled to do; for according to the
<hi>Dominican</hi> notion, what <hi>ſinner</hi> ſoever dieth in his
<hi>ſin,</hi> is a <hi>ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned</hi> ſinner; which being ſo, in
the ſenſe of theſe <hi>Stoical Schoolmen,</hi> there can be no ſcruple,
but that in the ſenſe of <hi>moſt</hi> others, ſuch as pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in
their iniquity will be found to be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>condemn'd of themſelves.</hi> For what more evident, than
that the <hi>Arminian,</hi> and the <hi>Moli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:34827:54"/>pretend to oppoſe the <hi>Dominican,</hi> principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to clear God
from the reproach of being a deſtroyer of Humane Liberty, and
conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from the being the <hi>Author of mans ſin?</hi> and 'tis as
certain, that for the ſame reaſon, <hi>Duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> rejects not only the
notion of the <hi>Dominican,</hi> but alſo <hi>that</hi> of the
<hi>Moliniſt,</hi> inſiſting only on a <hi>Remote,</hi> or <hi>mediate
concourſe</hi> of the <hi>firſt cauſe with the ſecond,</hi>
eſpouſing that old <hi>Dogma</hi> of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> and the
<hi>Pelagians,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> aſſerts de <hi>Grat. &amp; Lib.
Arb. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 4.
<q rend="inline">'Quidam enim do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerunt, poſſe homines, ut etiam
res caeteras, opera ſua efficere ſine ullo Dei auxilio, ſive ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerali
ſive ſpeciali. Ita videtur ſenſiſſe <hi>Origines</hi> in lib. 3. de
principiis, ut annotavit S. <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> lib. 3. contra <hi>Gentiles</hi>
c. 89. ita etiam ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerunt <hi>Pelagiani,</hi> teſte S.
<hi>Hieronymo</hi> in Epiſt. ad <hi>Cteſiphontem,</hi> &amp; lib. 1.
adv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Pelag. ita ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit ex
Scholaſticis Theologis <hi>Durandus</hi> in 2. Sent. diſt. 1. q. 5. &amp;
diſt. 37.1.'</q> Whence it appears, that <hi>Durandus</hi> was not the
<hi>Author</hi> of this <hi>Pelagian Hypotheſis;</hi> Mention being made of
it long before him, even by the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the Sentences,
<hi>Albertus, Henricus,</hi> and others, yea, and by S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> de
Gen. ad lit. t. 5. c. 20. as I find in <hi>Malderus</hi> in 12. Thorn. q. 79.
dub. 2.
<q rend="inline">'Meminit hujus ſententiae Magiſter, <hi>Albertus
Henricus</hi> &amp; alii, ſunt enim (inquit Aug.) qui arbitrantur
tantummodò mundum ipſum factum à Deo, caetera jam fieri ab
ipſo mundo, ſicut <pb n="95" facs="tcp:34827:54"/>ille ordinavit &amp; juſſit, Deum
autem ipſum ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil operari:'</q> Theſe things being ſo, I ſhall no
ſooner be able to evince the <hi>Phyſical Predetermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> to be one
who is ſo far from caſting man under a <hi>Phyſical neceſſity</hi> of
ſinning, as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, his <hi>deſtruction to be of himſelf,</hi> but
this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing truth will appear in its ſplendor, viz. <hi>That ſuch</hi>
is the <hi>Infiniteneſs of Free-Grace</hi> towards <hi>all,</hi> that whoever
is for ſin condemned to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal flames, is <hi>ſo</hi> moſt
<hi>Righteouſly,</hi> after the <hi>abuſe of much patience, and forbearing
Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order then, to a more clear, and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing procedure, it muſt
be obſerved,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Dominican</hi> acknowledge the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
cauſe</hi> to be in a <hi>proper</hi> ſenſe a <hi>cauſe,</hi> and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, <hi>Man</hi> the <hi>proper,</hi> though not the <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary
Efficient</hi> of his own actions: <hi>Herein</hi> do the <hi>Dominicans</hi>
differ from <hi>Peter de Aliaco</hi> and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel</hi> his follower, as
<hi>Molina</hi> himſelf aſſerts in 1 <hi>m. Thom. q.</hi> 14.
<hi>Art.</hi> 13. <hi>Diſp.</hi> 5.
<q rend="inline">'<hi>Gabriel</hi> (inquit Molina) in 4. diſt. q.
1. Art. 1. &amp; Art. 3. dub 2. &amp; 3. ſecutus <hi>Petrum</hi> de Aliaco,
in ea eſt ſententia, ut dicat <hi>Cauſas ſecundas</hi> nihil omnino
operari, ſed Deum in illis, atque ad earum praeſentiam ſe
<hi>ſolo,</hi> producere omnes ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus, unde Dub. 3. Citato, ait, Cauſas
ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das non <hi>propriè</hi> eſſe cauſas, quaſi influunt in
ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum—Cauſas vero ſecundas, dicit appellari<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34827:55"/>Cauſas ſine quibus non, quatenus conſtitutum habet Deus ad earum
praeſentiam producere effectus;'</q> which opinion of <hi>Peter de
Aliaco</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers not from that of the Sectators of <hi>Mahomet;</hi> as
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> out of Thom. in q. 3. de potentia, art. 7. doth declare.
The clearneſs then of this <hi>Truth</hi> is ſuch, that, ſhould I enter
on an enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, the many Authorities, which may be eaſily produced for
the evincing it to be the ſenſe of the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> viz. that the
ſecond <hi>cauſe</hi> is <hi>ſuo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> a <hi>proper</hi> cauſe,
and that, <hi>man,</hi> notwithſtanding that <hi>Phyſical Efficient
predetermination,</hi> that doth <hi>premove</hi> him to <hi>thoſe
actions</hi> he performs, is <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum actionum Dominus,</hi> doing what he
doth moſt <hi>Freely,</hi> time would fail me; and ſince, the great
conteſt is, rather about the <hi>Reconcilable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of theſe points,
than about the <hi>Dominicans avouching</hi> them, 'tis become
<hi>unneceſſary:</hi> I will therefore proceed to a 2d. thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Dominicans</hi> do alſo diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the <hi>materiale,</hi> &amp; <hi>formale peccati,</hi> and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, that
<hi>Phyſical predetermination</hi> hath a <hi>cauſal influence only</hi> on
the <hi>materiale,</hi> q. d. The <hi>Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale</hi> ſeu <hi>Subſtratum
peccati</hi> eſt <hi>à Deo tanquam à Cauſa prima,</hi> which
is but according to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſentiment of the <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> as
<hi>Mar. Scrib.</hi> doth particularly evince, by which they clear God from
being the Author of ſin. The <hi>Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riale,</hi> ſeu <hi>actio quatenus
actio,</hi> being <hi>quid phyſicum</hi> 
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:34827:55"/>as
<hi>ſuch,</hi> is <hi>ens reale,</hi> and conſequently, ſince
<hi>ens</hi> &amp; <hi>bonum</hi> convertuntur, 'tis ſomewhat <hi>good,</hi>
&amp; à <hi>Deo;</hi> for, <hi>omne ens eſt, aut primum, aut</hi>
à <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ortum.</hi> Thus <hi>Gabriel</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> in 2
diſt. 37. q. 1. (as <hi>Scribonius</hi> at large in Pantal. in Coſ. de pec.
actuali, diſ. 18. q. 4.)
<q rend="inline">'aſſerunt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um non eſſe cauſam malitiae
peccati, quae conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur <hi>actum</hi> poſitivum; quia quilibet
<hi>actus pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati, poteſt eſſe ſine malitia;</hi> &amp; exemplum
poteſt eſſe in <hi>odio</hi> Dei, quod, quamvis maximè omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um
videatur conjunctum cum malitia, poteſt tamen eſſe ſine
illa—&amp; ideo, licet Deus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currat in <hi>omnem actum,</hi> non tamen
concurrit in <hi>actus</hi> malitiam.'</q> Yea, <hi>Sotus</hi> li. 1. de nat.
&amp; Grat. c. 18. &amp; <hi>Canus</hi> lib. 2. de locis c. 4. &amp; in lect.
de Sacram. p. 4. &amp;c.—<q rend="inline">'dicunt, quod licet Deus concurrat ad actum peccati
ſecundum <hi>rationem,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſubſtantiam operis,</hi> non tamen
dicit cauſam peccati ſecundum <hi>formalem rationem culpae.</hi> Sunt enim,
inquiunt, Duo cauſarum genera, alterum cauſae <hi>naturalis,</hi> quales
ſunt omnes cauſae <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae,</hi> alterum cauſae <hi>moralis,</hi>
qualis eſt ille, qui <hi>monet, imperat</hi> &amp; <hi>conſulit.</hi> Cum
igitur Deus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currat cum noſtra voluntate ad <hi>actum</hi> Peccati, per
modum <hi>Cauſae naturalis,</hi> non <hi>moralis,</hi> nulla ratione poteſt
dici <hi>Cauſa Peccati,</hi> non enim <hi>monet, ſuadet, conſulit ad
peccatum,</hi> ſed ſolum ad Actum, qui, ſi <hi>naturaliter</hi>
ſumatur, <hi>vitioſus non eſt,</hi> ſed ſolum prout
<hi>moraliter,</hi> quia <hi>Culpa</hi> ſecundum rationem Culpae, non
à <hi>Cauſa naturali,</hi> ſed à <hi>morali</hi>
procedit.'</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34827:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:34827:56"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:34827:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:34827:57"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:34827:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:34827:58"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:34827:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:34827:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:34827:60"/>The like <hi>Anſelm</hi> l. de concord
praeſc. praedeſt. Grat. &amp; Lib. Arb. c. 1.
<q rend="inline">'Facit, inquit, Deus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, quae juſtâ, vel
injuſtâ voluntate fiunt, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> opera bona, &amp; mala. In
bonis enim facit quod <hi>ſunt,</hi> &amp; quod <hi>bona</hi> ſunt; in
malis facit quod <hi>ſunt,</hi> non quod <hi>mala</hi> ſunt.' So he is
quoted by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> de Grat. &amp; Lib. Arb. l. 4. c. 4.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus, they diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Materiale and the
Formale</hi> of ſin: which diſtinction once granted, and added to the
foregoing aſſertion about mans being a <hi>proper cauſe</hi> of his own
acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Dominicans will be ſufficiently defended from all the
<hi>Reproaches</hi> caſt on their Doctrine, about the making <hi>God the
Author of ſin;</hi> and real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this <hi>diſtinction</hi> (although in
other words,) is acknowledged by their <hi>adverſaries,</hi> who ſay, that
the <hi>Actus Peccati</hi> may be conſidered as in <hi>genere,</hi> in which
ſenſe 'tis <hi>quid diſtinctum</hi> à <hi>formâ
ſpecificante,</hi> of which <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Fons naturae,</hi> is the
<hi>Univerſal Cauſe,</hi> and what is this <hi>actus pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati,</hi>
condſidered in <hi>genere,</hi> but the ſame with the <hi>Materiale:</hi>
'Tis true, if we conſider the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>as a ſinful action,</hi> and in
the action include the <hi>obliquity,</hi> that action, as <hi>ſuch,</hi> is
not à <hi>Deo;</hi> yet in that action, there is the <hi>Act</hi> it
ſelf <hi>diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhable</hi> from the <hi>obliquity,</hi> which Act is
<hi>ens Phyſicum,</hi> &amp; à Deo, thus <hi>Bellarmine</hi> de
<hi>amiſſ. grat. &amp; ſtat. pecc.</hi> l. 2. c. 18.
<q rend="inline">'Actiones <hi>intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecè</hi> nullas malas
eſſe niſi ut ſint determinatae in ſpecie; nam <hi>entitas ipſa Odii
Dei, ſi per ſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideretur,<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34827:60"/>non eſt mala</hi>
ſed ſolum ut eſt talis <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titas.</hi>'</q> Yea and <hi>Durandus</hi>
himſelf adknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as much lib. 2. diſt. 37. Q. 1. which is, <hi>Utrum
actio</hi> peccati ſecundum quod <hi>actio,</hi> ſit à Deo? which he
affirms, with this reaſon,
<q rend="inline">'Quia illud quod non eſt cauſa actus, non eſt
cauſa effectus producti per actum; ſed per actionem peccati aliquid
effectus in eſſe producuntur: ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerantur enim homines ex adulteriis. Si
ergo talium actionum Deus non eſſet cauſa, per con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequens nec hominum,
qui his actionibus gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur, quod eſt inconveniens.'</q> And thence he
concludes,
<q rend="inline">'Quod Deus eſt cauſa actionis pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti
Univerſalis &amp; prima; for which reaſon he muſt diſtinguiſh
<hi>inter actionem peccati</hi> &amp; <hi>ipſum pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum,</hi> ſeu
<hi>obliquitatem (i.e.) inter materiale,</hi> &amp; <hi>formale,</hi>'</q>
unleſs the very <hi>ſin,</hi> as to its <hi>forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> or
<hi>obliquity</hi> ſit à Deo.</p>
            <p>Whence then, according unto the <hi>Dominican,</hi> the
<hi>obliquity</hi> of a ſinful action, is not from <hi>God, but</hi> from
<hi>man;</hi> who is a <hi>Proper cauſe</hi> of <hi>all his</hi> own actions;
and who is the <hi>ſole cauſe</hi> of the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquity</hi> of them, as
hath been proved.</p>
            <p>I confeſs that <hi>great attempts</hi> are made for the
<hi>reproaching</hi> this doctrine, and that the <hi>Advantages</hi> which
ſome (if not too many) <hi>Obſcure</hi> writers have given, by
inſiſting on a <hi>Phyſical-Efficient-Praemotion,</hi> as the
<hi>cauſe</hi> of the <hi>Individuated acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as evil, have been
great; but if, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34827:61"/>the unhappineſs ſuch
have been guilty of, in expreſſing themſelves <hi>ſo unwarily,</hi>
they mean no more, than what I have ſaid concerning the <hi>Materiale
peccati,</hi> &amp;c. I humbly apprehend, their ſenſe to be
<hi>defenſible;</hi> for what more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent than that their ſeveral
oppoſers (as hath been prov'd) acknowledging that God is the <hi>cauſe of
all Being,</hi> and of every <hi>Action,</hi> as ſuch, do ſeem to grant the
<hi>whole,</hi> theſe <hi>Moderate Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determinants,</hi> would be thought to
aſſert? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it muſt be acknowledged, that the ſevere and
<hi>Rigid</hi> do aſſert what is attended with <hi>Inſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
difficulties,</hi> the <hi>conſequences</hi> that are ſaid to flow from
their <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> ſeeming moſt <hi>groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abſurd.</hi> And
be it ſo, Yet</p>
            <p n="1">1. Since <hi>theſe,</hi> do deteſt the <hi>Dogma</hi> of
<hi>Hobbes,</hi> and <hi>Spinoſa,</hi> and with the greateſt indignation,
ſhew their <hi>abhorrence</hi> to all ſuch <hi>groſs,</hi> and
blaſphemous abſurdities, why may we not charitably conclude, that the
<hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,</hi> they have plung'd themſelves into, is but
<hi>equal</hi> to <hi>that</hi> of their bold <hi>adverſaries,</hi>
occaſion'd by a <hi>peremptory determining</hi> what is too ſublime and
high, yea, and what is by finite comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions really
<hi>indeterminable?</hi> Conſider what the learned Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his
<hi>Cathol. Theolog. part.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. hath moſt excellently
evinced in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That 'tis impoſſible Finite Mortals ſhould
comprehend the <hi>modes</hi> or <hi>media</hi> of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Knowledge,</hi>
or of <hi>Divine Operations;</hi> whence who-ever enters into a diſpute
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:34827:61"/>about the <hi>controverſies</hi> between the
<hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans, Jeſuites,</hi> &amp;c. cannot but run them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into
ſuch intricate, and perplexing Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as will, after the utmoſt
attempts, prove diſmally confounding; and therefore what the ſame Reverend
Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſaith in the following <hi>Sect.</hi> about
<hi>Fore-knowledge</hi> is true as to <hi>Phyſical-Predetermination,</hi>
viz.
<q rend="inline">'If any particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner therefore offer it ſelf
to your minds, as that which probably ſeemeth to be the Right, it may afford
you reaſon therefore to <hi>ſuſpect,</hi> that it is not the right:
Becauſe it is certain, that the <hi>manner</hi> is paſt our reach. And what
<hi>man</hi> can comprehend is infinitely below God.'</q>
            </p>
            <p>This being the <hi>Truth;</hi> no wonder, if the <hi>bold</hi>
entangle themſelves, and by an unwarineſs of expreſſion inſiſt on
ſuch Notions, as are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with difficulties moſt invincible; In
order to an eſcaping which, I humbly apprehend a conſulting that moſt
<hi>excellently Treatiſe</hi> of the learned and Judicious Dr. <hi>Burthogge.
viz.</hi> his <hi>Organon novum,</hi> may be of great uſe. For in that little
<hi>Tract,</hi> there are ſuch <hi>Harmonical</hi> (which are the moſt
convincing) <hi>Arguments,</hi> as cannot but oblige the <hi>Diſcreet
Reader</hi> to ſatisfy himſelf in being <hi>modeſt</hi> in his inquiries
about moſt things, eſpecially about what is ſo <hi>abſtruſe,</hi>
ſince otherwiſe looking too near things, inſtead of obtaining more
diſtinct and full conceptions, he may be abundantly confounded: There muſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:34827:62"/>be a <hi>due diſtance</hi> between the faculty, (as well
as the <hi>Organ</hi>) and its <hi>object;</hi> for by our looking too near the
Object, we run into the dark, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting</hi> one another even when
<hi>agreed;</hi> or if there be a <hi>difference,</hi> ſuch, as embrace not
the <hi>one extreme,</hi> muſt be cenſured, as <hi>Aſſerters</hi> and
<hi>Abettors</hi> of the <hi>other;</hi> yea, and in the heats of
diſputation, many fall into the <hi>Error</hi> they would oppoſe: Many
inſtances of each particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar might easily have been produc'd, but I'le only
mention ſome. As, 1. <hi>Alvarez,</hi> who repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents <hi>Calvin</hi> as
an oppoſer of the <hi>Dominican</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, even when by <hi>others</hi>
the ſame <hi>Calvin</hi> is blam'd for eſpouſing it. 2.
<hi>Victorinus</hi> by the learned (but proud) <hi>Illyricus</hi> is revil'd,
as if the <hi>denyal</hi> of that <hi>ſtrange error</hi> contended for by
<hi>Simon Muſaeus,</hi> and himſelf, had been <hi>Pelagianiſm.</hi>
Moreover, 3. In the preſent diſpute, How do the <hi>confident,</hi> on
every ſide, diſcover their <hi>weakneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> by falling into the
errors they pretend to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject? Thus the <hi>Anti-Dominicans,</hi> who
deſpiſe the <hi>Predeterminants diſtinctions,</hi> for reaſons that are
as much againſt their own, and who in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſtrange conſequences from
the <hi>Dogmata</hi> of the <hi>Dominican,</hi> do themſelves entertain
Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as liable to the ſame abſurdities. How much is ſaid againſt
all thoſe who are <hi>onely</hi> for an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate concourſe,</hi> not
by the <hi>Dominican only,</hi> but alſo by the <hi>Durandiſts,</hi> and
what is conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is this, That the Reverend Mr. <hi>B.</hi> in his
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:34827:62"/>
               <hi>Cathol. Theol.</hi> li. 1. part. 3. § 4. doth
argue moſt unanſwerably againſt them, in the follow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing words.
<q rend="inline">'It ſurpaſſeth my underſtanding to conceive,
what it is for God <hi>Phyſicè influere in actum immediate, &amp; non
in potentiam ſeu vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem agentem:</hi> Nor how he can be ſaid <hi>to move
the faculties to act,</hi> that doth <hi>cauſe</hi> the <hi>act,</hi> and not
<hi>meddle</hi> with (and therefore not <hi>move</hi>) the <hi>Faculty.</hi>
Nor know I how an <hi>Act immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately</hi> (and not the <hi>Agent</hi>) can be
the <hi>terminus</hi> of a <hi>Phyſical Motion.</hi>'</q> But ſince
<hi>Durandus</hi> is the man who ſeems to have an advantage above all others,
I will inſtance <hi>onely</hi> in him: whom <hi>Bellarmine</hi> has prov'd to
aſſert what neceſſarily infer's <hi>Deum operari omnia peccata.</hi>
For ſaith <hi>Bellarmine</hi> de <hi>Grat. &amp; Lib. Arb. l.</hi> 4.
<hi>c.</hi> 4.
<q rend="inline">'Poſt <hi>Pelagium Durandus</hi> dicit, Deum omnia
operari, quia virtutes operatrices rebus attribuit.—But if this ſhould
be ſo, ſequeretur <hi>Deum omnia pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata operari,</hi> quia dedit homini
&amp; Angelo Liberum Arbitrium, quo peccata omnia fiunt. Et apud
<hi>Durandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> id <hi>maximè</hi> locum haberet, cum ipſe contendat
in 2. ſentent. diſt. 44. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam peccati formaliter eſſe
à Deo.</hi>'</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the learned may impoſe on each others infirmities <hi>ad
infinitum,</hi> to the great diſhonour of God and of his truths. Oh! what
reaſon then have we to be <hi>cautelous</hi> in our expreſſions
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe matters! for, what we ſpeak, ſince it <hi>ſo</hi>
nearly concerns the <hi>Glory of that God,</hi> who<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34827:63"/>is
cloth'd with <hi>terrible Majeſty,</hi> and whoſe name is a <hi>Great</hi>
and a <hi>Dreadful Name,</hi> we ſhould do it with <hi>Fear</hi> and
<hi>Trembling;</hi> with an <hi>humble mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty,</hi> dreading the thoughts
of being <hi>bold</hi> in any <hi>determinations,</hi> about what is ſo
<hi>incomprehenſible</hi> in it ſelf, and ſo infinitely above the
<hi>largeſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate capacity.</hi> But what is further of weight with me is
this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That theſe very things, have been <hi>bandied</hi>
amongſt the <hi>learned</hi> of all ages, not only by the
<hi>Antichriſtian</hi> (I had almoſt ſaid the <hi>Irreligious</hi> and
<hi>Trifling</hi>) <hi>Schoolmen;</hi> but alſo by the <hi>Jewiſh
Rabbines</hi> and <hi>Heathen Philoſophers,</hi> who ſpent much time in
theſe unſearchably deep myſteries, to no accountable advantage; can we
then hope to explicate what by woful experience hath been found inexplicable
from the beginning. But,</p>
            <p n="1">1. As touching the <hi>Jews,</hi> whoever conſults <hi>Rabbi
Moſes Ben Majemon</hi> in his <hi>more Nevoch.</hi> part. 3. c. 17. as
tranſlated by <hi>Buxtorf. Fil.</hi> may ſee, that as there are the
<hi>Dominicans, Moliniſts,</hi> and others amongſt the <hi>Schoolmen;</hi>
even ſo, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>them,</hi> there were, not only <hi>ſome</hi> who
followed <hi>Epicurus,</hi> but alſo <hi>ſome</hi> of the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of
<hi>Ariſtotle, qui credunt, quarundam rerum eſſe providentiam,</hi> ita
ut ab <hi>aliquo regantur</hi> &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigantur; quaedam verò
derelicta, &amp; <hi>fortunae<pb n="105" facs="tcp:34827:63"/>eſſe expoſita.</hi> But
<hi>others</hi> contrary unto theſe, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert,
<q rend="inline">'omnia eſſe ex <hi>certa voluntate,
intentione,</hi> &amp; <hi>gubernatione.</hi> Haec ſententia eſt <hi>Sectae
Aſſariae</hi> inter <hi>Iſmaelitas,</hi> &amp; ſequuntur eam
<hi>inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> &amp; <hi>abſurda multa:</hi> Tollitur ſecundum
eam <hi>natura poſſibilium,</hi> quod omnia ſunt vel
<hi>neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> vel <hi>impoſſibilia.</hi> Inſuper ſequitur,
<hi>nihil quicquam prodeſſe leges.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Quarta ſententia</hi>
eſt eorum qui ſtatuunt, Hominem poteſtatem vel facultatem aliquam habere,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> Et in hac ſententia eſt Secta <hi>Muatzali,</hi> licet
poteſtatem homini abſolutam non tribuant. Ex hac quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſententia,
<hi>abſurda</hi> &amp; <hi>contradictoria multa ſequuntur.</hi>'</q> And
then he comes unto the <hi>laſt,</hi> which, he ſaith, is according to
their <hi>Law,</hi> which is, Quod <hi>homo per naturam, Arbitrium,</hi> &amp;
<hi>voluntatem ſuam faciat, quicquid homo facere poteſt.</hi> Thus they
preſuming too much on ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred myſteries, as <hi>ſome,</hi> came near
unto the <hi>Truth, others,</hi> as far from it, but <hi>all</hi> in an heat,
inſiſting on the abſurdities of each others opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>heathen Philoſophers,</hi> were entangled with
the ſame perplexities, contradicting each other. So <hi>Cicero</hi> de Fato,
who ſaith that ſome of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he
<hi>Old Philoſophers.</hi>
               <q rend="inline">'cenſerent <hi>omnia ita fato fieri,</hi> ut id
fatum vim neceſſitatis afferret. In qua ſententia <hi>Democritus,
Heraclitus, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docles, Ariſtoteles</hi> fuit: altera ſententia eorum,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:34827:64"/> quibus viderentur ſine <hi>ullo fato</hi> eſſe
animorum motus voluntarii;'</q> but <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> the chief of the
<hi>Stoicks,</hi> would walk in <hi>medio,</hi>
               <q rend="inline">'tanquam ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter honorarius, medium ſe ferre
voluiſſe: Sed applicat ſe ad eos potius, qui neceſſitate motus animos
liberatos volunt. Dum autem verbis utitur ſuis, delabitur in eas
difficultates, ut <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitatem</hi> Fati confirmet invitus.'</q> But I
hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conceive that this <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> and all the <hi>Stoicks</hi>
his ſectators, had a glimpſe of this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine about <hi>Phyſical
Predetermination,</hi> which, they concluded to be neceſſarily inferred,
from that other about <hi>Preſcience,</hi> as may be eaſily evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of
<hi>Cicero</hi> de divinatione, where their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion de Fato is explained thus,
<q rend="inline">'<hi>Fatum</hi> autem id appello, quod Graeci
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(i.e.)</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem,
ſeriemque cauſarum, cum cauſa cauſae nexa rem ex ſe gignat, Ea eſt
ex omni aeterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate fluens veritas ſempiterna. Quod cum ita ſit, nihil
eſt factum, quod non <hi>futurum</hi> fuerit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> codemque modo nihil eſt <hi>futurum</hi> cujus no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>cauſas</hi> id ipſum
<hi>efficientes,</hi> natura contineat. Ex quo intelligitur, ut <hi>fatum</hi>
ſit non id quod <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitioſe,</hi> ſed id quod
<hi>Phyſicè</hi> dicitur, <hi>Cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> aeterna rerum, Cur &amp; ea, quae praeterierunt, fact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> ſint,</hi> &amp; <hi>quae inſtant,
fiant,</hi> &amp; <hi>quae ſequuntur, fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tura ſint.</hi>'
&amp;c.—</q>Whence they conſider th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Doctrine de <hi>Divinatione,</hi> &amp; de <hi>Fato,</hi> to be
a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 'twere <hi>inſeparable,</hi>
the former neceſſarily i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferring the latter; for in their judgment, nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:34827:64"/>can be
<hi>Foreknown,</hi> but what hath a <hi>Natural An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teceding cauſe.</hi> This
concluded by the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> they are plunged into as many an intricate
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, as are our <hi>Phyſical Predeterminants;</hi> ſome
aſſerting this to be <hi>a dogma</hi> attended with the ſame abſurd
conſequences, that of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus,</hi> &amp;c. is <hi>viz.</hi> that it
introduceth a <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> on humane actions;
<q rend="inline">'At qui introducunt cauſarum ſeriem
ſempiternam, ij mentem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis voluntate libera ſpoliatam neceſſitate
fati devinciunt.'</q> But <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> hath his diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to
clear himſelf from ſuch ſmart cenſures, as is to be ſeen in
<hi>Cicero</hi> de <hi>Fato,</hi> Where you will find him to conclude thus:
<q rend="inline">'Non enim ſi alii ad alia ſint propenſiores
propter <hi>cauſas naturales,</hi> &amp; <hi>antecedentes,</hi> idcirco etiam
<hi>noſtrarum volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> atque appetitionum, ſunt <hi>cauſae
naturales &amp; antecedentes,</hi> nam nihil eſſet in noſtra
pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi res ita ſe
haberet,'</q> q. d. Phyſical prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination doth not infer a Phyſical
neceſſity on humane actions, whence <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> cum &amp;
<hi>neceſſitatem</hi> improbaret, &amp; nihil vellet ſine prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitis
cauſis evenire, cauſarum genera diſtinguit, ut &amp; <hi>neceſſitatem
effugiat,</hi> &amp; retineat <hi>fatum.</hi> His diſtinction is this.
Cauſarum aliae ſumt <hi>perfectae</hi> &amp; <hi>principales,</hi> aliae
<hi>adjuvantes,</hi> &amp; <hi>proximae:</hi> And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes, that if the
<hi>cauſae antecedentes</hi> had been <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectae</hi> &amp;
<hi>principales,</hi> Humane Liberty had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, but ſince they
are but <hi>adjuvantes</hi> &amp; <hi>proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae,</hi> 'tis not ſo: But they
are mightily confounded.<pb n="108" facs="tcp:34827:65"/>
               <hi>Diodorus</hi> contradicting
<hi>Chryſippus,</hi> aſſerting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be poſſible, but what is
<hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>future: Carneades</hi> inſiſting on a
diſtinction inter cauſas <hi>fortuitò</hi> antegreſſas, &amp;
inter <hi>cauſas cohiben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> in ſe <hi>efficientiam naturalem,</hi>
and others argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt both <hi>preſcience</hi> and
<hi>predetermination,</hi> as what is <hi>impoſſible.</hi> In the
apprehenſion of ſome the <hi>one</hi> introduceth the <hi>other;</hi> and
again, 'tis urged, as if <hi>one</hi> deſtroyed the <hi>other.</hi> In
<hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero de divin.</hi> l. 2. 'tis thus diſputed;</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Praeſenſio</hi> ſeu <hi>praedictio</hi> [or if
you will <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia</hi>] non <hi>eſt earum rerum quae ſunt
fortuitae:</hi> For,
<q rend="inline">'Nihil eſt tam contrarium rationi, &amp;
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiae, quam <hi>fortuna;</hi> ut mihi nè in Deum quidem cadere
videatur,'</q> ut ſciat quid <hi>caſu,</hi> &amp; <hi>fortuitò</hi>
futurum ſit; ſi enim ſcit, certò illud eveniet; ſin certè
eveniet—rerum igitur <hi>fortuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> nulla eſt praeſenſio,
[q.d.nulla <hi>praeſcientia.</hi>]
<q rend="inline">'Aut ſi negas eſſe fortunam &amp; omnia quae
fiunt,'</q> quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que futura ſint, ex omni aeternitate definita dicis eſſe
<hi>fataliter;</hi> muta definitionem Divinationis, quam dicebas eſſe
<hi>praeſenſionem rerum fortuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> to which I may agreeably enough
add <hi>[rerum contingentium.]</hi> But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary;</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Praeſenſio</hi> [ſeu <hi>praeſcientia</hi>]
<hi>non eſt rerum futurarum:</hi>
               <q rend="inline">'Nam ſi fato omnia fiant, nihil nos d monere
poteſt, ut cautiores ſimus; quoquo<pb n="109" facs="tcp:34827:65"/>enim modo nos
geſſerimus, fiet tamen illud quod futurum eſt; ſin autem id poteſt
flecti, nullum eſt fatum, ita nec Divinatio [ſeu Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia] quidem,
quoniam ea rerum futura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt. Nihil autem eſt pro certo futurum, quod
poteſt aliqua procuratione accidere ne fiat. Si enim nihil ſit extra Fatum,
nihil levari re Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina poteſt.'</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus many an hundred years have been ſpent in theſe inquiries,
by ſuch as have been both too <hi>curious</hi> and <hi>confident;</hi> and
what was the <hi>fruit</hi> of all their labours, but in <hi>ſome,
confuſion</hi> and much <hi>torment;</hi> in <hi>others,</hi> viz. the more
<hi>judicious</hi> and <hi>ſober,</hi> juſt light enough to ſee their
<hi>Ignorance,</hi> and the <hi>truth</hi> of this, viz. that there was a
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi> a <hi>Fate;</hi> which in <hi>Laertius</hi> his Zeno is
<hi>Ratio per quam mundus adminiſtratur;</hi> and that notwithſtanding this
Fate or Providence, <hi>man</hi> was not ſo diveſted of his rational
<hi>liberty,</hi> as to be by force compel'd to a violation of the Laws. From
all which, I thus argue. That either <hi>we muſt be modeſt in our inquiry
after theſe things;</hi> or give <hi>our weak underſtandings the liberty of
rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the whole of this</hi> Labyrinth; If the <hi>Second,</hi> then
there remaineth nothing but <hi>obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, confuſion</hi> and torment, if
not, through raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, much <hi>error,</hi> and our time ſpent in
contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting, reviling, and ſeverely cenſuring each other ad
<hi>infinitum:</hi> But if the <hi>Firſt,</hi> if we muſt
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:34827:66"/>be <hi>modeſt,</hi> then ſurely, enough may be ſaid
even in <hi>favour</hi> of the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> to ſhew, <hi>that
Phyſical Predetermination,</hi> as <hi>Preſcience,</hi> doth but infer, a
<hi>Logical neceſſity,</hi> which neceſſity is conſiſtent enough,
in the judgment of all, with Humane <hi>Liberty.</hi> The product of all which
will be this, viz. That ſuch are the <hi>tranſactions</hi> of God with
<hi>men,</hi> ſo <hi>infinitely wiſe,</hi> ſo <hi>Juſt,</hi> ſo
<hi>Equal,</hi> ſo <hi>Holy,</hi> and yet ſo <hi>merciful</hi> and
<hi>Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> that none, no not thoſe who are to be condemned unto
Eternal Miſery, will have one word to offer againſt God.</p>
            <p>Oh! How Infinite is the Freeneſs of his Grace!</p>
            <p>Thus, I have further ſhewn, the <hi>Grace</hi> of God to be ſo
infinitely glorious, that there is nothing in thoſe profound points about
<hi>Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination,</hi> &amp;c.—when <hi>modeſtly</hi>
aſſerted, that can in the leaſt <hi>blemiſh it;</hi> I ſay, when
<hi>modeſtly</hi> aſſerted, becauſe ſuch as are too confident, and
<hi>peremptory</hi> in their <hi>determinations</hi> about this point, which is
as dark and as myſterious as any in the <hi>whole body</hi> of
<hi>Divinity,</hi> may ſuddenly break the <hi>bounds,</hi> and come too near
the <hi>Mount</hi> to their own hurt.</p>
            <p>For although a <hi>Predetermination</hi> is moſt clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Revealed
in Scripture, yet whether by a <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical efficient-praemotion</hi> to
<hi>this</hi> ſinful action, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to <hi>that,</hi> is not ſo
obvious. A <hi>praedetermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> there is; but whether St. <hi>Auſtin,
Proſper</hi> and <hi>Fulgentius</hi> had not righter apprehenſions of it,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34827:66"/>than the <hi>Dominicans,</hi> who differ from St.
<hi>Auſtin</hi> in ſeveral reſpects as <hi>Janſenius</hi> in his
Auguſtinus de Grat. Chriſt. Salvat. lib. 8. c. 1. &amp;c.—hath
unanſwerably proved, is no <hi>impertinent Quaery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But without any further determination of theſe incomprehenſible
difficulties, as I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, ſo I'le end both this Chapter and Treatiſe
with <hi>moſt neceſſary</hi> and <hi>concerning truths,</hi> which as
they are ſo <hi>ſelf-evident</hi> as to be known to the <hi>Heathen,</hi>
in like manner they are <hi>ſuch</hi> as add to the <hi>illuſtrating
Free-Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That, Although <hi>God</hi> is the great <hi>Orderer</hi>
and <hi>Diſpoſer of all things,</hi> the <hi>Author,</hi> and
<hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver of all beings,</hi> and hath eternally predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and
fore-ordained all things that come to paſs in time; yet <hi>man</hi> is not
hereby <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally neceſſitated</hi> to any <hi>ſin,</hi> but doth
what he doth <hi>moſt freely,</hi> and therefore, muſt not
<hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain</hi> on God, nor <hi>neglect</hi> the performance of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
duties</hi> unto him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Mans <hi>Liberty</hi> is not deſtroyed by
<hi>Predeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination;</hi> ſo <hi>Seneca Natur. Quaeſt. l.</hi> 2.
<hi>c.</hi> 38.
<q rend="inline">'<hi>Iſta nobis opponi ſolent,</hi> ut probetur
<hi>nihil volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati noſtrae relictum,</hi> &amp; omne jus <hi>fato</hi>
traditum. Cum de iſta re agitur, dicam, quemadmodum, <hi>manente fato,
aliquid ſit in hominis arbitrio</hi>' &amp;c.—</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:34827:67"/>2. Men muſt not <hi>complain</hi> on
<hi>God,</hi> as if they had <hi>been compel'd</hi> to ſin: So
<hi>Chryſippus</hi> in A. Gell. noct. Attic. lib. 6. c. 2.
<q rend="inline">'Propterea <hi>Negat opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere ferri, audirique
homines</hi> aut nequam aut ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navos &amp; nocentes &amp; audaces; qui cum in
culpa, &amp; in maleficio revicti ſunt, perfugiunt ad Fati neceſſitatem,
tanquam in aliquod Fati aſylum; &amp; quae peſſimè fecerunt, ea
non ſuae temeritati, ſed fato eſſe attribuenda dicunt.'</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. We ought not to neglect duty, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this
<hi>Predetermination,</hi> but muſt <hi>Pray,</hi> and uſe ſuch means, as
are ſuited to the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the deſired end. So <hi>Seneca</hi> ubi
ſupra c. 37.
<q rend="inline">'nos quoque exiſtimamus vota proficere,
ſalvâ vi ac poteſtate fatorum; quaedam enim à Diis
immortalibus ita ſuſpenſa relicta ſunt ut in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num vertant, ſi
<hi>admotae Diis preces fuerint;</hi> ſi vota ſuſcepta. Ita non eſt hoc
contra <hi>fatum,</hi> ſed <hi>ipſum quoque in Fato eſt.</hi>'</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">'Aut futurum, inquit, eſt, aut non. Si futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
eſt, etiam ſi non ſuſceperis vota, fiet: Si non eſt futurum, etiam
ſi ſuſceperis vota, non fiet: <hi>Falſa eſt illa interrogatio;</hi>
quia <hi>mediam illam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter iſta exceptionem praeteris.</hi> Futurum,
inquam, hoc eſt, ſed ſi <hi>vota ſuſcepta fuerint.</hi>'</q> So
<hi>Cicero,</hi> de fato.
<q rend="inline">'Sic enim interrogant: Si fatum tibi eſt ex hoc
morbo convaleſcere; ſive medicum adhibu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eris, ſive non, convaleſces.
Item ſi fatum tibi <pb n="113" facs="tcp:34827:67"/>eſt, ex hoc morbo non
convaleſcere: ſive tu medicum adhibueris, ſive non, non convaleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:
&amp; Alterutrum fatum eſt; medicum ergo adhibere nihil attinet. Rect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>genus</hi> hoc inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogationis
<hi>ignavum</hi> atque <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> nominatum eſt, quod eadem ratione, <hi>omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> è vita tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur actio.</hi>
But to the Second ſelf-evident propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition."</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That although we cannot fully compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend HOW theſe
things are <hi>reconcilable;</hi> yet we have the greateſt reaſon
imaginable, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>that</hi> they are moſt <hi>true;</hi> yea, and
<hi>capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of a Reconciliation:</hi> What is not poſſible with men, is
poſſible with God; Gods works do bear the characters of Divinity on them,
and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently 'tis become <hi>impoſſible,</hi> that any <hi>Finite
wight,</hi> ſhould have any <hi>adaequate conceptions</hi> of them; We muſt
be ſatisfied, that we know, <hi>what is,</hi> though we cannot comprehend
<hi>How</hi> it is.</p>
            <p>For the confirming this, conſider what is ſaid by
<hi>Lactantius</hi> de Orig. er. l. 2. c. 9.
<q rend="inline">"Adeo nefas exiſtimandum eſt, ea ſcrutari quae
Deus voluit eſſe celata.—Quaſi verò ex hoc putan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſit,
non eſſe haec divinitus facta, quia <hi>quo modo</hi> facta ſunt, non
poteſt pervideri—Opera ipſius videntur oculis: <hi>Quomodo</hi> autem
illa <pb n="114" facs="tcp:34827:68"/>fecerit, ne mente quidem videtur: quia (ut
<hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> ait) mortale immortali, temporale perpetuo, &amp; corruptibile
incorrupto propinquare non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, id eſt propius accedere, &amp;
intelligentia ſubſequi.—Denique, cum aperiret homini veritatem Deus,
ca ſola <hi>ſcire</hi> nos voluit, quae interfuit hominem ſcire ad vitam
conſequendam; quae verò ad <hi>curioſam &amp; profanam
cupiditatem</hi> pertinebant, reticuit, ut arcana eſſent. Quid ergo
quaeris, quae nec potes ſcire, nec ſi ſcias, beatior fias? perfecta eſt
in homine ſapientia, ſi &amp; Deum eſſe unum, &amp; ab ipſo eſſe
facta univerſa cognoſcat. So <hi>Cicero</hi> de divinat. l. 1. Hoc ſum
contentus, quòd etiamſi <hi>Quomodo</hi> quidque fiat ignorem,
<hi>Quid</hi> fiat, intelligo—ſic ventorum &amp; Imbrium ſigna, quae
dixi, rationem quam habeant, <hi>non ſatis perſpicio: vim</hi> &amp;
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum <hi>agnoſco, ſcio, approbo.</hi> Again, Quid quaeris,
<hi>Carneades,</hi> cur haec ita fiant, aut <hi>qua arte perſpici
poſſent?</hi> neſcire me fateor: evenire autem, teipſum dico
videre.—Quae eſt igitur iſta <hi>calliditas,</hi> res vetuſtate
robuſtas calumniando velle pervertere? Non <hi>reperio cauſam,</hi> Latet
fortaſſe obſcuritate involuta naturae. <hi>Non enim me Deus iſta
ſcire, ſed his tantummodo uti voluit.</hi> Utar igitur,"
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe two acknowledged Truths there
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth naturally flow this
<hi>other.</hi> viz.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:34827:68"/>3. That <hi>none more Judicious</hi> and
<hi>wiſe,</hi> none <hi>more ſober</hi> and <hi>modeſt,</hi> none
<hi>more regardful</hi> of <hi>the Dread Majeſty of God,</hi> than thoſe
who, on the ſtrict eſt inquiry after theſe things, profeſs, that what
concerns <hi>God, ſo immediately,</hi> as theſe profound Doctrines about
the <hi>modes,</hi> and <hi>media</hi> of Divine operations, being infinitely
beyond us, are more meet for our <hi>humble admiration,</hi> than <hi>proud
deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. Placeus</hi> is to be applauded, who ſaith tract. de lib.
arb. (as I find in Le blank de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Arb. Hum. cum div. concurſ. ad
Theſ. 52.) Nos quidem <hi>Qua Reverentia erga Infinitam Dei Majeſtatem</hi>
ducimur, non <hi>Audemus</hi> definire quanta ſit dependentia cauſae
ſecundae à prima. <hi>Nobis ſufficit,</hi> modo ne Deo ullam
peccatorum noſtrorum, vel minimam labem aſpergat, non poſſe Nimiam
ſtatui. So <hi>Le Blank</hi> himſelf, ubi ſupra. theſ. 55,58,59.
<q rend="inline">"Quantum ad me attinet, horumce Doctiſſimorum
virorum <hi>modeſtiam</hi> maximè laudandam cenſeo: &amp;
<hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> Divini concurſus, quo cum cauſis ſecundis prima
cooperatur, pro certo definire <hi>temerarium</hi> mihi &amp; <hi>nimium
audax</hi> videtur, quum ingenii noſtri tenuitas divinae potentiae &amp;
ſapientiae abyſſum penetrare &amp; ſcrutari non valeat, nec ea res
ſit ſatis ratione percepta, aut ſat diſtincte in ſacra Scriptura
Revelata," <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—</q>Yea, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them the ſame was the
ſenſe of the <hi>Judicious,</hi>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:34827:69"/>as I find in <hi>Pet.
Tartaret. Reportata,</hi> in ſenten. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <q rend="inline">"Tota materia praedeſtinationis tangit
<hi>myſterium imperſcrutabile</hi> intellectui humano. Nam ad Roman. 11.
Exclamat Paulus, O altitudo <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Ne igitur ſcrutando, de profundo
in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundum eatur, ut dicit Magiſter," <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I have gone thorough the <hi>Province,</hi> I engaged in, and
have in ſome meaſure, made a <hi>Diſplay</hi> of this <hi>Glorious
Grace.</hi> I have ſhewn, That the <hi>Election</hi> of <hi>ſome</hi> unto
<hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> even when <hi>others</hi> are paſſed
by, but left as <hi>ſelf condemned wretches,</hi> is of <hi>Grace.</hi> That
the <hi>Covenant tranſaction,</hi> between the <hi>Father</hi> and the
<hi>Son</hi> from all Eternity, conſidered in its particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, adds light
unto this <hi>profound myſtery:</hi> That God the <hi>Son</hi> ſhould
aſſume humane nature, and in that nature, lie under both the <hi>Guilt</hi>
and <hi>puniſhment</hi> of ſin is admirable; and that the
<hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of Chriſt ſhould be given the <hi>elect
believer</hi> in order to his actual entrance into to Glories of God is no
leſs ſurpriſing. That <hi>Grace</hi> is offered <hi>all,</hi> and
although rejected by <hi>all,</hi> yet <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually</hi> given
<hi>ſome,</hi> in ſuch circumſtances that the honour of all Gods other
attributes is ſet forth with the greater Luſtre, is alſo of Grace. In the
doing all which, to the end, I might, according to the Goſpel of our Lord
Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Vindicate</hi> God, from thoſe blaſphemous, and
unworthy<pb n="117" facs="tcp:34827:69"/>abuſes are caſt on his <hi>pure Majeſty</hi>
by the <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian;</hi> I have proved, that <hi>no ſpot</hi> of
<hi>ſin</hi> was ever on the Lord Chriſt, <hi>He</hi> never was ſtained
with the filth of any evil, neither are the <hi>Elect ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied</hi> by an
<hi>imparting</hi> or an <hi>imputing</hi> the <hi>ſubjective Intrinſecal
Holineſs</hi> of Chriſt unto them; nor, are they <hi>actually
juſtified</hi> in <hi>God's ſight,</hi> while under the <hi>pravalcncy</hi>
of <hi>unbelief:</hi> Moreover, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the <hi>Arminian,</hi> I
have evinced, That God, in giving Grace unto the <hi>Elect,</hi> converts them
by the <hi>Irreſiſtible</hi> power of his Holy Spirit, which, although ſo
neceſſary to our converſion, that none are ſavingly engaged to believe
in Chriſt without it, yet doth it not lay <hi>man</hi> under any
<hi>unnatural violence,</hi> but <hi>ſweetly</hi> draws him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our
bleſſed Jeſus. Whence it follows that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though mans
<hi>deſtruction</hi> is of <hi>himſelf,</hi> his <hi>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> and
Salvation is <hi>wholly</hi> of <hi>Free-grace.</hi> And in fine, that no
<hi>Debauchee</hi> or <hi>Atheiſt</hi> may have the leaſt pretence for the
abuſes he may caſt on God, as if there had been any want of <hi>Grace</hi>
in him, I have prov'd that the <hi>Dominican Hypotheſis,</hi> which ſeems
moſt liable to exception, if <hi>modeſtly</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi>
Judiciouſly) look't into, will appear to be <hi>Defenſible</hi> againſt
thoſe reproaches are caſt on it: It being moſt evident, that although God
is both our <hi>Creator,</hi> and <hi>Preſerver,</hi> He, in whom we live,
move, and have our being, yet doth he not lay man under a <hi>Phyſical
neceſſity</hi> of ſinning, for mans<pb n="118" facs="tcp:34827:70"/>ſin is from
himſelf; as is aſſerted by the <hi>Stoicks</hi> themſelves; which being
ſo, I will only add this <hi>Caution,</hi> viz. That, although, the
<hi>Grace</hi> of God is <hi>ſo</hi> infinitely extended, (as hath been fully
proved) yet 'tis a ſin to expect the being made a partaker of the
<hi>ſpecial inſtances</hi> thereof, unleſs we ſincerely repent; 'Tis
the <hi>Believing, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Humbled</hi> ſinner, that is the <hi>proper
object</hi> of this <hi>Glorious Grace. Deſpiſe</hi> not then <hi>this</hi>
Grace, by continuing in thy ſin; for, as there are <hi>mercies</hi> with the
Lord, 'tis, that he ſhould be <hi>feared: Deſpiſeſt thou the Riches of
his Goodneſs and Forbearance, and Long-ſuffering, not knowing that the
Goodneſs of God leadeth</hi> to Repentance? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member then that if
<hi>Free-Grace</hi> leadeth thee not to <hi>Repentance,</hi> thou doſt but
treaſure up unto thy ſelf <hi>wrath</hi> againſt the day of wrath, and
Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Righteous judgment of God.</p>
            <p>Think on theſe things ſeriouſly, and by an <hi>Holy,
Humble</hi> life give God the Glory of all this <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:34827:70"/>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:34827:71"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:34827:71"/>
            <head>THE APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>SInce the preceding Diſcourſe hath been finiſhed, I have had
the advantages of <hi>ſuch Remarks</hi> on ſome Particulars therein
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, as do call for a fuller Explanation of my thoughts concerning them;
for which Reaſon, I muſt preſume on the <hi>Candor</hi> of the
<hi>Reader,</hi> in adding this following <hi>Appendix.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">§ 1. I have inſiſted much on the diſtinction
there is between the <hi>Sin</hi> itſelf, and the <hi>Guilt</hi> of the
<hi>Fault,</hi> which ſome think to be but <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>ſame
thing;</hi> for <hi>Reatus,</hi> being <hi>à Re,</hi> it doth intimate,
that the being <hi>guilty of Sin,</hi> imports no more than that he is a
<hi>Real Sinner,</hi> (i.e.) hath <hi>really ſinned,</hi> or broken the Law;
whereas I humbly conceive, it doth moreover import a <hi>liableneſs to
Puniſhment for Sin:</hi> But that I may be the more full in the diſcovering
my thoughts, it will be proper to conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> of the word <hi>Guilt,</hi> which in Latine is
<hi>Reatus,</hi> a word not very ancient; for,<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:34827:72"/>ſay the
<hi>Learned,</hi>
               <q rend="inline">"Dictio <hi>Reatus</hi> Ciceroni &amp; aliis
antiquis inuſitata, primùm à M. <hi>Meſſala</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficta,
ut <hi>Fabius</hi> autor eſt lib. 8."</q> So <hi>Schard.</hi> But how
<hi>novel</hi> ſoever this word is, yet, among the <hi>Romans</hi> it
ſignified the <hi>quality,</hi> and ſtate of the <hi>Accuſed;</hi> which
was repreſented to be ſad and diſimal, by the <hi>poor, filthy, ſqualid
garments</hi> the accuſed did wear, yea, and by <hi>Hair</hi> and
<hi>Beards</hi> undreſſed,
<q rend="inline">"<hi>Reatus,</hi> ſtatus, &amp; conditio Reorum,
(h.e.) ut <hi>Budaeus</hi> ait, Habitus demiſſus, pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſus,
<hi>ſqualidus,</hi> &amp; miſericordiae aucupator,"</q> whence
<hi>Martial.</hi> lib. 2. Epigram.
<q>
                  <l>Si det iniqua tibi triſtem fortuna <hi>reatum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Squalidus</hi> haerebo <hi>pallidiorque Reo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
The like may be concluded from what is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by <hi>Plinie, lib.</hi> 7.
<hi>ad Suram.</hi> And alſo by <hi>Aul. Gell. noct. Attic. lib.</hi> 3.
<hi>c.</hi> 4.] All which was done, thereby to engage the Judges to a more
compaſſionate procedure, they being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently conſidered as
<hi>Guilty,</hi> as ſoon as <hi>Accuſed,</hi> and conſequently, before it
appear'd, that the <hi>Fault,</hi> of which they were Accuſed, was
<hi>Really</hi> committed by them, whence although <hi>Reus ſit à
Re,</hi> it is not as if the perſon had been denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Guilty</hi>
meerly becauſe he had <hi>really</hi> done the <hi>Fact;</hi> but he is
ſaid to <hi>Reus à Re, quae ab eo petitur,</hi> whence the guilty
perſon is <hi>one, qui defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, &amp; propulſat actionem,</hi> vel
<hi>accuſationem;</hi> yea,<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:34827:72"/>and conſequently he may be
guilty, although he did never <hi>really</hi> commit the Fault; for to be
<hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed</hi> is to be guilty. For this conſult Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> of
<hi>Juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, to be <hi>guilty,</hi> according to the <hi>Ancients,</hi>
is taken yet more <hi>largely,</hi> as appears out of <hi>Cicero</hi> de
<hi>Orator.</hi> lib. 2. who was well acquainted with the word <hi>Reus,</hi>
although not ſo with <hi>Reatus;</hi> and who ſaith,
<q rend="inline">"<hi>Reos</hi> autem appello, non eos modò
qui arguuntur, ſed omnes quorum de re diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptatur: ſic enim
<hi>olim</hi> loquebantur:"</q> And agreeably hereunto <hi>Aelius Gallus</hi>
lib. de ſignif. verb. ad jus pertinentium, <hi>Reum definit, qui cum altero
litem conteſtatam</hi> habet, ſive <hi>is agat,</hi> ſive <hi>cum eo
agatur,</hi> ſo <hi>Schard.</hi> Whence although it be ſometimes uſed for
the <hi>Crime</hi> itſelf, and again for the <hi>puniſhment</hi> inflicted
for ſuch a Crime, yet, 'tis certainly ſomewhat <hi>diſtinct,</hi> both
from the <hi>Crime,</hi> and the <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> yea, <hi>ſo</hi>
diſtinct from the <hi>Crime,</hi> that, as one, who never committed a Crime,
may in the ſenſe of the Ancients be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; even ſo, 'twas a wonder to
ſome, that any ſhould conclude the Crime and the Guilt to be the ſame;
for <hi>Speigelius,</hi> yea, <hi>Schardius</hi> and <hi>Kakl.</hi> on the word
<hi>Reatus</hi> do agree in this, take the words of the laſt, Quapropter
omnino fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntur ſcriptores poſt <hi>Accurſium</hi> exiſtimantes,
Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris conſultos <hi>Reatus</hi> verbum pro <hi>Crimine</hi> uſurpari,
eorumque ſententia refutatur per l. 3. §. quod patet F. de mun. &amp;
honor. Non enim <hi>Crimen</hi> ſed <pb n="iv" facs="tcp:34827:73"/>habitum illud
pannoſum, ſtatumque demiſſum ſignificat. l. fin. F. ad leg. &amp;c.
Moreover,</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we conſider the uſe of the word, <hi>as it doth
preſuppoſe</hi> a <hi>crime,</hi> for which reaſon, to ſay ſuch an
one is <hi>guilty,</hi> is as if it had been ſaid, he hath done the
<hi>Fact;</hi> yet <hi>guilt,</hi> as <hi>ſuch,</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
diſtinct from the Crime, whence although the learned in the exerciſe of
their freedom, may uſe the word <hi>Reatus diverſly,</hi> yet 'tis
abſolutely neceſſary, that we conſider the word <hi>Guilt,</hi> as
expreſſive of ſomewhat diſtinct from the <hi>Fault</hi> itſelf, or
that ſome other word that is as meet, or more ſo, be inſiſted on for
ſuch an End: For what more evident, than that <hi>as</hi> the doing this or
the other thing contrary to the <hi>preceptive</hi> part of the Law is
<hi>ſin,</hi> even ſo, from <hi>this ſin,</hi> as it regards the
<hi>retributive</hi> part of the ſame Law, there reſults a
<hi>liableneſs</hi> to puniſhment, an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxiouſneſs thereunto, which
liableneſs being but the reſult of the ſin, is not the ſin itſelf,
'tis only ſomewhat reſulting from ſin, as it regards the <hi>penal
part</hi> of the Law, which is the thing the <hi>learned</hi> generally mean by
<hi>Guilt;</hi> and if not fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough expreſs'd by <hi>Guilt,</hi> or by
<hi>Reatus,</hi> by what Engliſh or Latin term can it be better made known?
'Tis a liableneſs, or an obnoxiouſneſs unto puniſhment: To be Guilty,
is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, q. d
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, qui reus eſt poenae à
Judice definitae, or propriè obnoxius è re judicata, obnoxious to
the puniſhment for<pb n="v" facs="tcp:34827:73"/>ſome fault, which as it is a
liableneſs unto <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> may be called <hi>Reatus poenae,</hi>
but as 'tis <hi>ſuch</hi> a liableneſs <hi>propter culpam,</hi> it may be
called <hi>Reatus culpae;</hi> But if any of the learned will ſay, that there
is 1. <hi>Reatus Facti.</hi> 2. <hi>Reatus Culpae.</hi> And 3. <hi>Reatus
Poenae,</hi> diſtinct from each other, and mean 1. That the <hi>Fact is
done.</hi> 2. That <hi>this Fact</hi> is a breach of the Law. 3. That he that
did this <hi>Fact</hi> is by the Law to be puniſhed; ſince by <hi>Reatus
culpae,</hi> as much ſeems to be intended as the <hi>ſin itſelf,</hi> the
<hi>breach of the Law,</hi> although ſuch learned perſons may uſe their
own freedom, yet it muſt be duly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred that in their ſenſe, I do
<hi>not aſſert,</hi> That <hi>Reatus Culpae,</hi> (i.e.) the ſin itſelf
<hi>formally</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, is laid on Chriſt; but the <hi>Reatus
Culpae,</hi> (i.e.) the <hi>Guilt,</hi> which is ſomewhat diſtinct, and
ſeparable from the <hi>Fault itſelf,</hi> is laid on Chriſt; for, I
underſtand by <hi>Guilt</hi> (call it <hi>Guilt</hi> of <hi>Fault,</hi> or
<hi>Puniſhment</hi>) an obnoxiouſneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wrath for ſome fault, which
is ſomewhat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the fault itſelf. But moreover,</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>Guilt,</hi> I mean the <hi>Guilt of the
Fault,</hi> is diſtinct from the <hi>Fault itſelf,</hi> is evident, in that
it may be on ſuch as never <hi>really</hi> committed the actual ſin, or did
the fault, for thus it was with reference unto the guilt of <hi>Adam</hi>'s
ſin, which is really the <hi>Guilt</hi> of his <hi>Poſterity,</hi> who are
ſuch as have not <hi>actually,</hi> and in a <hi>proper ſenſe really
ſinned.</hi> We did not actually ſin in <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:34827:74"/>and yet the <hi>guilt</hi> of his actual ſin is ſo much
<hi>ours,</hi> that we are <hi>juſtly</hi> puniſhed for it: What more
evident than that the <hi>corruption of nature,</hi> which we receive with our
Beings, is <hi>penal,</hi> a <hi>juſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,</hi> which
neceſſarily preſuppoſeth <hi>Guilt,</hi> which Guilt muſt be the
<hi>reſult</hi> of ſome <hi>anteceding ſin,</hi> but ſince 'tis
impoſſible it ſhould be the <hi>reſult</hi> of any ſin that hath been
<hi>really,</hi> and in a proper ſenſe actually committed by us, it muſt
be for the ſin of our firſt Parent; which being ſo, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there may be <hi>real Guilt</hi> on him, who hath
not <hi>really,</hi> in a proper ſenſe ſinned, and therefore to ſay
<hi>He is guilty,</hi> is not as much as to ſay, <hi>He hath really committed
the fault.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Guilt</hi> of the <hi>Fault,</hi> or a
<hi>liableneſs to puniſhment</hi> for <hi>ſin</hi> may be on him, in whom
the actual ſin, the <hi>foundation</hi> of that <hi>Guilt</hi> is not: For it
muſt be acknowledged, that 'tis <hi>naturally impoſſible,</hi> that
<hi>Adam</hi>'s actual ſin ſhould paſs from him to us, and yet nothing
more true than that the <hi>guilt</hi> of the ſame <hi>actual ſin</hi> is
made <hi>our guilt,</hi> and we are as liable to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the eye of
<hi>God,</hi> the <hi>righteous Judge,</hi> as if we had actually, and in a
proper ſenſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ſin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>guilt</hi> of our ſin, the <hi>guilt of
our fault,</hi> which I humbly conceive is beſt expreſs'd by the Latine
<hi>Reatus Culpae,</hi> may paſs from us to Chriſt, even when the ſin, or
fault itſelf doth not, or rather <hi>cannot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="vii" facs="tcp:34827:74"/>4. The reaſon, why I ſo much
inſiſt on this diſtinction between the <hi>formal nature of ſin,</hi>
and <hi>guilt,</hi> is, becauſe of that <hi>light,</hi> we may thereby
receive in order to our <hi>clearer comprehending the fundamental
miſtakes</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> about <hi>Juſtif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> who
ſometime inſiſting on <hi>guilt,</hi> as the <hi>formal nature</hi> of
ſin, underſtand by <hi>remiſſion of ſin,</hi> the
<hi>Mortification</hi> thereof, and by <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
Sanctification.</hi> Whence we may perceive, on what ground that <hi>Reverend
Biſhop</hi> Dr. <hi>Uſher</hi> told a perſon of great worth and learning,
from whom I had it, <hi>That</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> did not hold any
ſuch thing as the <hi>pardon of ſin, diſtinct from the mortification of
ſin,</hi> (if I miſtake not.) For if the guilt be the ſame with the ſin
itſelf, remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere <hi>peccatum,</hi> or the <hi>removing guilt</hi> can be
but the deſtroying the <hi>formal nature of ſin,</hi> the ſin itſelf,
and conſequently pardon of ſin the ſame with mortification. Again, the
<hi>Papiſts,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering <hi>guilt</hi> as the <hi>Formale
Peccati,</hi> do with the greateſt confidence conclude, that
<hi>Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> being <hi>pardoned in the Regenerate,</hi> the
<hi>guilt</hi> thereof removed, the <hi>formal nature</hi> thereof is
<hi>gone,</hi> and 'tis no more <hi>formally ſin in them.</hi> But ſince,
the <hi>ſin formally</hi> conſidered is ſomewhat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from the
<hi>guilt</hi> thereof, (as I have proved in the preceding diſcourſe) the
<hi>ground</hi> of theſe <hi>Popiſh miſtakes</hi> is detected; and that
which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows is a great Truth inſiſted on, <hi>viz. The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference there
is between Holineſs and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> 
               <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:34827:75"/>for
<hi>as ſin</hi> regards the <hi>preceptive part of the Law,</hi> even
<hi>ſo</hi> doth <hi>Holineſs;</hi> the <hi>former</hi> being a
<hi>diſconformity,</hi> the <hi>latter</hi> a <hi>conformity</hi> thereunto:
And as the immediate <hi>reſult of ſin</hi> with reference to the
<hi>retributive</hi> part of the Law is <hi>Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs,</hi> even
ſo <hi>contrarily</hi> the immediate <hi>reſult</hi> of <hi>Holineſs</hi>
is <hi>Righteouſneſs:</hi> the one <hi>Dignitas poenae propter
inobedientiam,</hi> the other <hi>Dignitas praemii propter obedientiam;</hi>
for <hi>contrariorum eadem eſt ratio:</hi> Which being ſo, we eaſily may
ſee <hi>how</hi> our <hi>ſin</hi> is <hi>imputed</hi> unto Chriſt in its
<hi>guilt,</hi> even when <hi>ſin formally conſidered</hi> is not laid on
him. Yea, and <hi>how Chriſt's obedience</hi> is made ours in its
<hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> when the <hi>formal, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jective</hi> Holineſs
of Chriſt is not.</p>
            <p n="2">§ 2. I have introduced <hi>Maeratius</hi> as one, who
diſtinguiſheth inter <hi>Reatum culpae</hi> &amp; <hi>poenae,</hi> though I
have not, as yet, found him to be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs</hi> in his doing ſo; but,
the reaſon, which prompted me to ſingle out this <hi>Schoolman,</hi> is his
diſtinguiſhing <hi>inter dignitatem poenae,</hi> &amp; <hi>obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem ad
poenam,</hi> which is the ſame that <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> intends by the
<hi>Guilt</hi> of the <hi>Fault,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> of the
<hi>Puniſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">§ 3. In order to a fuller vindicating the
<hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans,</hi> I humbly conceive it neceſſary to ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, that
<hi>they,</hi> in their oppoſing <hi>Peter de Aliaco,</hi> who judg'd the
<hi>ſecond cauſe</hi> to be no <hi>proper</hi>
               <pb n="ix" facs="tcp:34827:75"/>cauſe,
[it not being the fire that burns, but God in the fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] do
aſſert the <hi>ſecond cauſe</hi> to be a <hi>proper,</hi> though not a
<hi>ſolitary cauſe.</hi> This I prove out of <hi>Molina</hi> himſelf,
who, although he is no way a lover of the <hi>Dominican Dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta;</hi> yet doth
aſſert, that <hi>Aquinas</hi> the great <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
Predeterminant,</hi> doth regard the notion of <hi>Pet. de Aliaco</hi> as
<hi>fooliſh,</hi> and as what <hi>contradicts</hi> a general experience, and
our common ſenſe, it being more abſurd than the Notion of <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius
Cordubenſis</hi> and <hi>Abailardus,</hi> that is followed by ſome of the
Nominals, to which <hi>Scotus</hi> (as <hi>Molina</hi> ſaith) gave too great
countenance, even when it cannot be ſaid that the <hi>Phyſical
Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminants</hi> did ſo. <hi>Molina</hi> in primum Th. q. 14. Art. 13.
diſ. 1,2,3, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">§ 4. In this laſt Chapter I have alſo inſiſted
on the report the <hi>Schoolmen make</hi> of things, ſhewing into what
<hi>Paſſions an eſpouſed intereſt did anciently drive men.</hi> For
<hi>Bellarmine</hi> aſſerts <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randus</hi> to have been a <hi>Follower
of Pelagius,</hi> but how truly, let the learned judge; for, although I have
mention'd it, I think my ſelf no way ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to believe it. Again, the
ſame <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth prove, that <hi>Durandus</hi> himſelf makes
<hi>God to be the Author of Sin;</hi> but if ſo, how is it poſſible that
what <hi>Le Blanc</hi> ſaith ſhould be true, when he aſſerts it to be
the ſenſe of <hi>all,</hi> that if <hi>Durandus</hi> be in the right, as to
this point,<pb n="x" facs="tcp:34827:76"/>there will be <hi>no difficulty</hi> in clearing
God from the but-now-mentioned reproach: But what is the more ſurprizing is
this, That <hi>Bellarmine</hi> hereby doth but revile his own Notion, if the
learned Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (who is well acquainted with the Schoolmen) doth
not miſtake;
<q rend="inline">"For, ſaith he, I do verily believe that
<hi>Durandus</hi> and his Followers, under the name of ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the
<hi>Natural,</hi> and <hi>Free Faculties</hi> did mean <hi>incluſively,</hi>
that which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> pleadeth for, <hi>A general concourſe to the
Act as an Act.</hi> And that they differ in words, not in ſenſe."</q> Thus
the Learned ſpend their time in contradicting themſelves as well as one
another.</p>
            <p n="5">§ 5. I have moreover inſiſted on the different
apprehenſions the <hi>old Philoſophers</hi> entertain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe
<hi>inſuperable</hi> difficulties that are about <hi>Predetermination,</hi>
&amp;c. thereby to intimate, that the <hi>confident Schoolmen,</hi> and their
ſeveral Sectators, do but <hi>actum agere,</hi> and conſume their
ſtrength on <hi>needleſs Controverſies,</hi> to the great diſadvantage
of true Religion. <hi>Theſe</hi> acting in <hi>Divinity,</hi> as our
<hi>Virtuoſi</hi> do in <hi>Philoſophy, who,</hi> by a zealous attempt to
eſtabliſh their new <hi>dogmata</hi> (as they call them) do not walk in any
untrod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den paths; The <hi>Copernican Hypotheſis</hi> about the <hi>motion of
the Earth,</hi> as alſo the <hi>learned Fancies</hi> about the
<hi>Earth,</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants</hi> that are ſaid to be in the Moon, as
well as that <hi>ſolid Truth</hi> about<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:34827:76"/>the
<hi>Antipodes,</hi> ſo much reproached by <hi>Lactantius,</hi> were all known
in <hi>Cicero</hi>'s, if not in <hi>Plato</hi>'s, or <hi>Pythagoras</hi>'s
dayes. For this, conſult Cicero. Quaeſt. Acad. l. 2.
<q rend="inline">"Habitari ait <hi>Xenophanes</hi> in
<hi>Luna,</hi> eamque eſſe <hi>terram multarum urbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> &amp;
<hi>montium.</hi> Portenta videntur: ſed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men neque ille qui dixit jurare
poſſet ita ſe rem habere, neque ego. Nonne etiam dicitis, eſſe
è <hi>regione</hi> nobis, è <hi>contraria parte terrae,</hi> qui
<hi>adverſis veſtigiis ſtent contra veſtigia noſtra,</hi> quos
<hi>Antipodas</hi> vocatis? Cur mihi magis ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſetis, qui iſta non
aſpernor, quam eis, qui quum audiunt, deſipere vos arbitrantur?
<hi>Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Syracuſius,</hi> ut ait <hi>Theophraſtus, Coelum, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,
Lunam, Stellas, ſupera denique omnia ſtare</hi> cenſet, <hi>neque praeter
terram rem ullam in mundo moveri:</hi> quae cùm circum axem <hi>ſe
ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma celeritate convertat,</hi> &amp; <hi>torqueat, eâdem</hi> effici
omnia, quae ſi <hi>ſtante terra, Coelum moveretur.</hi> Atque hoc etiam
<hi>Platonem</hi> in <hi>Timaeo</hi> dicere quidam arbitrantur, ſed
paulò obſcuriùs."</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus both our <hi>New Philoſophers,</hi> and the <hi>Old
Schoolmen,</hi> do but trace the <hi>Ancient Heathen</hi> in their particular
Fancies, concerning things not only <hi>unreveal'd,</hi> but moreover, too
<hi>high</hi> for vain Mortals to reach unto. The <hi>New Philoſophers</hi>
confidently ſolve, as they ſay, the <hi>inſolvable Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena</hi> in
the <hi>Natural</hi> world; and the <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> with no leſs
boldneſs overcome (at leaſt in their own conceit) the invincible
difficulties in<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:34827:77"/>the <hi>Moral.</hi> The <hi>New
Philoſophers</hi> can (if you will believe 'em) acquaint you with the
parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>methods</hi> of God in <hi>creating</hi> and
<hi>conſerving</hi> all Beings, ſhewing <hi>How,</hi> or after what
particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar manner every natural effect is produc'd; and the <hi>Schoolmen</hi>
are as expreſs in demonſtrating the <hi>particular modes</hi> of Divine
concourſe, not only unto every <hi>good,</hi> but alſo unto every
<hi>ſinful Action;</hi> though ſtill it muſt be aſſerted, that the
<hi>difficulties</hi> which occur unto both in theſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, are moſt
certainly uncapable of a <hi>clear, diſtinct,</hi> and <hi>ſatisfying</hi>
Solution; for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the <hi>vanity</hi> of each in their
<hi>Eſſays,</hi> is equally to be neglected; for the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> are
as vain, and conſequently as liable unto juſt rebukes, as are the <hi>New
Philoſophers;</hi> Do the <hi>New Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> revive the old
<hi>Dogmata</hi> of the Heathen? ſo do the <hi>Schoolmen:</hi> Do the <hi>New
Philoſophers</hi> diſturb the world with their learned Folly? ſo do the
<hi>Schoolmen.</hi> And muſt the <hi>New Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher</hi> be ſeverely
checkt for his <hi>Preſumption</hi> in <hi>Philoſophy?</hi> then ſurely,
much more <hi>ſo</hi> muſt the <hi>Schoolman</hi> for his <hi>greater
confidence</hi> in <hi>Divinity.</hi> For, might <hi>Divinity</hi> be freed
from the <hi>perplexing abuſes</hi> of theſe Schoolmen, as every <hi>other
Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> even ſo <hi>this</hi> of <hi>Free-grace</hi> in all the great
inſtances thereof, would ſuddenly appear to the view of the Vulgar,
affording them the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying comforts and ſpiritual advantages
deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:34827:77"/>§ 6. In the Cloſe of all,
'twill be neceſſary, that in order to the undeceiving the <hi>weak,</hi> I
do evince, that the Doctrines I aſſert are according to the Holy
Scriptures, as moſt rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the generality of our
<hi>Proteſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines;</hi> not only the <hi>Calviniſt</hi> beyond the
Seas, but alſo the <hi>Reformed Divines</hi> at home, <hi>viz.</hi> The
<hi>Church of England,</hi> and the <hi>Nonconformiſt,</hi> whether
<hi>Presbyterian,</hi> or <hi>Congregational:</hi> which, concerning the great
<hi>Doctrine</hi> about our actual juſtification in the ſight of God by
Faith in Chriſt's blood, I'll particularly evince, and the rather, becauſe
'tis the practice of <hi>Deceivers</hi> to draw <hi>Proſelytes</hi> to their
<hi>Errors,</hi> by repreſenting the <hi>Truth</hi> they oppoſe, as what is
either <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſm, Socinianiſm,</hi> or <hi>Popery;</hi> and the
<hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> they eſpouſe, as what is the true <hi>Proteſtant
Doctrine,</hi> whereby ſuch as are juſtly haters of the abovementioned
Errors, and lovers of the Proteſtant Truths, are tempted, for this
<hi>ſingle reaſon,</hi> to abandon the <hi>Truth,</hi> and entertain an
<hi>Error</hi> in its ſtead.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the <hi>Church of England</hi> (who cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly are
truly <hi>Scriptural,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> in this great Doctrine
about <hi>Juſtification by Faith</hi>) do in their <hi>Articles,</hi> and
Book of <hi>Homilies</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with me, is evident to any that ſhall,
without prejudice, peruſe them. Yea, <hi>this Church</hi> is ſo
<pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:34827:78"/>zealouſly concern'd for the eſtabliſhing this Truth,
[<hi>viz.</hi> Our Juſtification by Faith in Chriſt's blood, and
conſequently that none of the Elect are actually in God's ſight
juſtified, while under the reigning power of unbelief, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]
that, whoever will receive any advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges from <hi>her,</hi> muſt ſo
chearfully <hi>aſſent</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> thereunto, that 'tis
become impoſſible, that <hi>any of</hi> her Sons <hi>honeſtly</hi> recede
from it; yea, they muſt be <hi>ſo expreſs</hi> in their profeſſion,
that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a <hi>Popiſh diſtinction</hi> can be ſubtile enough to
extricate their Conſciences from the <hi>bonds</hi> into which by
<hi>Conformity,</hi> they have brought themſelves: Whence many ſober
<hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Divines,</hi> whoſe <hi>Principles</hi> are really
<hi>Proteſtant,</hi> [or which is the ſame, <hi>truly Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi>]
cannot but be fill'd with a kind of horror and aſtoniſhment, to obſerve,
how far ſome of the zealous Sons of the Church have receded from this
Doctrine. The truth of this is to be found in that <hi>learned,</hi> and
<hi>once dignified Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Divine</hi> Doctor <hi>Tully,</hi> in his Book
<hi>de Juſtif. Paulin. c.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 23. where he ſaith—<q rend="inline">"Quippe vehementer non <hi>mihi</hi> ſolum,
ſed aliis <hi>quamplurimis</hi> mirari ſubit, quâ vel
obſcuriſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ rationis umbrâ, quâ ſe defendant
vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundiâ, qui ſe Eccleſiae Anglicanae <hi>Filios,</hi> etiam
<hi>obſequentiſſimos</hi> dici volunt, quique ut <hi>tales, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu,</hi>
&amp; <hi>fide</hi> data toties in illius doctrinam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſum formaverint,
cum eâ nihilominus <hi>bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:34827:78"/>apertè
gerant.</hi>"</q> But the Doctors wonder is heightned, when he reflects on the
35th <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle</hi> about <hi>Homilies,</hi> amongſt which, that of
<hi>Juſtification</hi> is one, aſſented and conſented unto by ſome,
who in their Writings and Diſcourſes fully ſhew, that they
<hi>conſent</hi> to <hi>no ſuch</hi> thing. But if the <hi>Doctor</hi> had
but call'd to mind the <hi>Paraphraſe</hi> of <hi>Franciſc. à Sancta
Clara</hi> on this mention'd 35th Article <hi>de Homiliis,</hi> the ſurprize
might, at leaſt in ſome meaſure, be removed: for that this Popiſh
<hi>Caſuist</hi> aſſures them, that they may give in both their
<hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> unto <hi>every Homily,</hi> as to
what contains <hi>both god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>wholſom Doctrines,</hi> even when
they do <hi>not conſent</hi> unto <hi>the whole</hi> thereof <hi>as
ſuch:</hi> and his reaſons are prodigiouſly ſtrong, [<hi>i.e.</hi> to
ſuch as deſign an eſpouſing Popery, when 'tis their intereſt to do
ſo,] it being agreeable to the ſentiments of ſeveral <hi>Popiſh
Doctors,</hi> which is ſufficient to make the <hi>greatest
impoſſibilities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Probable.</hi> Conſider how particular, and
expreſs ſuch are, as do Conform, in the giving in their <hi>Aſſent</hi>
and <hi>Conſent,</hi> and what <hi>Franciſc. à Sancta Clara</hi>'s
Paraphraſe is, and you cannot but be convinced, that as to this I am in the
right. The ſentiments of <hi>Franciſc. à Sancta Clara,</hi> are as
follows—<q rend="inline">"Nec tenentur Proteſtantes ob haec verba in
Articulo ſtatim in <hi>ſingula verba,</hi> vel <hi>ſententias
Homiliarum</hi> jurare; nam ut olim <hi>Turrecremata,</hi> cum ipſa
Eccleſia Doctorum <pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:34827:79"/>aliquorum opuſcula probat, non ob id
intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum eſt, <hi>omnia in eis contenta probari.</hi> Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut in
conſtitutionibus 6 Synodi, aliquorum Doctorum opera probata ſunt, quod
etiam in decretis legitur, diſt. 15. <hi>non</hi> tamen <hi>omnia verba &amp;
particulas approbat,</hi> ut conveniunt <hi>Doctores.</hi> Hoc etiam
exactiſſimè tradunt <hi>Doctores Pariſienſes,</hi> exponentes
Bullam Urba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni quinti approbantem doctrinam S. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae, in qua ſcripſit
<hi>Tholoſanis, ejus doctrinam,</hi> ut <hi>bene dictam,</hi> &amp;
<hi>catholicam teneri debere.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt tamen <hi>Pariſienſes,</hi>
praedictam approbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem non eſſe <hi>univerſalem,</hi> ſed tanquam
doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae utilis, &amp; in <hi>multis</hi> probabilis; prudenter igitur quae
ſanam doctrinam ſapiunt, populo legenda, alia, neglectui habenda."</q> So
far <hi>Franc. à Sancta Clara.</hi> But to return. It muſt be
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that the <hi>Church of England</hi> is ſo <hi>Orthodox</hi> in
this great doctrine about <hi>Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that the greateſt
<hi>Sophiſtry</hi> of either her open Enemies, or pretended Friends, who
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs themſelves to be Her moſt obedient Sons, can never with the
leaſt colour of reaſon evince the contrary.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> alſo, are as
<hi>right</hi> in <hi>this,</hi> whence whatever any particular perſon among
them may aſſert, 'tis the judgment of the generality, whether
<hi>Presbyterian</hi> or <hi>Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> That <hi>our Juſtification
is by Faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſt's<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:34827:79"/>blood:</hi> and
conſequently our actual juſtification in God's ſight, doth not
<hi>precede,</hi> but <hi>follow Faith.</hi> That the <hi>Presbyterians</hi>
are right in this is acknowledged by <hi>ſome,</hi> who aſſert the
<hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational</hi> (notwithſtanding their profeſſed own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the
<hi>Presbyterians</hi> Confeſſion of Faith) to be <hi>Antinomian,</hi> of
which I do the rather take ſome notice, becauſe in an eſpecial manner
<hi>ſuch,</hi> as are of <hi>that Error,</hi> attempt the countenancing it,
by ſaying, that 'tis <hi>embraced by the Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal;</hi> than which
nothing more <hi>untrue,</hi> as may be evinced by a due peruſal of the
<hi>Declaration of their Faith,</hi> agreed and conſented unto by their
<hi>Elders</hi> and <hi>Meſſengers</hi> in their meeting at the
<hi>Savoy,</hi> Octob. 12. 1658. And might the world be ſo happy, as to ſee
a very <hi>Elaborate Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> written by
a very acute and ſolid Perſon, a great Diſputant, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr.
<hi>Stone</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> a Congregational Divine, it would
eaſily appear, that the <hi>Congregational are not</hi> Antinomian. However,
although this <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent MS.</hi> hath not ſeen the light, yet another
<hi>Treatiſe,</hi> whoſe worth is much above my Applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, hath, namely;
That of the <hi>Reverend Doctor Owen,</hi> about <hi>Juſtification;</hi>
which diſcourſe, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in it the ſame Truths, on which I have
inſiſted are particularly aſſerted, yet) hath given ſuch
ſatisfaction to the generality of the <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational,</hi> that
<hi>they</hi> cannot but judge themſelves<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:34827:80"/>greatly
indebted unto the <hi>learned Author</hi> for that ſpecial ſervice
<hi>he</hi> hath therein done the Churches; whence 'tis become impoſſible,
that any unprejudiced perſon ſhould <hi>conſult</hi> the but now
mentioned diſcourſe, and <hi>believe</hi> that in it he finds the
<hi>ſentiments</hi> of the <hi>Congregational,</hi> and yet
<hi>honeſtly</hi> aſſert, the <hi>Congregational to be Antinomian,</hi>
and Abettors of the Errors I op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: For who, without a running into the
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Extreme, can be more expreſs in rejecting the <hi>Antinomian
Error,</hi> than the Doctor is in the mentioned Treatiſe; for therein he
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The neceſſity of <hi>Faith,</hi> as
<hi>antecedent</hi> to our actual Juſtification in God's ſight.</item>
               <item>2. That <hi>this</hi> Faith includeth in its nature the
entire principle of <hi>Evangelical Repentance,</hi> ſo as that it is utterly
impoſſible, that a man ſhould be a <hi>true Believer,</hi> and not at the
ſame inſtant of time be <hi>truly penitent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. That <hi>conviction</hi> of ſin is a <hi>neceſſary
ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent</hi> unto this juſtifying Faith.</item>
               <item>4. That nothing but the <hi>Guilt</hi> and
<hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of Sin was laid on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it being
im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that the Sin itſelf, <hi>formally</hi> conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:34827:80"/>or the <hi>Fault</hi> itſelf, as diſtinct from the
<hi>Guilt</hi> and Puniſhment of Sin, ſhould be laid on
<hi>him.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe things being ſo, nothing more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly true, than
that, as the Errors I oppoſe are diſcountenanced by the <hi>generality</hi>
of the <hi>learned</hi> and <hi>judicious Proteſtant,</hi> even ſo, it
high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerns all ſuch, as would adhere unto <hi>the</hi> Proteſtant
Doctrines, to <hi>beware,</hi> how they cloſe with the contrary Errors,
concerning which, I would the rather <hi>Caution</hi> the
<hi>well-meaning,</hi> but <hi>weak Chriſtian,</hi> for theſe following
Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The aſſerting the <hi>Filth</hi> of Sin, as 'tis
ſomewhat diſtinct both from the <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of
Sin, to have been laid on Chriſt, doth not only <hi>expoſe</hi> our
bleſſed Lord and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer to the worſt of Reproaches, but wholly
incapacitate him for the accompliſhing fallen man's ſalvation. For if our
<hi>Faults</hi> or <hi>Sins</hi> be made <hi>Chriſts,</hi> then Chriſt
muſt have ſuffered for his <hi>own Sins,</hi> whereby he would have been
made uncapable of ſuffering for <hi>ours;</hi> yea, and whereby he would have
<hi>needed</hi> daily to have offered for his own Sins <hi>firſt,</hi>
contrary to that in <hi>Hebrews</hi> 7.27. But,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="xx" facs="tcp:34827:81"/>2. The concluding the <hi>Fault</hi> and
<hi>Guilt</hi> to be the <hi>ſame</hi> thing, or which is much the ſame,
the <hi>Guilt</hi> to be the <hi>formal nature</hi> of Sin, as it is a Notion
attended with the Abſurdities but now hinted, if it be ſaid to be laid on
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> even ſo, it is moreover but in order to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troducing
ſeveral <hi>dangerouſly Popiſh Errors,</hi> viz. the <hi>making
Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Sanctification</hi> the <hi>ſame,
Remiſſion</hi> and <hi>Mortification</hi> of Sin one thing; from all which
'twill follow, that if <hi>Original</hi> Sin, or <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> and
<hi>Lust</hi> be pardoned in the <hi>Regenerate,</hi> the <hi>formal
nature</hi> of Sin is removed; and although there remain the <hi>matter,</hi>
and the <hi>name</hi> of Sin, yet 'tis not <hi>formally Sin.</hi> After this
manner doth <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> himſelf argue de Amiſſ. grat. &amp;
ſtat. pec. l. 5. c. 7. lit. C. Primum enim ſi verè crede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
adverſarii <hi>Reatum</hi> dimitti in Baptiſmo, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri deberent
conſequenter, <hi>nihil</hi> eſſe in renatis quod habeat <hi>veram
peccati rationem.</hi>—And why, but becauſe this <hi>Bellarmme</hi>
doth with <hi>Phil. Melancthon</hi> conſider <hi>Guilt</hi> as the
<hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Peccati,</hi> (i.e.) the <hi>Guilt</hi> and the <hi>Fault</hi>
itſelf, or the <hi>formal nature</hi> of Sin to be the <hi>ſame,</hi>
whence, ſaith <hi>He,</hi>
               <q rend="inline">"Sublatâ rei for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ, non manet ejus
rei ratio, ſive natura, cum forma ſit praecipua pars naturae, imo ſit
<hi>ipſa ratio</hi> &amp; <hi>quidditas</hi> rei."</q> And really
<hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi>'s <pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:34827:81"/>Reply is very feeble.
<hi>Beware</hi> then of ſuch, as pretend high for the <hi>Proteſtant
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, who</hi> yet revile <hi>Conforming,</hi> and <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforming
Proteſtants;</hi> and, <hi>who</hi> ſeem to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the <hi>Guilt</hi>
of Sin, and the <hi>formal nature</hi> thereof, to be the ſame, for that, by
ſuch an <hi>unjust procedure,</hi> none but the <hi>Papiſts</hi> can be any
way advantaged.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The aſſerting the Elect, <hi>quatenus,</hi> or <hi>as
Elect,</hi> to be pardoned in the womb, and to be freed from the <hi>Filth of
Sin,</hi> by Chriſt's taking it on himſelf, is a Doctrine that
coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances the worſt of Villanies. For if I actually am <hi>pardoned,</hi>
in that I am <hi>Elect,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I remain under the power of the worſt
of Sins, what need I be any otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned about the ſalvation of my
Soul? What need I examine my heart, ſearch for ſin, mourn over it, pray,
and hear the Word, or abſtain from any Debaucheries, for that, if I received
not a <hi>Pardon</hi> with my <hi>Being,</hi> I ſhall never gain it? But if I
<hi>then</hi> received it, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more requiſite, than that I
confidently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade my ſelf that it is ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For theſe Reaſons,</hi> we may eaſily perceive the
neceſſity there is, that ſuch as deſign the glory of God in the
ſalvation of their own<pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:34827:82"/>ſouls, <hi>Take heed,</hi> how
they forſake the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant,</hi> which is the <hi>Goſpel
Doctrine,</hi> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>two,</hi> or <hi>three,</hi> [an
<hi>inconſiderable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>] in entertaining Notions, which, if
<hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally obſerv'd</hi> in their <hi>Principles</hi> and
<hi>Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> cannot but prove their eternal Ruine. I ſay, if
<hi>practically obſerved</hi> both in their <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> and
<hi>Conſequences,</hi> becauſe I hope, that through a ſpecial inſtance
of infinitely <hi>FREE GRACE,</hi> the <hi>Hearts</hi> of ſome, whoſe
<hi>heads</hi> have been filled with theſe Principles I oppoſe, have been
<hi>ſo</hi> averſe from a practical cloſure with the diſmal
<hi>conſequences</hi> that attend them, as to be freed from the miſchiefs
that otherwiſe they would have fallen into. But, although <hi>ſome,</hi> by
an aſtoniſhing inſtance of Divine Bounty, may be preſerved, and
conſequently, although a <hi>few good men</hi> have <hi>embraced</hi> this
Error in the <hi>Notion,</hi> when they have <hi>hated</hi> it in the
<hi>Practice;</hi> yet, 'tis <hi>unſafe,</hi> and really dangerous ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
on ſuch hazards; for, although <hi>One</hi> may eſcape the Contagion, yet
<hi>thou</hi> may'ſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to thy greater damage. For the Lord's
ſake therefore conſider what thou doeſt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor, that thou
may'ſt be both <hi>ſound</hi> in thy <hi>Notions,</hi> and alſo in thy
<hi>Practices,</hi> for thereby thou wilt be in a better capacity of giving
<hi>God</hi> the greater glory, to the <hi>praiſe</hi> of infinitely <hi>FREE
GRACE.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:34827:82"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Page 18. line 19. for <hi>ſhal,</hi> read
<hi>ſhould.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 19. in the uſes ſet before l. 13.1. and l. 16. for 3.
r. 2.</item>
               <item>P. 22. l. 19. for 13. r. 16. for 5. r. 2.</item>
               <item>P. 27. l. 2. for <hi>ſit,</hi> r. <hi>ſint.</hi> l. 3.
after <hi>obligatio,</hi> r. <hi>poenae.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 28. l. 12. <hi>dele</hi> who.</item>
               <item>P. 33. l. 10. for <hi>formerly,</hi> r.
<hi>formally.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 35. l. 26. after <hi>that,</hi> r. <hi>as.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 72. l. 15. for <hi>proves,</hi> r. <hi>prove.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 79. l. 18. after <hi>pene,</hi> r. <hi>verbis.</hi> l. 19.
for <hi>q.</hi> 4. r. <hi>q.</hi> 14. and for 9. r. <hi>q<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 87. l. 19. for 12. r. 2.</item>
               <item>P. 88. l. 22. for <hi>qu.</hi> 5. r. <hi>qu.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>P. 97. l. 5. r. <hi>art.</hi> 3. for <hi>lect.</hi> r.
<hi>relect.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 101. l. 20. for <hi>excellently,</hi> r.
<hi>excellent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pag. 2. line 26. (in the Appendix) after <hi>to,</hi> r.
<hi>be.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
